<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>norswap</title>
    <description></description>
    <link>http://norswap.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://norswap.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Essence of Blockchains</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;What are blockchains for? Why are they useful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I contend that the essence of blockchain is that they are decentralized trust
engines.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Decentralized trust has a lot of benefits, but the one I&amp;#39;m personally excited
about is that it enables &lt;strong&gt;permissionless innovation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below I explain what the hell I mean by &lt;em&gt;decentralized trust&lt;/em&gt; and
&lt;em&gt;permissionless innovation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;who-do-you-trust&quot;&gt;Who do you trust?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever you perform some action online, you&amp;#39;re always implicitly trusting some
entity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, if you run a computation on Amazon Web Service (AWS), or even in
Google Sheets, you trust Amazon and Google not to alter the result of the
computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you host files on Dropbox, you trust Dropbox not to alter their content, and
to not arbitrarily destroy your backup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You trust that Google won&amp;#39;t return you completely fabricated search result to
get you to take some specific decision (e.g. a purchase) that is in their
interest. (They certainly influence search results, but they don&amp;#39;t (yet?)
fabricate them.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You trust that your bank won&amp;#39;t take your money. You trust that your insurer will
actually compensate you in case of accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might also trust all of these companies with the privacy of your data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Etc, etc...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might object that these companies won&amp;#39;t do these shady things. They stand to
lose a lot, including reputation, customers, future revenues, etc! As for banks
and insurances, they are heavily regulated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s true — although I will say these companies have gotten away with a
surprising number of things. But more importantly it means you can only deal
with entities that either (a) have something to lose or (b) comply with draconic
and time-consuming regulations — and mostly that means big entrenched companies.
We&amp;#39;ll explore this when we talk about &lt;em&gt;permissionless innovation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also consider that companies might be &lt;em&gt;forced&lt;/em&gt; to do something, probably by some
government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;decentralized-trust&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Decentralized&amp;quot; trust?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fundamental proposition of blockchains is the following: &lt;strong&gt;What if you did
not have to trust a single entity, a single company?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In blockchains, there is a network of &lt;em&gt;nodes&lt;/em&gt; (aka &lt;em&gt;verifiers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;validators&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;stakers&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;miners&lt;/em&gt;, ...) that verify the operations of the blockchains. As long
as a majority of these nodes are honest (e.g. 50% of them, this changes between
blockchains), you can trust that anything that happens on the blockchain follows
the rules of the blockchain. And dishonesty has dire consequences for validators
— because of sunk costs, or because of explicit penalties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This changes your trust assumption from trusting a single entity to trusting
that a majority of validators are honest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more validators there are, the less collusion is likely. Said otherwise, the
more decentralized the system is, the less trust you need to put in the system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is also of paramount importance that anyone be able to become a validator of
the network. Otherwise, the network is really controlled by the gatekeeper of
the validation rights. This is less easy than it sounds — you have to make
validation costly enough, otherwise an attacker could just spin a huge number of
nodes and take over the network — a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sybil_attack&quot;&gt;sybil attack&lt;/a&gt;. Preventing sybil attacks is
the main technical breakthrough of blockchain technology. I explain the
solutions (proof-of-work and proof-of-stake) in my article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/blockchain-how&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Freaking
blockchains: How do they work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;applications--trade-offs&quot;&gt;Applications &amp;amp; Trade-Offs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s go back to our examples. Am I saying that blockchains will supersede AWS,
Google Sheet, Google Search, Dropbox, banks and insurances?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not necessarily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, there is a trade-off. Nothing is truly trustless or riskless.
Running most web apps on AWS is really fine, because the risk that Amazon is
going to manipulate your results is close to zero, and the downside if they do
is very low. Even if you&amp;#39;re running with a brand-new competitor, you&amp;#39;re not
risking all that much.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for some applications, trust and security are a really big deal. In
particular, where money is concerned. It&amp;#39;s not by accident that finance is
stringently regulated. And similarly, it&amp;#39;s not an accident that most popular
applications of blockchains right now deal with money. It&amp;#39;s doubly important
when you&amp;#39;re dealing with anonymous blockchain developers with no pre-existing
reputation (more on this in the section on permissionless innovation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--

Since we mentionned Dropbox, I will mention there are a few blockchains
specialized in storage, like [Arweave] and [Filecoin]. These are very useful if
censorship is a concern ([example][hong-kong]).

Privacy-wise, blockchains are not there yet, at least for computation. In most
blockchain, transactions are public! It&#39;s already possible the hide the
transactions using [zero-knowledge proofs][zkp], however the resulting
blockchain state modification is public. you are only &quot;protected&quot; by the
pseudonimity of your blockchain address, but that is a weak kind of protection.
This is a topic of ongoing research.

[Arweave]: https://www.arweave.org/
[Filecoin]: https://filecoin.io/
[hong-kong]: https://www.reuters.com/article/us-hongkong-security-apple-daily-blockch-idCAKCN2E00JP
[zkp]: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-knowledge_proof

--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;permissionless-innovation&quot;&gt;Permissionless Innovation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we come to what is to me the most exciting consequence of decentralized
trust: &lt;em&gt;permissionless innovation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On computation-centric blockchains, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org/en/&quot;&gt;Ethereum&lt;/a&gt;,
the network certifies computation, and the code of the computation is a public
smart contract stored on the blockchain, you can trust the contract to do what
its code says, nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means that &lt;em&gt;anybody&lt;/em&gt; can deploy a new smart contract, and other people can
use it as long as they trust the code. The contract author does not need to have
resources, a reputation or even to comply with regulations (1) to deploy his
contract, or for you to trust that the contract will be executed faithfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(1) He &lt;em&gt;has to&lt;/em&gt;, legally speaking, but blockchains being novel, it&amp;#39;s unclear
which rules apply in the first place. Such &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fear,_uncertainty,_and_doubt&quot;&gt;FUD&lt;/a&gt; would normally stifle
innovation — but not on the blockchain where the barrier to entry is low, and
many developers are anonymous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is super exciting! It has already led to numerous innovations in the
financial realm, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paradigm.xyz/2021/04/understanding-automated-market-makers-part-1-price-impact/&quot;&gt;automated market makers&lt;/a&gt; (AMM), as well as many
new forms of clever incentivization mechanisms such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://academy.shrimpy.io/post/what-is-liquidity-mining&quot;&gt;liquidity mining&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.okex.com/academy/en/olympusdao-protocol-owned-liquidity-defi-reserve-currency-ohm&quot;&gt;liquidity purchases via bonding&lt;/a&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides brand new constructions, it also makes opportunities available to
everyone that were previously available only to a few. Option protocols such as
&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.lyra.finance/&quot;&gt;Lyra&lt;/a&gt; make it possible for everyone to profit from market-making the option
market: a process where the &lt;em&gt;market maker&lt;/em&gt; sells an option, which is hedged by
the underlying, in order to pocket the option premium. (If this is Chinese to
you, see my articles on &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/options/&quot;&gt;options&lt;/a&gt; and on &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/gamestop/&quot;&gt;gamma squeezes&lt;/a&gt;.) Previously, this
lucrative and relatively safe opportunity reserved to big investment banks.
On-chain, everyone can add their money to a pool and participate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this is just an example amongst many. Another one would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/coinmonks/what-is-liquidation-in-defi-lending-and-borrowing-platforms-3326e0ba8d0&quot;&gt;lending to
overcollateralized borrowers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, more areas can benefit from this innovative drive besides finance.
One area that looks promising at the moment is gaming. Increasingly, game
development is financed by the sales of in-game assets (skins, character
customizations, convenience features, ...). One could be hesitant to buy into a
relatively unknown game. Using the blockchain to encode these assets incurs many
benefits: it can be made certain that they won&amp;#39;t disappear at the whim of the
developer, that they are tradeable without the developer investing any resources
to make them so. Even better, another developer could decide to reuse the
assets, and give them a function within his own game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the use of blockchain in gaming is at the same stage where
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer&quot;&gt;peer-to-peer&lt;/a&gt; (P2P) technology used to be some 20 years back. P2P had a
terrible reputation as a thing used only to download copyrighted material. Yet
only a few years later it became a common way to distribute big games and their
updates, proving invaluable at handling the load on release day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe crypto gaming doesn&amp;#39;t work out. Who knows? There are &lt;strong&gt;many&lt;/strong&gt; other
areas in which people are building on the blockchain at the moment. Most
projects will fail, but those who succeed might create immense value (I&amp;#39;m
talking about usefulness, not money), and these wouldn&amp;#39;t have gotten built
without the blockchain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll simply recap the thesis: blockchain are decentralized trust engines.
Instead of trusting a single service provider, you trust a majority of the
validators to be honest — and they are incentivized to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On decentralized computation blockchains like Ethereum, this enable anybody to
deploy a smart contract, and anybody else to trust that the code will be
executed faithfully (it still requires reading and understanding the code!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This enables permissionless innovation: anybody can innovate, not only big
companies with a reputation, or with government sign-off — even when money is
involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also enables anybody to port existing constructions to the blockchain, for
all to take advantage of (e.g. option market-making).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, these innovations will spread outside finance in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ps&quot;&gt;PS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subject seems to be momentous, and here are two excellent recent pieces that
harp on the value of decentralization:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://mnot.github.io/avoiding-internet-centralization/draft-nottingham-avoiding-internet-centralization.html&quot;&gt;Avoiding Internet Centralization&lt;/a&gt; talks about the importance of
decentralizing the internet&amp;#39;s infrastructure, but many of its arguments are
valid arguments against centralization in general. (It also makes clear that
blockchains aren&amp;#39;t really the solution for low-level internet infrastructure.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chris-granger.com/2021/12/09/is-web3-anything/&quot;&gt;Is Web3... anything?&lt;/a&gt; is similar to this post and explains
blockchains as &amp;quot;a protocol/architecture for near-trustless commitments&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-12-10T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/essence-blockchains</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/essence-blockchains</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How rollups scale Ethereum</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;a href=&quot;https://hackmd.io/ZJR05zr-SP-tm1D9aqKJaA&quot;&gt;overview&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ethereum&amp;#39;s limited resources, specifically bandwidth, computation, and
storage, constrain the number of transactions which can be processed on the
network, leading to extremely high fees. Scaling Ethereum means increasing the
number of useful transactions the Ethereum network can process, by increasing
the supply of these limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But how do rollups increase these resources? To understand this, we first need
to give some details about layer-1 (L1) Ethereum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;state-in-l1-ethereum&quot;&gt;State in L1 Ethereum&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The size of the L1 state &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/LjGPCX2V1qk?t=267&quot;&gt;as per summer 2021&lt;/a&gt; was around 35GB.
However, during execution, the state needs to be stored in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/nanoeth/tree/master/src/com/norswap/nanoeth/trees/patricia#readme&quot;&gt;Merkle Patricia
Tree&lt;/a&gt; (MPT), which takes the effective stored size to 100GB. This size is
expected to grow by 50GB per year, assuming the Ethereum &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org/en/developers/docs/gas/#what-is-gas-limit&quot;&gt;gas limit&lt;/a&gt; stays
constant. These amounts does not even include historical state, some of which
&lt;strong&gt;must&lt;/strong&gt; be kept to be able to process &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paradigm.xyz/2021/07/ethereum-reorgs-after-the-merge/&quot;&gt;chain reorganizations&lt;/a&gt;. A node
must also keep at least some recent block header data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, core developers are not increasing the gas limit because we expect
higher throughput to cause faster state growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still these numbers are manageable. 4TB SSD drives can be purchased for 400$ or
less. So why don&amp;#39;t we just increase the gas limit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-not-increase-the-gas-limit&quot;&gt;Why not increase the gas limit?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two reasons. The first is a commitment to keep Ethereum as
decentralized as possible, which includes making it possible for as many people
as possible to validate the network. We could increase the gas limit and require
every validator to spend a few thousand dollars to participate and this wouldn&amp;#39;t
really decrease the security of the network. However, the same kind of reasoning
could be repeatedly applied to take us to a situation where you&amp;#39;d need to rent
in a data center to validate the network. This is extremely undesirable, because
it would let a small number of majority actors (e.g. staking pools) collude with
very few people noticing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me give just one possible scenario. A majority cabal of staking pools could
claim to run a jointly-developed custom client, which so happened to have a
&amp;quot;subtle bug&amp;quot; that associates of the pools are able to exploit for profit. The
few remaining honest actors need to detect and then identify the problem — are
the pools or the other validators correct? The pools could make this
investigation difficult, and by the time the &amp;quot;bug&amp;quot; surfaces, the chain has moved
on so far that a fork becomes unthinkable. The pools can maintain plausible
deniability by claiming this was an innocent bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a lot of things in the blockchain space, this is a social problem as much
as a technical one. One reason more eyes on the chain is better is because it
can cause more outcry in case of fraud, and give legitimacy to the correct fork.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second reason we don&amp;#39;t want to increase the gas limit is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parity.io/blog/what-is-a-light-client/&quot;&gt;light clients&lt;/a&gt;.
Light clients are clients that can validate the network but are not required to
store the state. Instead they can request the state from the network and
validate it against state roots stored in recent block headers. Light clients
allow reducing the reliance on centralized state providers like Infura.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aside: how light clients work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A light client needs to start with a trusted block header (either coming from
an initial sync or trusted source). Let&amp;#39;s assume that this hash is a
semi-recent block hash, updated each time you use your light-client-enabled
wallet. Then, the next time you use your wallet, you need to get all the block
headers between that trusted header and the current head of the chain. There
are solutions to validate these headers in both proof-of-work and
proof-of-stake, but let&amp;#39;s focus on the latter, as it is Ethereum&amp;#39;s future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To verify a block header, you&amp;#39;ll need to determine that the block was indeed
signed by known Ethereum validators (stakers). The validator data is small
enough that it could be kept locally, or you can request it from the network
and validate it against the trusted block header.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;#39;re caught up with the chain (which should be fast unless you haven&amp;#39;t
opened your wallet in months/years), you can speculatively execute
transactions locally, or even execute whole new blocks yourself. During these
executions, you&amp;#39;ll need to request the state from the network, which you can
again validate against the state Merkle root in the most recent block header.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This state can even be obtained from a centralized provider. The difference is
that you do not need to trust him anymore: now you can verify the state
against block headers, and you run the computations yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Light clients are expected to run on user&amp;#39;s machines (laptops, cell phones) and
only sporadically (e.g. when using a wallet). Clearly this puts a limit on
storage, computation and bandwidth. The storage is solved by getting the state
from the network, but this further constrains bandwidth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Increasing the gas limit too much would overwhelm light-client&amp;#39;s ability to
catch up and keep up with the chain, in terms of bandwidth and computation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, light clients help keep Ethereum decentralized by creating more
validators. Light clients associated with wallets are a formidable deterrent
because it means these wallets won&amp;#39;t transact on fraudulent chains, even if they
are supported by a majority of miners/stakers. Vitalik Buterin makes this point
&lt;a href=&quot;https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/05/23/scaling.html#its-crucial-for-blockchain-decentralization-for-regular-users-to-be-able-to-run-a-node&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;enter-rollups&quot;&gt;Enter Rollups&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first want to acknowledge the fact that how rollups scale Ethereum — while
preserving its security guarantees — is not as straightforward as it is often
made out to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scaling property of rollups falls out from two facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A rollup needs orders of magnitude less validators than L1 to maintain its
security. As long as a single honest validator does its job, the network will
remain secure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State growth can be spread between multiple independent rollups.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s look at (1) first. In an &lt;a href=&quot;https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/01/05/rollup.html&quot;&gt;optimistic rollup&lt;/a&gt;, the rollup will be secure if
there is always a validator that can submit a fraud proof for every detected
sequencer fraud. Therefore, it is okay to increase the requirements needed to
run these validators, as long as motivated entities and individuals are able to
run them. Note also that many entities have a vested interest in running these
validators, because they derive value from the rollup: data and insight
providers like Infura, The Graph, Dune Analytics; as well as projects building
on top of the rollup. Unlike in my &amp;quot;evil staking pools&amp;quot; scenario, a majority of
bad actors is no longer able to get away with fraud!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/01/05/rollup.html&quot;&gt;zk rollup&lt;/a&gt;, you do not need validators at all for security (you might need
them for data availability however, depending on the architecture of the
rollup), but you need to trust the code of the zk verifier smart contract. While
no external validators are needed, the requirements on the prover (the zk
pendant of the sequencer) are extreme, as building the zk proofs is very costly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding (2), this lets different validators verify different parts of the
state, hence not imposing the burden of the extra state of every rollup on every
validator. Because of (1), we know that it&amp;#39;s okay for each rollup to have many
less validators than L1. This is also the insight behind &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org/en/eth2/shard-chains/&quot;&gt;sharding&lt;/a&gt; — though in
this case the reduced validator requirement does not apply and is solved with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/04/07/sharding.html&quot;&gt;random committee selection&lt;/a&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-summary&quot;&gt;In Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can&amp;#39;t just raise the gas limit to scale Ethereum, because that would raise
hardware requirements for validators, and the chain needs to be validated as
broadly as possible to avoid a collusion of majority actors. It would also
preclude the introduction of light clients to break our reliance on centralized
data providers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rollups help scale Ethereum because they require order of magnitude less
validators than L1 to stay secure (via the use of fraud proofs or zero-knowledge
proofs), hence the requirements for validators can be increased. Additionally,
the state growth between multiple rollups that can be validated separately.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-12-03T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/rollups-scale</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/rollups-scale</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Life Updates</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s been a crazy year. It was already crazy &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/ragged&quot;&gt;back in March&lt;/a&gt;, but
against my better judgement, I (thankfully!) doubled down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In June, I took a leave from my Job at Oracle to take part in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.ethereum.org/2021/05/13/core-dev-apprenticeship/&quot;&gt;Ethereum Core
Developer Apprenticeship&lt;/a&gt; for four months. I learned a ton — here&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ethereum-cdap/cohort-zero/blob/main/showcase/norswap.md&quot;&gt;a
recap&lt;/a&gt; of what I did there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end of the program, I was sold, and I joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.optimism.io/&quot;&gt;Optimism&lt;/a&gt; to work on
scaling the Ethereum blockchain. My first task there will be to help &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/ethereum-optimism/optimistic-specs&quot;&gt;specify
and prototype&lt;/a&gt; the new version of the Optimistic Ethereum rollup. It&amp;#39;s
been a blast so far!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expect more content soon, especially blockchain-related. If you hate blockchains
— I&amp;#39;m so sorry.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-12-03T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/life-updates</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/life-updates</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviews 11</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Part of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews&quot;&gt;Reviews Series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;cobra-kai&quot;&gt;Cobra Kai&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;previously: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-10#cobra-kai&quot;&gt;Season 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my review of the first season, I said the show was constantly toeing the line
of overuse on its narrative ropes. I really enjoyed the third season too, but
it&amp;#39;s clearly the season where the line gets crossed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rest of the review behind the spoiler tag!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Click for spoilerful review.&lt;/summary&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s good and there&amp;#39;s bad in the storylines and character development arcs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last time, I said I would be interested in how they handled Tory and Kreese.
Tory is very much in the background. Her difficult background is briefly
glimpsed, but mostly that doesn&amp;#39;t make her more relatable. Instead of being a
crazy bitch, she&amp;#39;s now a crazy bitch in a difficult situation — but that
happens, and it&amp;#39;s not necessarily bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kreese gets a lot of attention, in particular through the flashback fleshing his
background. The issue is it doesn&amp;#39;t work one bit. I reckon the goal of the
flashback is to explain how Kreese got the way he was. But it doesn&amp;#39;t really.
Past Kreese is mostly sympathetic and good-hearted. What he goes through doesn&amp;#39;t
even explain why someone would become angry, bitter, violent, cynical, and
jaded. They could have pulled that off, but they didn&amp;#39;t. But what they really
needed to pull off is to explain how he became a sociopath. Of course, people
don&amp;#39;t really suddenly become sociopaths (barring extremely extravagant plot
events and/or brain damage), so they would have had a hard time pulliing that
one off. The result is that the flashbacks have almost zero tie-in to the rest
of the story (except explaining the origin of the term &amp;quot;Cobra Kai&amp;quot;), which is
weird. Maybe they&amp;#39;ll continue in the next season, but I&amp;#39;m not confident in their
ability to salvage the plot line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest missed opportunity of the season lies in a character whose storyline
gets really butchered: Hawk. Since the first season, it&amp;#39;s obvious they are
setting up a redemption/reconciliation arc between Hawk and Demetri. Compared to
the other storylines, this one already felt sluggish. But mostly, things move
along, coming to a head when Hawk breaks Demetri&amp;#39;s arm. This should be the
breaking point (pun intended) for Hawk. Afterwards, it&amp;#39;s just awkward. I get
they wanted him to flip in the final battle, but the timing just makes this
awkward. Triple akward in fact as Demetri immediately welcomes him back (&amp;quot;don&amp;#39;t
worry for my arm bro!&amp;quot;), robbing the whole thing of its emotional payload. They
also just push things way too far with Cobra Kai being assholes I think,
removing a lot of the nuance that made the show great. There&amp;#39;s being an asshole
and then there&amp;#39;s being a caricature of caricature of an asshole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel&amp;#39;s Japanese adventure is meh, and feels like a huge wink. The
&amp;quot;Daniel-san!!&amp;quot; cliffhanger is so cringe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aisha went MIA, probably for actor&amp;#39;s reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robby&amp;#39;s storyline is retarded, plain and simple. His action don&amp;#39;t really add up,
especially the ending point of &amp;quot;Kreese is cool, he told me to fight — never mind
he just tried to stab you&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I&amp;#39;m very negative and a bit disappointed — but I actually mostly
enjoyed the thing. I probably couldn&amp;#39;t bring myself to write such a long review
for a thing I didn&amp;#39;t care about anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s talk about some good things. Johnny and Miguel&amp;#39;s storyline were pretty
good. I was pleasantly surprised that the Amy plotline did not feature some
misunderstanding between Johny &amp;amp; Carmen. Demetri is hilarious as always and
standing up for himself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can season 4 pull an Attack on Titan and turn this ship around?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lupin&quot;&gt;Lupin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV show&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Part 1 (6 episodes)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/lupin.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lupin is the first French TV show I&amp;#39;ve watched in forever. And, oh shock, it&amp;#39;s
actually pretty good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story centers around Assane Diop (played by the excellent Omar Sy), a
professional thief. When he was young, his father was framed for a theft he
didn&amp;#39;t commit — something Assane only learns at the start of the season. We then
follow his struggle against his mighty enemies, in order to get justice for his
father.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Assane is inspired and emulates the character of Arsène Lupin — the gentleman
burglar. This leads to a series of clever plans, tricks and deceptions that make
the show quite entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the great story, the show also benefits from the insane charisma of Omar
Sy, who really sells the character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly, a pleasure to watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/ga0iTWXCGa0&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pragmatic-capitalism&quot;&gt;Pragmatic Capitalism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Cullen Roche&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a book I enqueued on my read list when I started to learn about
finance. I have mixed feelings about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is mostly concerned with discussing the monetary system, with some
investment portfolio advice thrown in the middle. This is not capitalism, it&amp;#39;s
not finance, it&amp;#39;s macro-economics. Fine, but what not what I expected from the
book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The description of the monetary system itself is well-meaning, but falls short
for me. I&amp;#39;m not quite sure who the intended audience is. Roche keeps emphasizing
some points — common misconceptions that seem to be his pet peeves — and to his
credit that is very clear, though a little preachy. More advanced topics are
unfortunately not that well-explained and seem to assume some familiarity with
the system already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can tell Roche means well, but its content would have worked better as a
series of blog posts. It would be hard to me to recommend it to anyone. It&amp;#39;s too
long to be an introduction, doesn&amp;#39;t go far enough to be textbook, and doesn&amp;#39;t
explain the advanced concepts well-enough anyway. The portfolio advice is also
well-meaning but all the same, I don&amp;#39;t particularly recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not a bad book, but I&amp;#39;m not sure what it&amp;#39;s trying to achieve. Meh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fff-class-trashhero&quot;&gt;FFF-Class Trashhero&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to chapter 86&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another entry in the leveling genre. In this one, we join the hero (that has
been summoned to another world to defeat the demon king, nothing unusual) after
he defats the demon king. However, it turns out that his performance is being
graded, and he fails, because he actually murdered his party before confronting
the demon king. So now he has to start all over again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why did he do such a thing? From his point of view, he was being abducted
against his will, and the people in this fantasy land actually mistreated him
pretty badly, beating him to toughen him up, having him run nonsensical errands,
etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is fairly comedic in nature, there&amp;#39;s some slapstick humor
à-la-&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/every-anime/#konosuba&quot;&gt;Konosuba!&lt;/a&gt;, albeit much less charming. But it sits uneasy between its dark
premise and the comedic element. The hero&amp;#39;s character is terrible, but the story
is earnest in telling us that he has good reasons for it — he&amp;#39;s not just being
silly. At the same, the story also depends on its dumb factor. The hero starts
being evil from the get-go in his second attempt, even as that&amp;#39;s obviously not
the correct way to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, it also veers into a weird over-the-top power trip, and I&amp;#39;m not
sure how the author will extirpate himself from this mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed this, but I would have enjoyed it much more if the comedic element was
dropped and the premise was left to shine. What could a bitter hero have done to
try to pass while being subjected to the rules (or break free in other ways, or
get revenge)? And there are already plenty of elements that could have made that
good (for instance, how good or bad is it to kill a king to avoid a war?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, everything before the power trip was engaging enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kill-the-hero&quot;&gt;Kill The Hero&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to chapter 53&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fairly classical leveling-genre entry. The setting is very similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-9/#solo-leveling&quot;&gt;Solo
Leveling&lt;/a&gt; (modern-day South Korea, dungeons appear, some people get power, and a
whole semi-corrupt industry of &amp;quot;heroes&amp;quot; springs up). The twist is that the
protagonist is also a returnee that was betrayed in his previous life (another
super common trop of the genre). Hence &amp;quot;kill the hero&amp;quot;, where the &amp;quot;hero&amp;quot; is
actually this scheming villain that everybody thinks is good. I was hoping the
title was referring to some story-telling twist or some unusual perspective, but
not really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is bog-standard, but indubitably well done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-great-mage-returns-after-4000-years&quot;&gt;The Great Mage Returns After 4000 Years&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to chapter 82&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another &amp;quot;leveling&amp;quot; story that takes some of the basic genre building blocks and
arranges them in yet another configuration. In this one, a very powerful mage
(just like in &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-10/#i-am-the-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;I am The Sorcerer King&lt;/a&gt;) dies and returns in the future, this
future is not modern-day South Korea, but instead some kind of medieval fantasy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his previous life, the mage was defeated by a &lt;em&gt;demigod&lt;/em&gt;, some kind of
malevolent super-powerful entity. In his new life, the mage seeks to find out
what happened to his companions and to take on the demigods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is a bit more earnest than average, and the tone reminded me of &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-9/#the-beginning-after-the-end&quot;&gt;The
Beginning After The End&lt;/a&gt;, which is great since that&amp;#39;s one of the best leveling
webtoons out there. Recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;your-throne&quot;&gt;Your Throne&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to chapter 67&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a webtoon that&amp;#39;s not about people powering up! This one follows two
noble lady — Medea and Psyche. The cold ruthless Medea was promised to the crown
prince, before the engagement was broken and he chose to get engaged to the
sweet innocent Psyche. Medea swears to have revenge and retrieve what is
rightfully hers. And then a lot of things happen but I don&amp;#39;t want to spoil you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty well done. One criticism I have is that it&amp;#39;s at times a bit
confusing. Another one is that it departs from the traditional &lt;em&gt;arc&lt;/em&gt; format.
While I applaud initiatives to be less formulaic, arcs are used because they
work, and this works less well. What would have been arcs in other stories
instead blend into one another. And I don&amp;#39;t mean this in the positive, &amp;quot;story
expertly woven&amp;quot; way. Instead, we&amp;#39;re not given the time to breathe, assimilate
what happened, participate in the protagonist&amp;#39;s happiness, sadness, triumph or
defeat and instead we&amp;#39;re immediately trust into the next thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think saying the story doesn&amp;#39;t breathe enough is maybe clearer. As a result,
it becomes much more emotionally muted than it could be. Its high points don&amp;#39;t
take you that high, and its low points don&amp;#39;t take you that low. Which is too
bad, because the story has potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;akudama-drive&quot;&gt;Akudama Drive&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched on the recommendations of a few friends who said it was one of the
best anime of the Fall 2020 season (this was a particularly dry season for me, I
don&amp;#39;t think I watched a single other anime from it, excepted giving &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-9/#jujutsu-kaisen&quot;&gt;Jujutsu
Kaisen&lt;/a&gt; a try).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up nonplussed. Like, it&amp;#39;s not bad. It&amp;#39;s not that great either. It&amp;#39;s
annoying because there are a lot of great things about it. I really dig the
aesthetic, the character design is top-notch, the animation looks very good, the
music is quite nice. But the story never really got me invested or even
interested. The stakes are not that much, character development is meh-meh-meh,
the ending is unsatisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think I&amp;#39;d recommend it if you really dig the outrun/retrowave/neon sci-fi
aesthetic or if you watch anime for the eye candy. If you&amp;#39;re story-driven, this
will leave you hungry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;unordinary&quot;&gt;unOrdinary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to chapter 235&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/unordinary.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one looks straightforward, but I actually found it to be quite weird. In
this world, most people get a special ability (usually fighting-related — I
appreciated how straightforward they all were), and the strong trample on the
weak in a very hierarchical society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story follows John, who doesn&amp;#39;t have any ability, as he has a hard time at
his high school, being unpowered as he is but still rather proud. Many twists
ensue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what makes this weird? Well, first, the society being depicted is despicable.
Unrealistically, and unsustainably so, in fact. By the way, fair warning, if you
don&amp;#39;t want to see kids beat each other meanly and bloodily for 200 chapters, you
probably shouldn&amp;#39;t read this. There&amp;#39;s bullying on every second panel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, surprisingly, no one ever dies — even after someone uses their head to
bash some concrete. Nobody ever goes for the eyes somehow. In a world so full of
bullying, there also isn&amp;#39;t a single mention of suicide. Honestly, the world is
so bad that you&amp;#39;d expect that to pop up, and also strong people to be murdered
in their sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But alright, none of that happens, and to enjoy the story you really got to take
as a premise that it is the way of that particular world to be like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has another awkward consequence, which is that almost everyone in the story
is despicable. Yes, even the main character. There are maybe two main characters
that are not loathsome, but they were strong and uncaring in a world where you
can&amp;#39;t walk through two hallways without finding some bullying, which uhhhm ...
eeeeh. Some people start to improve towards the end, and to the credit of the
writing, this is done in a subtle way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what else is strangely lacking in a high-school setting? Nobody seems
to have the slightest interest in romance and/or sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Webtoons often shy away from these themes, for what I ignorantly assume must be
weird Korean cultural reasons? Although seeing that K-Drama is a thing, this at
least makes no sense for romance. Often, there is some romance slapstick, like
unreciprocated crushes, tsundere moments, and even the occasional lewd event
where the male MC&amp;#39;s head lands on some woman&amp;#39;s breasts. I really don&amp;#39;t get the
absence of these themes, which are interesting and complex and inherently
interesting to us humans. Someone please enlighten me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, unOrdinary doesn&amp;#39;t even have the slapstick. Nobody expresses even a iota
of romantic intentions or sexual tension. And that&amp;#39;s just weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all that said, unOrdinary&amp;#39;s story is quite gripping. Despite its characters
being often (or at least initially) loathsome, it&amp;#39;s a character-driven story and
the characters &lt;strong&gt;are&lt;/strong&gt; well-written. They have clear motivations, personalities,
and as alluded earlier, there is real character development. The broader story
is also solid enough that it makes you want to keep reading to know what will
happen and how the characters will end up being implicated in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m conflicted about this one. On the one hand, I found it hard to put down once
I got started, and there is objectively a lot that it does well on the
story-telling front. Perhaps my problem with it is a lack of relatability to the
characters, given the problems with the setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;second-life-ranker&quot;&gt;Second Life Ranker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to chapter 84&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another formulaic leveling webtoon. A confusingly-named one at that, since
in this one, the MC does not return from his previous life, but instead goes by
the notes left by his deceased brother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t have much else to say, it&amp;#39;s fairly classic as an entry, but quite well
done. You&amp;#39;ll like this if you like the other leveling webtoon, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;raid&quot;&gt;Raid&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;up to chapter 95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yep, another level webtoon! This one is of the Solo Leveling &amp;quot;monster gates
spawn all over Korea&amp;quot; persuasion, though with less emphasis on RPG mechanics (no
skill windows!) and less of a fantasy theme (no orcs and goblins and the rest of
the fantastic bestiary, just plain old demons).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aaand, it&amp;#39;s okay. Entertaining, but clearly a notch under &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/#kill-the-hero&quot;&gt;Kill The Hero&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/#second-life-ranker&quot;&gt;Second Life Ranker&lt;/a&gt; as far as not-particularly-original entries go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;castlevania&quot;&gt;Castlevania&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 4&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-6/#castlevania-all-3-seasons&quot;&gt;Seasons 1-3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In its final season, Castelevania keeps being good, but imperfect, but damn
entertaining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to the previous seasons, I feel like this one steps up the game in
terms of animation. These last few fights are really impressive. On the other
hand, maybe we didn&amp;#39;t need &lt;strong&gt;quite&lt;/strong&gt; that much fighting? When you get 4 fights
back to back, it kind of undermines their weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Story-wise (and you know I&amp;#39;m a story guy), it&amp;#39;s not bad — I was engaged through
— but could have been better. The big conclusion didn&amp;#39;t really feel
woven/foreshadowed. I expected some big reveal, and I guess there was some
reveal, but it fell flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the final season, I also expected some confluence of the storylines. More
after the spoiler tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Click for spoilers.&lt;/summary&gt;
The Isaac storyline feels unfinished. I really thought it was going somewhere.
Maybe the spinoff that is reportedly in the works will focus on him?

&lt;p&gt;I also found Lenore&amp;#39;s ending unecessarily melodramatic and unecessary. Most of
all, it does not feel like a conclusion that the story led into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m curious to watch the spinoff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;overcoming-gravity&quot;&gt;Overcoming Gravity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked this up as a book about bodyweight exercise. What I got is not what I
expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book tells less about bodyweight training than I&amp;#39;d hoped. Sure, there are
instructions and cues, etc. But it&amp;#39;s relatively terse. You can easily find more
detailed write-ups on Google, and some good tutorials on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, on the other hand, it&amp;#39;s an impressive compendium of knowledge of the basic
factors that affect strength and hypertrophy training, of how to setup a workout
routine etc. In fact, this occupies most of the first half of the book — you
only get to details on specific bodyweight exercises at around page 300...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being well-written and interesting, I wouldn&amp;#39;t recommend the book for
the purpose of creating a routine either. Not unless you have a few years of
training (and crucially, experimentation with your routines) under your belt
and/or are coaching other athletes. It&amp;#39;s written in a very encyclopedic style.
I don&amp;#39;t mean this in a bad way: it&amp;#39;s a presentation of facts. But that means
that the book does not read linearly. Despite the presence of &amp;quot;stop reading,
take action&amp;quot; sections, the book offer little opportunity to actually start
planning a routine until the whole has been read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it&amp;#39;s not bad, but unless you&amp;#39;re looking for a routine-building reference,
I&amp;#39;d try other places first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;trading-volatility&quot;&gt;Trading Volatility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trading Volatility is a book, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trading-volatility.com/&quot;&gt;available online&lt;/a&gt; for free about trading
in volatility-related products, in particular options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started reading the book as parts of my efforts to learn about &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;finance&lt;/a&gt;. In
the end, I decided to drop it after the first chapter, as it becomes too
technical, and not particularly applicable to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the strategies presented later in the book seem to require stock-based
hedging, for which you need zero commissions and taxes on stock transactions, as
well as some way to automate trading (i.e. a broker with an API). I don&amp;#39;t fit
these conditions. It also discusses instruments that are not readily available
to the retail trader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does look very interesting however, but I currently have much more useful
things to learn, so I shelved it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tales-of-demons-and-gods&quot;&gt;Tales of Demons and Gods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Manga&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to chapter 348&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/tales.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my quest to find more webtoons in what I&amp;#39;ve dubbed &amp;quot;the leveling genre&amp;quot;, I
came across &lt;em&gt;Tales of Demons and Gods&lt;/em&gt;. The particularity of this one is that
the original is in Chinese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much of a difference does it make? Some. Clearly the tone and the attitudes
of the characters are different. It&amp;#39;s still closer to Korean webtoons than to
anything western I&amp;#39;ve seen however. The tropes of the genre are pretty-well
respected: in this case there is a reincarnation, growable powers, a magic
school, world-threatening elements, ... There are few added cultural element,
e.g. the people grow their &amp;quot;soul power&amp;quot; by &amp;quot;cultivating&amp;quot;, a term I&amp;#39;ve seen
popped up in other Chinese media (notably &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-6/#mo-dao-zu-shi&quot;&gt;Mo Dao Zu
Shi&lt;/a&gt;, which I didn&amp;#39;t enjoy so much).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As far as the story goes, it&amp;#39;s really long, and it&amp;#39;s pretty decent. Details are
woven throughout, so it&amp;#39;s not just choppy arc after choppy arc, but you can
still expect the leveling hustle to take up most of the space compared to the
intrigue. It might be tiresome after a while — this one is definitely not a
literary masterpiece, but it&amp;#39;s fun enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;true-detective&quot;&gt;True Detective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV Show&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After hearing so much about it, we finally took the leap and watched the first
season of true detective. There is a second season, but the characters and story
are completely different — it&amp;#39;s just reusing the same principle. People say it&amp;#39;s
less good, but since I haven&amp;#39;t seen it, I can&amp;#39;t comment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story revolves around a pair of cops, one of which is new (where have I seen
that before?) as they investigate a murder steeped in voodoo spiritism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What really makes the show is it&amp;#39;s grisly, bleak and oppressive atmosphere. It
really doesn&amp;#39;t make you want to move to Louisiana where the story takes place.
The characters are dark and conflicted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting together this atmosphere in a way that&amp;#39;s interesting and keeps you
engaged is really the show&amp;#39;s greatest strength. It is a somewhat unique
experience, I must admit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the plot itself... it&amp;#39;s decent, I suppose? I kept expecting more twists,
more reveals, some acceleration of the intrigue, and in the end I was pretty let
down. I think a great plot would have elevated this from an interesting show to
a masterpiece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, as-is, it&amp;#39;s well worth watching. If you&amp;#39;re afraid it&amp;#39;s not your jam, just
watch the first episode — if you don&amp;#39;t like it I doubt it&amp;#39;s worth going any
further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;koi-to-yobu-ni-wa-kimochi-warui-kokoimo&quot;&gt;Koi to Yobu ni wa Kimochi Warui (Kokoimo)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were looking for something more romcom-ish to watch with Sasha and landed on
kokoimo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dangerous-sounding plot is a young salaryman falling in love with a
high-school girl, pursuing her as best he can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The shows ends being quite inoffensive. It&amp;#39;s decent enough I guess, though I
lack points of comparison in the genre (which is not my forte). Still I have
watched it and not hated it. I also didn&amp;#39;t think it was particularly
interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;that-time-i-got-reincarnated-as-a-slime&quot;&gt;That Time I Got Reincarnated as a Slime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div id=slime /&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese Title: Tensei shitara Slime Datta Ken&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/even-more-anime/#that-time-i-got-reincarnated-as-a-slime&quot;&gt;Season 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of what I said in my review of season 1 still holds. Slime is enjoyable,
but never truly great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time around it&amp;#39;s a bit less formulaic, but it&amp;#39;s not really better or worse,
just different. I&amp;#39;m sure some people will argue it&amp;#39;s worse though, seen as
entire episodes are dedicated to meetings. There are one or two interesting plot
developments however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, if you liked the first season, keep watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;boku-no-hero-academia&quot;&gt;Boku no Hero Academia&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/more-anime/#my-hero-academia&quot;&gt;Season 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/even-more-anime/#my-hero-academia-season-3&quot;&gt;Season
3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-6/#my-hero-academia-season-4&quot;&gt;Season
4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hero academia is still good, but it&amp;#39;s again not the strongest season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s divided in two arcs, the first of which is a &amp;quot;training tournament&amp;quot; that
feels a little bit filler-ish. It&amp;#39;s not too bad though, there are interesting
fight strategies etc, but no real stakes (not even in terms of character
development).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second one is much more interesting and revolves around the ligue of
villains encountering challenges of their own. This could have been amazing, but
the effect is slightly spoiled by the fact that the treatment is very formulaic.
At some point, they go through all the key members of the league and they all
experience some breakthrough one after the other — this is a bit ham-fisted an
tends to pull me out of the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That second arc also reveals some key background elements on some characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;to-your-eternity&quot;&gt;To Your Eternity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese Name: Fumetsu no Anata e&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A really nice surprise, and also one that is hard to review without spoiling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll say two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch it if you&amp;#39;re going to watch any anime on this list, it really is good
enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The only letdown in the anime is that some patterns repeat again and again,
and I think it makes the anime less compelling. I was really like &amp;quot;oh come
on... again?&amp;quot; at some points. This makes the story less compelling than it
could have been if the arcs were a bit more varied / open-ended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;demon-slayer-mugen-train&quot;&gt;Demon Slayer: Mugen Train&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Japanese Title: Kimetsu no Yaiba: Mugen Ressha-hen&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-4/#demon-slayer&quot;&gt;Season 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the first season of Demon Slayer, the movie share the same visual
strengths, and packs an emotional punch too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movie form factor perfectly suits Demon Slayer&amp;#39;s strength. This one is a
must watch if you like good animation, shonen, or both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the showrunners have made the decision to adapt/convert the movie
into a 7 anime episodes prelude to season 2, which have recently started airing.
No idea how that will turn out (I won&amp;#39;t watch it), but I expect it&amp;#39;s worth
seeing it as originally intended, as an unbroken movie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;james-bond-no-time-to-die&quot;&gt;James Bond: No Time To Die&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/bond.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repeatedly-delayed movie if finally out (if you&amp;#39;re reading from the future:
covid), and it&amp;#39;s pretty good!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clocking at 2 hours and 40 minutes, it&amp;#39;s the longest James Bond to date.
Fortunately, it&amp;#39;s entertaining and time passes rather quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Craig does an amazing job as usual, the other characters are pretty good,
and the plot is decent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not perfect however. While Rami Malek makes a very convincing villain, his
motivations are very much lacking. There isn&amp;#39;t really any rhyme or reason as to
why he wants to destroy large part of the world. His bionic-eyed henchman
(apparently called &amp;quot;Primo&amp;quot; though I don&amp;#39;t think that&amp;#39;s mentioned in the movie
even once) feels like ticking a James-Bond checkbox. He&amp;#39;s not really
interesting, and fighting him feels like a formality to get rid of as fast as
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was left wondering why the movie was so long. I think there&amp;#39;s simply too much
fighting — most of which is not very good. Bond and his associate mow down vast
number of redshirts in a way that stretches believability (yes, even by James
Bond standards). In some scenes, you really feel like Bond should emerge
completely peppered with bullets, but he&amp;#39;s invariably unscathed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only one that can score on James Bond is Rami Malek&amp;#39;s big villain &amp;quot;Lyutsifer
Safin&amp;quot; (terrible name, but that&amp;#39;s pretty much James Bond tradition), essentially
by virtue of plot convenience. Just like the henchman fight, their fight is
short and not that interesting excepted in its outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I came away with was the feeling that director Fukunaga wasn&amp;#39;t really
skilled not really interested in directing action scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, Fukunaga is the director of &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/#true-detective-season-1&quot;&gt;the first season of True
Detection&lt;/a&gt;, a show with a carefully crafted mood, but
also not much action and not much plot intricacy. I would say that maps pretty
well to the strength of this James Bond entry — it&amp;#39;s really good a showcasing
more human and psychological elements. This is something the James Bond
franchise is historically not so good at, but which has been a hallmark of
Daniel Craig&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;new&amp;quot; James Bond. The flip side is that the action scenes feel
like an afterthought and the plot is lackluster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I&amp;#39;d place this entry level with the previous Craig-era hits Casino
Royale and Skyfall. Thinking on it, I think those actually shared the shame
strengths and shortcomings: the villain looks the par but is not that convincing
in his convictions and the plot could be better. Other entries probably do a bit
better on the action though (especially the end of Skyfall, and the intro
sequences of Quantum of Solace and Spectre do deserve a mention).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder if I don&amp;#39;t like the more caricatural James Bond of the past. Mike
Taylor (whose blog I love) &lt;a href=&quot;https://reprog.wordpress.com/category/movies/james-bond/&quot;&gt;reviewed the whole franchise&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://reprog.wordpress.com/2012/11/19/james-bond-movies-part-1-sean-connery/&quot;&gt;wrote&lt;/a&gt; somewhere that &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Goldfinger_(film)&quot;&gt;Goldfinger&lt;/a&gt; was the prototypal James
Bond: it has a great villain (gold magnate Auric Goldfinger), a great henchman
(Oddjob, the steel-hat throwing Korean Oddjob), a memorable plot (irradiate the
gold reserve at Fort Knox to make Auric&amp;#39;s own gold value skyrocket), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Mx9z99YJ_7s&quot;&gt;the best
dialogue&lt;/a&gt;, etc...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point being that, if your villains are not going to have interesting
motivations, you might as well make them larger-than-life charisma machines, and
not wounded birds with a vaguely formulated desire for revenge as in the
Craig-era villains. Similar points can be made about other aspects of the
franchise, but this review is long enough. I&amp;#39;ll just mention that it&amp;#39;s not an
accident that my favourite Bond is Pierce Brosnan, who never loses his brushing
even in the most intense action scenes, but offered true spectacle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think in the end I like both types of Bond, but while Bond-as-entertainment
has been polished to a T, Bond-the-psychological-being is not quite there yet.
Right now it feels like a &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-10/#casablanca&quot;&gt;Casablanca&lt;/a&gt; knockoff with a lot of shooting, and I
think they can do better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Final note: the above sounds negative, but I think the movie is pretty good, and
worth a watch if you enjoyed any other Bond movie with Daniel Craig.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dune-2021&quot;&gt;Dune (2021)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/dune.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve read the books, I&amp;#39;ve seen the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dune_(1984_film)&quot;&gt;1984 movie&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#39;ve seen the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Herbert%27s_Dune&quot;&gt;2000
miniseries&lt;/a&gt;, so I was ready for this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But funnily enough, I didn&amp;#39;t know before watching it that it only adapted half
of the first book. The movie is pretty long (2h 35min) so the doubt persisted
for a fairly long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s clearly the most beautiful entry to date. Villeneuve knows what he&amp;#39;s doing.
Dune works better in my opinion than the (equally beautiful and even longer)
Blade Runner 2049 (which I saw but apparently forgot to review). I will chalk
that up with the fact that Blade Runner&amp;#39;s worst flaws where to include too much
crud that didn&amp;#39;t really matter to the plot in the final cut. Here Villeneuve
works from the book (the screenplay adapts it fairly faithfully).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a &amp;quot;slow&amp;quot; movie. There is action, but it&amp;#39;s nothing to write home about — in
fact, it&amp;#39;s a little bit disappointing even. Funny how I don&amp;#39;t consider myself an
action guy but I keep finding the action lacking in things I&amp;#39;m reviewing in this
entry. Fortunately, action isn&amp;#39;t really the point of Dune as it is James Bond&amp;#39;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, the movie really instills a mood that fits the universe. It&amp;#39;s
contemplative, but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would have liked better to see the first and the second part in a row, since
this first part doesn&amp;#39;t really peek or culminate anywhere. The story is
unfinished, and there is not much closure. Still, it was good enough that I&amp;#39;m
excited to see that second part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;invincible&quot;&gt;Invincible&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Series (Cartoon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews-11/invincible.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What a great surprise! I started watching the Amazon prime series on the
strength of a raving review from I-forget-where, which was well-deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It adapts a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Invincible_(comics)&quot;&gt;2003 comic&lt;/a&gt; (spoilers!), about a boy acquiring secret powers,
something that runs in the family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first 30/40 minutes felt like something straight out Spider-Man, it&amp;#39;s all
very consensual. But then, at the end of the first episode, the proverbial shit
hits the proverbial fan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show osciliates between the &amp;quot;fun for the whole family&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;grisly murder
scenes&amp;quot; quite seamlessly. Surprisingly, it works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot is quite good, with adequate foreshadowing and clues being placed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I really enjoyed was that each episode encompassed a whole story arc,
with no stupid cliffhanger at the end. That&amp;#39;s become so rare, it felt like a
breath of fresh air. And the show can pull it off, it&amp;#39;s good enough you&amp;#39;ll be
back even without the cliffhanger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ll be waiting for season 2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kaamelott&quot;&gt;Kaamelott&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie (French)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A movie sequel to the super popular French humoristic series &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kaamelott&quot;&gt;Kaamelott&lt;/a&gt;, which
parodies the Arthurian legend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was never a super fan of the series, who made me smile more than it made me
laugh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, the movie was greatly entertaining (though again, not something that made
me roar with laughter the way some other movie can).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was particularly admirative of how they managed to still maintain the humor &amp;amp;
spirit of the series, while still creating an epic narrative with at least some
amount of emotional weight. It&amp;#39;s a very delicate balancing act, and they nailed
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;oss-117-alerte-rouge-en-afrique-noire&quot;&gt;OSS 117: Alerte Rouge en Afrique Noire&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie (French)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movie is the sequel to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OSS_117:_Cairo,_Nest_of_Spies&quot;&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OSS_117:_Lost_in_Rio&quot;&gt;2009&lt;/a&gt; entries,
which follows the spy OSS 117 (played by Jean Dujardin, of internal fame thanks
to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Artist_(film)&quot;&gt;The Artist&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OSS 117 was a (serious) French James Bond knockoff, but this series uses the
character to make a French-scented parody of the spy genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I adore the first two movies, which have the unique flair &amp;amp; humor of director
Michel Hazanavicius. Notably, Hazanavicius also made &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/La_Classe_am%C3%A9ricaine&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;La Classe
Américaine&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; — un &amp;quot;détournement&amp;quot;, i.e. a movie made by dubbing over bits
and pieces of other movies, which happens to be infinitely quotable. He also
directed &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Artist_(film)&quot;&gt;The Artist&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The humor of the movies is somewhat risqué, always at the edge — OSS117 being
overly nationalistic, casually racist and sexist, and generally an idiot with
surprising talents, that somehow always comes out on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new entry in the franchise was not directed by Hazanavicius but by Nicolas
Bedos. I was wary, because I do not know Bedos very well, but did not like his
personality so much the few times I saw him on TV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I thought the movie was pretty good, and very faithful in spirit
to the previous entries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bedos is smart enough to switch the playbook slightly however. In this
installment, the bumbling OSS tries to appear politically correct by clumsily
hiding his prejudices. This is not easy to make work, but I think they pulled it
off pretty well. There are also plenty of small absurd elements (e.g. all the
maps are bonkers) that help make the movie fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One element I didn&amp;#39;t like was the character of the new spy they paired up with
OSS 117. The issue is that this character acts as a foil, pointing out loud that
OSS 117 is stupid/prejudiced/etc and really doesn&amp;#39;t know what he&amp;#39;s doing. That&amp;#39;s
quite unnecessary, it&amp;#39;s already obvious and some of the humor is precisely from
characters either buying into it or subtly signaling they think he&amp;#39;s an idiot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So anyway, a pretty good time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-10-14T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/reviews-11</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/reviews-11</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bonds Bonanza 2: Bonds Go Banana</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;in &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;Finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds&quot;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I explained the basics of the bonds market, the
difference the interest rate and the yield, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also mentioned that in February, yields soared from 1.13% to 1.6%, causing a
large upset in the stock market as well. In this post, I want to look at why
this happens, and how the effect spilled over to the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be warned that this post is a bit more about figuring things out than presenting
orderly facts. I&amp;#39;m far from mastering all the variables here, so take everything
with a grain of salt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-fundamentals&quot;&gt;The Fundamentals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic explanation of why the bond prices dropped precipitously and the yield
soared is pretty simple: people expect US dollar inflation, meaning rising
prices, hence a currency with less purchasing power. Inflation does all kinds of
bad things to the economy (which we will examine shortly) and so the federal
reserve tries to keep it subdued. It does this mostly by increasing the interest
rates it pays on newly emitted bonds. This decreases bond prices and increases
bond yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;#39;s not clear to you why the federal reserve increasing the interest rate on
bonds leads to falling bonds price and thus higher yields, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds&quot;&gt;the previous
article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember that government bonds are the ultimate safe investment. Raising the
interest rate leads to a bunch of other interest rates in the economy to
increase (for instance, on savings accounts), which promotes savings, which
reduces the amount of money circulating in the economy. The federal reserve also
uses the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/federalfundsrate.asp&quot;&gt;federal funds rate&lt;/a&gt; to achieve this objective. (Sorry if this is not
very precise. I wish I had a better understanding of the mechanics here.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reducing the amount of money circulating is important, because inflation is
caused by a changing balance between demand and supply. When there is a lot of
money chasing few goods, prices increase, and you have inflation. You reduce
inflation by decreasing the amount of money in circulation, or by increasing the
amount of good produced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People expect inflation, of course, because Joe Biden signed a stimulus bill
where the government would spend 1.9T$ (that&amp;#39;s trillion). For reference, the
total market capitalization (summing the value of every share) of the S&amp;amp;P 500 is
about 30T$. Then there is a 2T$ infrastructure bill being debated right now, and
there might some more down the line. When you inject so much money in the
economy, inflation is not exactly unexpected. There is however much debate about
how high inflation will go, and how transitory or persistent the increase will
be. The federal reserve currently maintains that the inflation rate might rise
over 2%, but that this should only be temporary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only uncertainty in all of this is if, or whether &lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt;, the federal reserve
would increase the interest rate in response to inflation increasing. The price
move caused such an uproar because the federal reserved had been saying (and has
kept saying since) that they don&amp;#39;t expect to increase the rate anytime soon and
that it&amp;#39;s fine if &amp;quot;the economy runs hot&amp;quot; and inflation is temporarily increased.
The bond market seemed to be saying that either the situation would be worse
than the fed expected, forcing its hand, or that, under pressure from the
markets, it couldn&amp;#39;t walk the line (as seen in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/t/taper-tantrum.asp&quot;&gt;2013 &amp;quot;taper
tantrum&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the move was initiated, however, it made sense for most people to follow
suit. Whether you&amp;#39;re a trader or a long-term investor in long-term bonds, you
expect the rates to increase eventually, meaning it will be profitable for you
to sell your bonds and buy new higher-rate bonds. If the bond price starts to
drop, you should therefore sell. In fact, the only reasons not to sell are if
either you don&amp;#39;t believe the rates will increase or if you&amp;#39;re contractually
obligated to hold bonds instead of cash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on top of this strong fundamental reason, there were a few other catalysts
and technical details that can help explain the sudden move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A first catalyst (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-02-26/chaotic-treasury-selloff-fueled-by-50-billion-position-unwind&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in April, the Federal Reserve tweaked its rules to exempt Treasuries from
banks’ supplementary leverage ratios — allowing them to expand their balance
sheets with U.S. debt. But that relief ends March 31 and what happens next is
something of a mystery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it was expected that by April 2021, banks would have offloaded excess bonds
to get back in cash and satisfy the re-tightened rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;bonds-butterfly&quot;&gt;Bonds Butterfly&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all these bearish expectations towards bonds, the market just needed
something to light the fuse. The catalyst was probably an auction of 7-year
bonds seeing record low demand. Remember from &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds&quot;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt; that bonds are
initially auctioned by the fed, so low demand would have caused these bonds have
a low price and a high yield. This in turn caused the associated but more common
5-year bonds to drop a whopping 0.75%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This made a lot of people happy, as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://finance.zacks.com/butterfly-fixed-income-trading-strategies-10170.html&quot;&gt;2-5-10 butterfly&lt;/a&gt; is a popular
trade:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The butterfly strategy involves buying both long and short-term bonds while
simultaneously selling medium-term bonds. This strategy is designed to help
investors profit from predicted fluctuations to the yield curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;... The purchase and sales cancel each other out, making this a theoretically
zero-cost investment. This has the impact of cancelling out any shifts in the
overall values of the bonds unless the shifts are disproportionately weighted
to one maturity over another. When disproportionate shifts occur, the investor
can earn a net return. ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One common butterfly trade involves three treasury bonds. The investor sells
five-year treasuries and buys two- and ten-year bonds with the money that he
receives in a proportion that makes the average life of the portfolio equal to
five years. To do this, the portfolio would be slightly more heavily weighted
towards the two-year bond. To begin with, the idea is for the blended yield of
the two- and ten-year bonds to be higher than the five-year bond&amp;#39;s yield. The
other advantage of the butterfly is that if the relationship in yields
changes, it could increase returns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It must be noted how &lt;a href=&quot;https://theirrelevantinvestor.com/2021/03/01/will-higher-interest-rates-kill-growth-stocks/&quot;&gt;remarkable&lt;/a&gt; these events are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tracy Alloway notes that, “The 2/5/10-year butterfly — a popular trade
involving two-, five- and 10-year U.S. bonds — moved by an astonishing 24
basis points (one of those events which, when measured by standard deviations,
is only supposed to happen once in a billion years, etc.).”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds-2/butterfly.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture: 2-5-10 butterfly expected returns&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I assume happened next is that traders unwound their positions to
capitalize on this sudden dip in the 5-years price. Since they were long
10-years bonds, that caused that price to also dip suddenly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s hard — if not impossible — to tell, but this might have been the initial
shock that set the yield surge in motion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;shorting&quot;&gt;Shorting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another straightforward force multiplier to the move was short selling. I
talked about short selling in &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/gamestop&quot;&gt;my article on Gamestop&lt;/a&gt;, but basically
bond short-sellers borrow bonds, sell them, wait for the price to drop to buy
them back and return them to the original owner, pocketing the difference as
profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was ample evidence of short selling in the bonds market. In particular,
the repo market rate for the 10-years bond went to -4% at some point... The what
now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repo or &amp;quot;repurchase agreement&amp;quot; market is where one party sells a security to
another, and agrees to repurchase it later at a higher price. Essentially, it&amp;#39;s
a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Collateral_(finance)&quot;&gt;collateralized loan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repo market allows financial institutions that own lots of securities (e.g.
banks, broker-dealers, hedge funds) to borrow cheaply and allows parties with
lots of spare cash (e.g. money market mutual funds) to earn a small return on
that cash without much risk, because securities, often U.S. Treasury securities,
serve as collateral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repo market allows financial institutions that own lots of securities (e.g.
banks, broker-dealers, hedge funds) to borrow cheaply and allows parties with
lots of spare cash (e.g. money market mutual funds) to earn a small return on
that cash without much risk, because securities, often U.S. Treasury securities,
serve as collateral. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brookings.edu/blog/up-front/2020/01/28/what-is-the-repo-market-and-why-does-it-matter/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The repo rate typically trades in line with the Federal Reserve’s benchmark
federal funds rate at which banks lend reserves to each other overnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact it went to -4% means that people were willing to pay up to 4% interest
for the privilege to borrow 10 years bonds, with the intention to short them and
turn a profit. In that market, 4% is a lot, meaning there was a lot of
competitive pressure, hence a lot of short selling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait! That&amp;#39;s not all. We have another villain in our story in the form of
&lt;em&gt;convexity hedging&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;duration-convexity--convexity-hedging&quot;&gt;Duration, Convexity &amp;amp; Convexity Hedging&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some funds invest in mortgage-backed securities (MBS). Yes, those that caused
the great financial crisis and gave us the delightful movie &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vgqG3ITMv1Q&quot;&gt;The Big Short&lt;/a&gt;
— check &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xbiDrzTd8fE&quot;&gt;this excerpt&lt;/a&gt; if you want Ryan Gosling to explain bad
mortgage-backed securities to you. What a time to be alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, when interest rates decrease, homeowners can refinance their mortgages
to lock in a lower rate. This involves paying off part of the remaining loan
immediately (hence it is called &lt;em&gt;prepaying&lt;/em&gt;). This shortens the mortgages, and
as a result the average length of mortgages in the MBS decreases. This causes
the &lt;em&gt;duration&lt;/em&gt; — the weighted average of the times until when cash flows (loan
repayments) are received — to go down. The opposite is also true: when interest
rates increase, people don&amp;#39;t refinance, and so the average length of mortgages
goes up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explain how that impacts the bond market, we need to lay some groundwork.
Bonds have a property called &lt;em&gt;convexity&lt;/em&gt; — when the interest rate decreases, the
price increases more than proportionally, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds-2/convexity.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture: Illustration of convexity in bond prices&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reminder:&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;#39;s always been unintuitive to me that bond price should rise
when interest fall (shouldn&amp;#39;t it be the opposite?). So let&amp;#39;s tackle that
first, then we can tackle the question of proportionality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To key is that the rate increase will only affect newly emitted bonds. The
yield must be constant across all bonds with the same maturity (otherwise
it&amp;#39;s an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/a/arbitrage.asp&quot;&gt;arbitrage&lt;/a&gt; opportunity). Adding new bonds with lower interest rates
tends to push the yield down, hence the price of existing bonds up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not obvious that it would push the yield down. After all, a lackluster
auction could bid the new bonds up just enough so that the existing yield
doesn&amp;#39;t move. It doesn&amp;#39;t seem to work like that in practice, and I suspect
it&amp;#39;s due to the new bonds shifting the expected future yield. As older,
higher-interest, bonds expire and newer, lower-interest, bonds are introduced,
it does make sense to expect the average yield to go down — at least when
ignoring fluctuations in the bond market, and excluding the possibility of a
sudden paradigm shift in bond valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So decreasing rates push bond price up. Why do they increase more than
proportionally to the decrease in rates? In one word: compounding — when the
yield moves, the price move must capture not only the change in coupon payments
but the proceeds of reinvesting these payments. For this reason, longer-term
bonds are more convex: more interest is being paid. At this point, I&amp;#39;m ready to
launch in a long, fascinating (uhm) mathematical digression on yields,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bond_duration&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/a&gt;, compounding and [present value calculations], but this isn&amp;#39;t really
the point of this piece. Maybe another time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So bonds have &lt;em&gt;convexity&lt;/em&gt;. Mortgage-backed securities, on the other hand, have
&lt;em&gt;negative convexity&lt;/em&gt; (not sure why they didn&amp;#39;t call this &amp;quot;concavity&amp;quot;, but
whatever). This means that as the interest rates fall, the price increase less
than proportionally, or even fall!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, why would the prices go up? Same reason that the bond yields go up (see
above). Since government bonds are the ultimate risk-free security, most other
rates in the market depend on them, and will be higher. The difference between
the yield for a financial product and the risk-free rate (the bond yield) is
called &lt;em&gt;the risk premium&lt;/em&gt;. So if bond yields go up, MBS yields are expected to
follow suit (at least if we assume that the reason that the yields went up has
no material impact on the mortgage market and the default rate).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason MBS prices go up less than proportionally (and in any case, less than
bond prices) is that, as we said at the start of this section, decreased rates
increase mortgage refinancing, which decreases MBS duration — the weighted (by
monetary amount) average time of received cashflows (loan repayments). More
refinancing and prepaying means less interest payments, though we will recover a
larger part of the principal earlier. What the MBS did offer us however was a
certain yield (based on the mortgage rate). When the duration decrease, we lose
on that yield, and must reinvest the prepaid sums elsewhere — right after the
interest rates went down! This loss in compound interest is what causes MBS
prices to rise less than expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, bonds have convexity, mortgage-backed securities have negative convexity.
What is convexity hedging? It has to do with the facts that the funds that own
these MBS include things like pension funds, which have regular cash outflows
(e.g. to pay said pensions). This means the cashflows need to be regular. But
MBS cashflows vary with interest rates!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take care of that unpredictability, these funds hedge for &lt;em&gt;duration&lt;/em&gt;. Here&amp;#39;s
how they do it: When interest rates increase, MBS duration increases, and funds
sell long-term bonds to cover liquidity needs; when rates decrease, MBS duration
decreases, and funds reinvest prepayments into long-term bonds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to our initial topic, the net effect is that when interest rates increase,
MBS duration increases, which leads to funds selling off bonds to hedge
duration. The opposite happens when interest rates decrease. This naturally
amplifies the movement of bonds in either direction (as the bond price is
already on the upswing when interest rates decrease).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with that, we completed our tour of the plausible reasons for the February
bond yield surge! Now we need to briefly examinate how this impacted the stock
market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;inflation-redux&quot;&gt;Inflation Redux&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inflation means that money loses value. With inflation, a dollar in a year is
worth less than a dollar today. In an ideal world of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Spherical_cow&quot;&gt;spherical cows&lt;/a&gt;, all
prices and wages would update instantly to reflect this new value of money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If inflation worked like that, it would cause very little trouble. Sure, if
you&amp;#39;re holding cash, you&amp;#39;re suddenly poorer in terms of purchasing power.
Conversely, if you&amp;#39;re holding debt, you&amp;#39;re suddenly &amp;quot;richer&amp;quot; because your
repayments are worth less — and your revenues increased proportionally to
inflation anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas, prices do not update instantly, and it&amp;#39;s precisely this transition process
that is painful. Inflation works in wave. The first goods whose price increase
are those whose price is very liquid. The best example is commodities: ores,
oil, grains, etc. In fact, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/billconerly/2021/05/22/why-lumber-and-plywood-prices-are-so-high-and-when-they-will-come-down/&quot;&gt;flare up in lumber price&lt;/a&gt; has been in
the news quite a bit recently. It&amp;#39;s probably unrelated to inflation, but it
shows how fast these prices can move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commodities are the very beginning of the supply chains involved in the
production of most goods. This means that, in the presence of inflation, the
increase in price slowly cascades through the supply chain. The increase in
price is not reflected immediately for two big reasons: existing commitments and
competition. If you already signed a contract to supply a good at a certain
price, you&amp;#39;re stuck. If you&amp;#39;re in a very dynamic market and you can change your
price, you might still not want to do so, because your competitors might not
have done so yet, and you&amp;#39;ll lose customers to them. Of course, they&amp;#39;ll have to
raise prices too eventually, but these effects slow down the price cascade —
it&amp;#39;s a coordination problem. Where commodities are concerned, there&amp;#39;s also
uncertainty as though whether a price increase is just a spike (possibly fueled
by speculation (*1)), or a more permanent shift.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the supply chain lies the final customer, the individual.
Unfortunately, wages are typically the last thing to increase in the inflation
process. This is because the price increase takes quite some time to reach final
consumers, and because the profits of a company must increase (after it can
reflect inflation in the price it charges) before it starts paying employees
more. And companies will tend to increase pay, if only to get a competitive
advantage by poaching promising talent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(*1) This kind of speculation has, of course, unpleasant side-effects, such as
making lumber more expensive for those that have a genuine use for it. However,
I want to emphasize that this is the cost you pay for having an efficient
market, and an efficient market does buy you something. In particular, it
greatly reduces the time for inflation to cascade through the system, and hence
the economic pain that results from it. This is what the next section is all
about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-inflation-does-to-companies&quot;&gt;What inflation does to companies&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So inflation is a painful transition towards higher prices caused by a loss of
value of the currency. Inflation occurs when the balance of money and goods
shifts in the direction of there being more money and/or less goods. In the
current situation, there is more money in circulation due to stimulus and
massive public spending (*2), and a modest deficit for goods whose supply
chains were shut down during the Covid pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(*2) At least in the United States, though it seems likely that other parts of
the world will suffer from, at least, a milder version of the same problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The consequence of this on companies is that they will go through a transition
period where their expenses will increase, but their revenues do not increase in
kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What, then, does inflation do to the valuation of companies? We mentioned two
things already. First, there is an impact on the balance sheet: cash loses
value, but so do debts. Second, there is a loss of profit due to price lag. In
some cases, those are straightforward to compute. In some cases not so much. On
top of this, there is the concern that this will put too much strain on the
company&amp;#39;s finance, which will have to borrow at unattractive rates or, in the
worst case, be forced to liquidate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So inflation is bad for everyone; but depending on balance sheet composition,
position within the supply chain and general financial health, it is worse for
some companies than for other. But wait — hasn&amp;#39;t the S&amp;amp;P 500 has been making
consistent all-time highs since the events of February?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, to understand why growth stock got hammered in February, we need to
look beyond just the fundamental prices in the growth, and into the theory of
stock valuation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;equity-risk-premiums-and-hurdle-rate&quot;&gt;Equity Risk Premiums and Hurdle Rate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pricing the stock of a company is more art than science (otherwise they wouldn&amp;#39;t
constantly be swinging around even when absolutely nothing of substance
happens). Nevertheless, many theoretical frameworks have been proposed to try to
explain the factors that underly stock prices, and to try to estimate what a
&amp;quot;reasonable&amp;quot; stock price may be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is quite the rabbit hole, and if you&amp;#39;re interested, the best place to start
is Aswath Damodaran&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLUkh9m2BorqlJsEfix7R9jtSXClFZhGvC&quot;&gt;valuation course&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two concepts that are particularly useful in analyzing the price of stocks are
the notion of &lt;em&gt;equity risk premium&lt;/em&gt; and that of &lt;em&gt;hurdle rate&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The equity risk premium is the (expected or actual) return on equities in excess
to that of the risk-free alternatives. Typically, treasury bonds are used as the
risk-free alternatives, the 10-year rate being the most commonly used. So if
10-year bonds have a 2% yield, and the stock market (for instance, the S&amp;amp;P 500
index) returned 12%, then the equity risk premium was 10%. Typically, the equity
risk premium is calculated on historical data; there is obviously no guarantee
going into the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s the &lt;em&gt;equity risk premium&lt;/em&gt;, but the concept of &lt;em&gt;risk premium&lt;/em&gt; generalizes
to other financial asset and even to sub-classes of stock. Of particular
interest to us here is the risk premium for growth stocks and the risk premium
for value stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recall that value stocks are stocks who trade in line with a valuation
obtained through some kind of &lt;em&gt;fundamental analysis&lt;/em&gt; process. The most common
of which is to use discounted flash flows (DCF): computing the present value
of the expected net profits of the company for some future period (typically
10 to 20 years). This approach is of course only applicable to profitable
companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Growth stocks, on the other hand, are companies whose revenues are growing a
lot (or are deemed to be poised to grow a lot), but who may not yet be
profitable. The valuation is based on future expectations of growth — which
may not come to pass and can sometimes be a bit too optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the name implies, risk premiums are rewards for risk. Growth stocks are
riskier than value stocks, and so should command a higher risk premium. But what
is this &amp;quot;risk&amp;quot; we talk about? Consider that a risk premium is an average
computed on a basket of stock (or on an index) over a certain period of time.
Risk can be seen as the variance between the stocks in the basket, and the
variance over time. Growth stocks, for instance, are particularly risky: most
innovative companies end up failing, but those who survive tend to have
extraordinary growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second important concept is the &lt;em&gt;hurdle rate&lt;/em&gt;, which is simply the expected
return you demand to take on some amount of risk. Everybody will have its own
hurdle rates for different level of risks, though it tends to depend on possible
alternative uses of capital and risk-free rates of returns. Just like the risk
premium, the hurdle rate increases with perceived risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting the two concerns together is straightforward. Given a class of assets
(e.g. growth stocks) and their associated risks, you come up with a hurdle rate
(the return required to convince you to invest in the asset) and a risk premium
(the return you expect to earn on top of the risk-free rate). If the total
expected return for the asset (risk-free rate + risk premium) is higher than the
hurdle rate, you invest, otherwise you don&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want a deeper and more data-driven take on inflation and stock valuation,
I recommend &lt;a href=&quot;http://aswathdamodaran.blogspot.com/2021/03/rates-growth-and-value-investment.html&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; by Aswath Damodaran. I don&amp;#39;t
pretend to understand all of it, but it makes very interesting points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-happened-to-growth-stocks&quot;&gt;So what happened to growth stocks?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be a stretch to say that, as bond yields rose, investors recomputed
their hurdle rate up (because the risk-free rate was up) and their expected risk
premium down (because inflation was likely, cutting into profits).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But on the other hand... Everyone knew that valuations in the growth segment
were historically high on any metric that you cared to consider. This meant the
category was particularly risky. Inflation comes in and maybe the risk is now
too high given the potential rewards. Better to lock in some profit. This is
essentially the hurdle/premium process, but perceived intuitively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we also have to mention that inflation might be particularly bad
for the typically non-profitable growth companies, as it impedes their ability
to raise money. Not only does inflation expectation increase the interest rate
on debt, but it means that the money you borrow has lost value by the time you
spend it. Inflation also negatively affects the ability to raise cash via stock
sales: reflectively from the above, we expect inflation to negatively impact the
stock price, which mean that less money will be generated by selling (so you
need to sell more of it, which negatively impacts the stock price, ...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always whenever we talk markets, we have to consider force multipliers and
momentum. As growth stocks sold off in February, it became clear this that this
was not a mere fluctuation but a full-blown correction. This causes stockholders
that had not reacted to the bond market to start selling too, in reaction to the
price movement, but for the same reasons: the upside of continuing to hold
longer is limited compared to the immediate risk embedded in the downward trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big moves in the stock market are also driven by de-leveraging: if you purchased
stock &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margin_(finance)&quot;&gt;on margin&lt;/a&gt;, a sudden price drop forces you to sell stock to maintain your
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.firstrade.com/content/en-us/education/margin/marginrequirements/&quot;&gt;margin requirements&lt;/a&gt; and avoid &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margin_(finance)#Margin_call&quot;&gt;margin calls&lt;/a&gt;. This is especially relevant
since margin debt levels are historically high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds-2/margin-debt.png&quot; alt=&quot;picture: Margin debt chart&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The margin debt level may be in line with the S&amp;amp;P 500 price, but note that you
would expect the debt ratio to decrease as stock prices go up. If you buy 5k$
worth of stock at 5:1 leverage (so fronting 1k$ of your own cash, taking a 4k$
margin debt), and the stock goes up 20%, your stock is now worth 6k$ and your
leverage ratio is now 3:1 (stock worth 6k$, of which 2k$ is not debt). One
&lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; interpretation of the chart is that as stock prices go up investors
reinvesting the profits with leverage (i.e. they maintain a constant leverage
ratio). Note that the chart also does not say where the leverage is deployed
(across the stock market? or is it concentrated in certain stocks?). In the end,
it seems that leverage will accentuate any &amp;quot;natural&amp;quot; price move, both in the up
and down directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what happened? What have we learned?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bond prices decreases and the yield rose, driven by inflation expectations. A
series of events catalyzed (the 7-year bond auction) and amplified (the
butterfly trade, convexity hedging) this change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect spilled over to the stock market, where it was mostly driven by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/marketsentiment.asp&quot;&gt;sentiment&lt;/a&gt;, reflecting both the increased risk-free rate and the lowered return
expectations due to inflation. Because growth stocks&amp;#39; valuations were stretched,
that was all it took to tip this segment of the market into a correction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When these events transpired, I did not get how inflation and the bond market
could influence stock valuation to this extent. In fact, some of my intuitions
were to the opposite. For instance, since companies will keep making money in
the future, shouldn&amp;#39;t inflation push the stock price up to reflect the future
revenue increase due to higher prices?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also looking for a technical explanation (based on some mechanics of the
financial markets), whereas the move seems to have mostly been driven by
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/marketsentiment.asp&quot;&gt;sentiment&lt;/a&gt; and risk-reward considerations. This happened on the heels of the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/gamestop&quot;&gt;Gamestop gamma squeeze&lt;/a&gt;, which had a straightforward technical explanation, so
there might be some &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Availability_heuristic&quot;&gt;availability bias&lt;/a&gt; there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this article, you might enjoy other articles about &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;finance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-06-05T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/bonds-2</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/bonds-2</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freaking blockchains: How do they work?</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;in &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;Finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cryptocurrency hype is at its peak, blockchains are on every lips. Since I
started writing this, Bitcoin &amp;amp; assorted cryptocurrencies hit multiple all-time
highs then crashed 50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides all the sound and fury, I think I have something interesting and nuanced
to say about blockchains and cryptocurrencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also believe that to understand the topic, one has to understand the basics of
the technology, more precisely than most articles make allowance for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contrary to popular belief, blockchain technology is not that complicated. I
dare say it&amp;#39;s even quite simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in this article I explain the technology. I will tell you what it does, but
not what the practical applications are, nor whether I think the technology has
a future, whether it&amp;#39;s a scam, or whether cryptocurrency prices are justified. I
will, however, tackle all these topics in a follow-up article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-a-blockchain&quot;&gt;What&amp;#39;s a blockchain?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blockchain is a decentralized ledger of transactions. It&amp;#39;s a kind of permanent
log: once a transaction makes it into the log, it will remain there forever.
Note that the concept can be extended to log more than financial transactions,
but we&amp;#39;ll use transactions as an example in this write-up, where users can
transfer digital coin currency, also called &lt;em&gt;tokens&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes blockchains special is that they are truly decentralized in the sense
that anybody can join &lt;em&gt;the network&lt;/em&gt; that monitors and mirrors the state of the
blockchain — such participants are called &lt;em&gt;nodes&lt;/em&gt;. Some nodes additionally
participate in the consensus process to verify the transactions that make it
onto the ledger. In the &lt;em&gt;proof-of-work&lt;/em&gt; scheme used by Bitcoin, such nodes are
called &lt;em&gt;miners&lt;/em&gt;. And again, everybody can become a miner. We&amp;#39;ll also tackle the
main alternative, &lt;em&gt;proof-of-stake&lt;/em&gt;, later in this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &amp;quot;blockchain&amp;quot; is called so because the ledger is composed of a chain of
&amp;quot;blocks&amp;quot;, each of which encodes many transactions. Miners in the network collect
transactions, verify their validity, pack them in a block, then try to validate
this block. In proof-of-work, this is calling &lt;em&gt;mining&lt;/em&gt; the block (in
proof-of-stake, it&amp;#39;s simply called &lt;em&gt;proposing&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;creating&lt;/em&gt; the block).
Whenever a node mines/proposes a block that is accepted by the network, it
receives a reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/blockchain-how/blockchain.png&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/blockchain-how/blockchain.png&quot; alt=&quot;proof-of-work overview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Click to open bigger version in a new page. Image source:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bitpanda.com/academy/fr/lecons/comment-fonctionne-une-blockchain/&quot;&gt;Bitpanda&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, a transaction is considered valid if it is signed by the
cryptographic key associated with the source&amp;#39;s address (a crypto address is a
little bit like a bank account number), if it&amp;#39;s legal with respect to the
address&amp;#39; token balance, and if the transaction did not previously appear in
another block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cases where an address spends the same tokens twice is called a
&lt;em&gt;double-spend&lt;/em&gt;. As we&amp;#39;ll see in a subsequent article, this is the principal
attack vector against blockchains. This is distinct from duplicating a
transaction, which might still be legal with respect to balances, but if
allowed, would allow miners to siphon off the funds from an address that
previously sent them tokens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To mine/validate a block, it is not sufficient to create and verify the block —
it must also be accepted as part of the blockchain. This is achieved through a
consensus protocol.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In computer science, we call a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_(computer_science)&quot;&gt;consensus protocol&lt;/a&gt; a protocol that lets a set
of nodes make a decision that is eventually accepted by the whole network. This
is typically based on some form of majority voting. We also know, to some
extent, how to guard against malicious nodes who lie to try to get their own
choice selected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this only works if the network participants are pre-established. In an
open network, a malicious actor could just create a huge number of nodes to get
a de facto majority — this is called a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sybil_attack&quot;&gt;sibyl attack&lt;/a&gt;. To tackle this issue,
blockchains must make it &amp;quot;expensive&amp;quot; to validate blocks. In reality, validation
must be profitable: that&amp;#39;s the incentive for miners/validators to participate in
securing the network. But when we say that validation should be &amp;quot;expensive&amp;quot;, we
mean it must be &lt;em&gt;capital-intensive&lt;/em&gt;. Because it costs money to validate blocks,
it becomes much more difficult to assemble enough mining or staking power to
mount a sibyl attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In proof-of-work blockchains, miners compete against each other to be the first
to validate a block. There is a sort of number-guessing contest going on based
on expensive computations (we&amp;#39;ll explain it shortly), and the winner gets to
mine the block and collect a reward. Miners buy specialized mining devices to be
able to run the expensive computations as fast as possible. Statistically
speaking, if you control X% of the mining power, you&amp;#39;ll get X% of the mining
rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;number guessing game&amp;quot; in question is made computationally expensive
through the use of &lt;em&gt;cryptographic hash functions&lt;/em&gt; (details will follow). To
the best of my knowledge, this is the reason for the &lt;em&gt;crypto&lt;/em&gt; in
&lt;em&gt;cryptocurrencies&lt;/em&gt;. It could also refer to the use of cryptographic keys to
sign transactions, but this is a fairly old technology whose use was already
pervasive when blockchains were introduced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In proof-of-stake, validators must lock some amount of on-chain currency (their
&lt;em&gt;stake&lt;/em&gt;). The protocol then selects which validator gets to validate the next
block. If you control X% of the total stake, you&amp;#39;ll be select with X%
probability. Note that this is not the only way to implement proof-of-stake, but
it is the simplest to understand, and it gives the right idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&amp;#39;t mentionned where these rewards come from. In both cases, they&amp;#39;re a
combination of both currency creation where the miner/validator might be granted
some amount of newly minted tokens, and transactions fees paid by the users
whose transactions end up on the block. Bitcoin famously has a supply limit,
where eventually only transactions fees will remain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently, most blockchains use proof-of-work, including #1 and #2
cryptocurrencies Bitcoin and Ethereum. A few minor blockchains use
proof-of-stake, and Ethereum has planned to transition to proof-of-stake. We
will now give more details about them, starting with proof-of-work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;proof-of-work---hashing&quot;&gt;Proof of Work - Hashing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In proof-of-work, mining is done by solving a cryptographic problem. In
particular, miners have to calculate a valid hash for the block. You can think
of a hash as a fingerprint for the block. More precisely, a hash is the result
of applying a hash function to some data (here, the block). Such a fingerprint
is really nothing else than a (potentially very large) number, encoded on 256
bits (which allows to represent 2^256 values, which is 1 followed by 77 zeroes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For blockchains, we use a &lt;em&gt;cryptographic hash function&lt;/em&gt;. Those have the
requirement that they should be irreversible (it is impossible to guess the
block content from the hash), and in general &amp;quot;look random&amp;quot; — it&amp;#39;s very important
that knowing the hash for a block does not give us any advantage in finding the
hash for a very slightly different block. Finally, a cryptographic function
should also be somewhat expensive to compute, so that it is difficult to guess
the data (e.g. the block, or the password) that generated the hash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crypto Trivia 1&lt;/strong&gt;: Did you know that most websites do not store your password?
Instead they store a hash of your password. When you login, they hash the
password you submit, and compare it to the hash they stored. That way, if the
website is compromised, the attacker only gets the hash of your password.
Since he can&amp;#39;t invert the hash, your password is safe, and the attacker can&amp;#39;t
use the hash to log on other websites. ... Or at least that&amp;#39;s what we&amp;#39;d hope.
In reality, getting the hash makes it easier to guess a password through the
use of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rainbow_table&quot;&gt;rainbow tables&lt;/a&gt;, which is why the website should hash your password
along with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salt_(cryptography)&quot;&gt;salt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Crypto Trivia 2&lt;/strong&gt;: Since the block is much bigger than the hash (in
Bitcoin&amp;#39;s case, most blocks are 1MB and a hash is 256 bits), it means that
there can exist many more different blocks than different hashes. This means
that, by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pigeonhole_principle&quot;&gt;the pigeonhole principle&lt;/a&gt;, it is possible for two blocks to hash to
the same value. This is fine here, and is fine for most uses of hashing. Just
note that our &amp;quot;fingerprints&amp;quot; are not necessarily unique. However such a
collision has a probability of 1/(2 followed by 59 zeros). It&amp;#39;s pretty rare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So proof-of-work consists of finding the hash of the block. Normally this is an
easy task. But in blockchains it involves a guessing component. The block&amp;#39;s data
contains all the transactions, but also a reference to the previous block
(actually, the &lt;strong&gt;hash&lt;/strong&gt; of the previous block) and a random number called
&lt;em&gt;nonce&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/blockchain-how/block-format.png&quot; alt=&quot;Bitcoin block format&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Image source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.scottlogic.com/2016/04/04/jenny-from-the-blockchain.html&quot;&gt;Scott Logic&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt; proof-of-work has to solve is as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;nonce = random 32 bit number
h1 = hash(block including nonce)
h2 = hash(h1 concatenated with nonce)
... such that h2 &amp;gt; difficulty
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we pick a nonce and hash the block which contains this nonce. Then we append
the nonce to this first hash, and hash that to get a second hash. The problem is
solved only this second hash is higher than a set number, called &lt;em&gt;the
difficulty&lt;/em&gt;. If the condition is not fulfilled, the process starts again with
another nonce, until the problem is solved or someone else mined a block — in
which case we need to update the previous block&amp;#39;s hash, as well as the list of
transactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficulty is set by the protocol, and determines how difficult it is to
solve the problem. For instance, Bitcoin adjusts it so that the average time
between each mined block remains around 10 minutes. Because a hash is a 256-bit
string, it can be interpreted as a number between 0 and 2^256. So if the
difficulty was 3/4 * 2^256 and hashes are uniformly distributed (which a
cryptographic hash function should ensure), this would exclude 3/4 of the valid
hashes. In reality, the difficulty is much much higher than that. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.bitcoin.com/clocking-terahash-three-next-generation-bitcoin-mining-rigs-launched-during-the-last-quarter/&quot;&gt;bitcoin
mining machine&lt;/a&gt; that can perform about 100 tera-hash per second (*) costs about
4000$!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(*) That&amp;#39;s 100 trillion — or about 2^47 — hashes per second. I&amp;#39;m not sure if
that number designates actual hash function calls or attempted nonces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Math Trivia&lt;/strong&gt;: Assuming the difficult is indeed 3/4 * 2^256, how many
nonce would we have to try to find a valid hash, on average?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/206798/&quot;&gt;this formula&lt;/a&gt; to answer the question, and the answer
happens to be approximately 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Thanks Andrew Gord Stewart for catching a mistake in this section!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So proof-of-work mining takes a lot of computational power to perform all these
hashes. This costs a lot of money, both as upfront machine costs and as energy
costs. This is all by design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, consuming a lot of energy is not ideal in a world where we&amp;#39;re trying to
stop global warming. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cbeci.org/cbeci/comparisons&quot;&gt;At the time of writing&lt;/a&gt;, the energy expended
annually on mining bitcoin is greater than the annual energy expenditure of
Sweden, and account for 0.6% of the globe&amp;#39;s total energy production. I&amp;#39;ve also
read that every Ethereum transaction currently consumes enough energy to power
an average household for 24 hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This can be caveated a little bit by saying that miners are after cheap energy,
and excess energy is the cheapest energy. It&amp;#39;s also possible for miners to build
renewable energy plants to power their mining rigs — though this also comes with
an environmental cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The energy consumption &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; not turn out to be a deal-breaker, but it&amp;#39;s far
from ideal. That&amp;#39;s one of the issues addressed by &lt;em&gt;proof-of-stake&lt;/em&gt;. But first,
let&amp;#39;s talk about consensus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;proof-of-work---consensus&quot;&gt;Proof of Work - Consensus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so miners compete in a hashing contest and, generally speaking, the first
miner to find a valid nonce for his block &amp;quot;wins&amp;quot;. Now we need to explain how
that happen, i.e. how this valid block is disseminated and eventually accepted
on the network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a simple scenario, the winning miner sends the block to all the other nodes
he knows. These will verify that the block is valid: all the transactions have
valid signatures, there are no double-spends, and the hash of the block
satisfies the difficulty requirement. Once this is done, they further
disseminate the block, and they append it at the end of their local chain. If
the node is a miner, he will also restart its mining efforts by creating a new
candidate block — the block he is currently attempting to mine does include the
hash of a block that is no longer the last in the chain, as well as transactions
that might have already been included in the block submitted by the winning
miner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, one could have a security question: what prevents miners from
completely ignoring blocks from their competitors in an attempt to mine their own
block? There is a neat game-theoretic incentive not to do this: If you assume
everyone else is honest, they will append this competitor block to their chain.
That means that even if you manage to mine your alternative block, other nodes
will reject it because it does not contain the hash of what they consider to be
the latest block in the chain (the block submitted by your competitor). What if
everyone cheats? We&amp;#39;ll explain later, but there is no incentive to do this, as
that makes all the profits go to the biggest miner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s tackle the hard case: what if two miners mine a valid block at more or
less the same time? Only one of the two blocks can win, since they include the
hash of the same previous block, and their set of transactions might overlap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, the rule used by nodes is to always favor the longest chain. Of
course, initially, the two blocks create two competing chains of equal length.
Miners will have to decide which block to use as base for the next block they
will attempt to mine (most likely they will select the block they saw first,
reasoning that other miners are more likely to also have seen this block first —
though that might not be the case because of network delays). Once a miner comes
up with a valid block on one of the two chains, that chain gains the upper hand,
and everyone converges on the same chain. Of course, it&amp;#39;s possible for the
scenario to repeat and the two chains to grow at about the same time, but this
is very unlikely and grows more unlikely as the competing chains grow. Remember
that the Bitcoin protocol adapts so that a new block is mined on average every
10 minutes: it should be rare for two blocks to be mined mere seconds away from
one another, and it will be exponentially rarer for that to happen multiple
times in a row.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This longest-chain rule is also why it is irrational for miners to just
ignore other blocks: if everybody mined their own chain, the largest miner would
always be able to overtake the others with a longer chain, and so all the
non-mining nodes would converge on that chain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The longest-chain rule is not infaillible: if an entity can get control of 51%
of the mining power, they&amp;#39;re able to mount a &lt;em&gt;51% attack&lt;/em&gt; which allows them to
double spend. We&amp;#39;ll talk about those in details in a subsequent article. Note
that 51% attacks are at least fairly easy to spot on non-anonymized blockchains
(which is most of them).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/blockchain-how/51attack.png&quot; alt=&quot;A 51% attack&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Above, a schematic representation of a 51% attack, where the attacker conceals
his mining and then release his blocks all at once to overtake the main chain.
(source: &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethresear.ch/t/timeliness-detectors-and-51-attack-recovery-in-blockchains/6925&quot;&gt;Vitalik
Buterin&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;proof-of-stake&quot;&gt;Proof of Stake&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we said earlier, proof-of-stake is another scheme to make validating blocks
capital-intensive enough so that it&amp;#39;s impractical for any single actor to
dominate the network, and impossible to mount a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sybil_attack&quot;&gt;sibyl attack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In proof-of-work, the hardware and energy costs make mining capital intensive.
In proof-of-stake, we simply have validators put money on the line directly. And
because cryptocurrencies are essentially money, that&amp;#39;s rather simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In proof-of-stake, validators engage a certain amount of currency, their
&lt;em&gt;stake&lt;/em&gt;, which becomes locked for as long as they participate in the
proof-of-stake mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The incentive structure is identical to proof-of-work. If you control 10% of the
mining power, you should validate 10% of the blocks and get 10% of the mining
rewards. Similarly, if you control 10% of the total stake, you should do 10% of
the verification work and you should get 10% of the validation rewards. The
difference is that instead of using a hashing contest, the protocol must
determine how to distribute rewards to validators according to this
distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are multiple ways to go about this, but the simplest is to use a
pseudo-random scheme to select the next validator that will create a block. As
an illustration, imagine that we filled an urn with 100 balls. On each ball the
name of a validator is written, and each validator gets as many balls as his
percentage of the total stake (of course in reality we need to accommodate many
more validators and very fine-grained fractions). Then we use some data from the
block (we need to make sure validators can&amp;#39;t easily manipulate it), run it
through a cryptographic hash function, and use the resulting hash to select a
ball from the urn. The validator whose name is written on the ball gets to
create the next block, and gets the validation reward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s not quite enough. Other validators need to cosign on the block, otherwise
the block&amp;#39;s creator could double-spend, or even include transactions without a
valid signature. The simplest scheme here is to have all validators verify each
block, and to require a quorum of agreement (e.g. a simple majority, or a 2/3
majority) to validate the block. We can&amp;#39;t require consensus, because that would
open the protocol to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Denial-of-service_attack&quot;&gt;Denial-of-Service (DoS)&lt;/a&gt; attacks, and some validators might
have temporary availability issues. If having every validator vote for every
block is impractical, we can also form &lt;em&gt;committees&lt;/em&gt; to validate individual
blocks. Care must be taken that the validators are randomized properly and that
committees are large enough to minimize the probability that all validators in
the committee are controlled by the same entity. It is commonly required that
this probability should be infinitesimal for validators controlling about 30% of
the stake, and ideally up to 50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/blockchain-how/committees.png&quot; alt=&quot;Committees in the Ethereum Beacon Chain&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pictured above: committees in the Ethereum beacon chain. Image source:
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ethos.dev/beacon-chain/&quot;&gt;ethos.dev&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s another issue: what if the validator designated to create the block
doesn&amp;#39;t answer? We must avoid stalling the chain in that case. One solution is
to assign blocks to time slots. If the designated validator does not propose a
block during its timeslot, the opportunity is lost and another validator gets to
propose a block that will follow the previous valid block.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Systems Trivia&lt;/strong&gt;: The above is not as easy as it sounds, even if
we assume that nodes are able to get highly accurate time information outside
of the blockchain (for instance using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Time_Protocol&quot;&gt;NTP&lt;/a&gt; protocol). This is due to
network delays, which makes the timeslot boundaries blurry. Some nodes may
consider a proposed block to be within its timeslot while others may not.
Therefore, the protocol must take care to handle these boundary conditions so
that the network always converges. It must also avoid unduly penalizing honest
actors because of network latency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to avoid relying on out-of-chain time information, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ethresear.ch/t/network-adjusted-timestamps/4187&quot;&gt;things get
even more difficult&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, we&amp;#39;d like to avoid the scenario where a block is skipped, if only
for reasons of throughput (how many transactions get validated each second).
Ethereum proof-of-stake incentivizes validators to be responsive by imposing a
fine on the stake of absentee validators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s more or less how proof-of-stake works. Unlike proof-of-work, there is a
lot of disparity between the various proposed proof-of-stake designs. This
article offers only a high-level overview, and elides a lot of the details. For
instance, we didn&amp;#39;t even talk about how stakes can be confiscated (&amp;quot;slashed&amp;quot;)
when a validator is caught attempting to cheat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These missing details are best examined in the light of potential attacks
against the protocol, which we will examine in a subsequent blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;coda&quot;&gt;Coda&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article, I presented an incomplete yet detailed technical overview of
the proof-of-work and proof-of-stake protocols used to implement most
blockchains, including the Bitcoin and Ethereum blockchains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important take-away is that blockchains are distributed ledgers built
on top of a network that is open to everyone — this is their main selling point.
Because of this, they must guard against &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sybil_attack&quot;&gt;sibyl attacks&lt;/a&gt; by making validation
capital-intensive so that any single actor is unlikely to control a majority of
the validation capacity. Proof-of-work makes mining capital-intensive by making
validation computationally expensive, while proof-of-stake has validators put
money (in the form of crypto tokens) on the line directly. Both methods must
contend with a series of challenges that involve concerns from distributed
systems, security, and game theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for further posts. Next post will take a step back and look at the
potential and applications of blockchain technologies. A subsequent post will
take a look at the security model and potential attacks against proof-of-work
and proof-of-stake. See you next time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed this? Check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;more finance articles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-05-26T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/blockchain-how</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/blockchain-how</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fun With Incentives</title>
      <description>
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never, ever, think about something else when you should be thinking about the
power of incentives.&lt;br&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/munger-psychology/&quot;&gt;Charlie Munger&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this past month, I had a lot of fun with &lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com&quot;&gt;1729.com&lt;/a&gt;, a
newsletter that pays its members in Bitcoins for performing tasks — which are
typically interesting and will teach you something useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the main things I did so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/proof-of-workout/&quot;&gt;Worked out&lt;/a&gt; (didn&amp;#39;t need them for that,
but it was nice getting 10$ for it!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/learn-basic-elixir-with-exercism/&quot;&gt;Learned some Elixir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/decentralized-task-creation/&quot;&gt;Wrote a task for the newsletter to
reuse&lt;/a&gt; — &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.norswap.com/paving-the-titans-way/&quot;&gt;here&amp;#39;s my
task&lt;/a&gt;. The useful thing in
this one was actually to setup &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cloudron.io/&quot;&gt;cloudron&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oracle.com/be/cloud/&quot;&gt;the
oracle cloud&lt;/a&gt; (not shilling this because I&amp;#39;m
an Oracle employeed, but because I&amp;#39;m cheap and it&amp;#39;s the only one that has a
permanent free tier). Cloudron is a cool service manager that lets you install
a bunch of server apps (including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.org/&quot;&gt;ghost&lt;/a&gt; blog
platform). Don&amp;#39;t worry, I still like my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/norswap.github.io/tree/master/_factory&quot;&gt;homegrown website
generator&lt;/a&gt;
better :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/refer-task-sponsors/&quot;&gt;Cold-emailed some rich people to ask for
money&lt;/a&gt; — not something I&amp;#39;d normally
feel very comfortable doing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/how-to-start-a-new-country/&quot;&gt;Wrote an article expanding on the idea of building a new digital-first
country&lt;/a&gt; — &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghost.norswap.com/new-country/&quot;&gt;here&amp;#39;s my
article&lt;/a&gt;. I must admit I feel a bit
shy about this one, because it&amp;#39;s such an optimistic view — which is not really
my usual personality. But that&amp;#39;s also why it was a useful exercise to get into
a different perspective. It did get me thinking about blockchain technologies
and their potential — expect a more nuanced article on that soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/quantum-computing-and-proof-of-memory/&quot;&gt;Learned about quantum
computing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/video-memes-on-indian-crypto/&quot;&gt;Made a video meme about India&amp;#39;s crypto
ban&lt;/a&gt; — I went for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ecnei9vtLyU&quot;&gt;Hitler
reacts&lt;/a&gt; classic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My submissions got selected on some of these tasks and I got ~220$ out of those
that have been awarded so far. That&amp;#39;s less that I could have earned otherwise in
the same timespan if I was hell-bent on earning money. But as we&amp;#39;ll see below,
that&amp;#39;s not why I did it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are now new tasks to learn about crypto technologies (the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ens.domains/&quot;&gt;Ethereum Name
Service&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://1729.com/learn-solidity-with-cryptozombies/&quot;&gt;learning the solidity smart contract
langauge&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m excited to
do these too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;#39;m actually not writing this to shill 1729. Rather, it&amp;#39;s to marvel about
the power of incentives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See — most of these things I enjoyed doing and might have done without the
possibility of a monetary compensation. But living is prioritizing (if you&amp;#39;re
doing it right at least) and besides working out, none of these things were
high-priority enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But 1729 offered me a collection of incentives to complete the tasks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I may earn some money!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&amp;#39;s a deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;#39;ve attempted all tasks so far, so I&amp;#39;m strongly motivated to attempt new
tasks, for the sake of completion (gamification!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These tasks have generally taught me something, or reinforced some good habit
or useful behaviour.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The tasks have been devised to be doable in a reasonable timeframe — no need
to worry about biting off more than one can chew.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, there was a reason that most of these things were not on my todo
list. But the added incentives were enough to put them past the hump. And the
way I use my time is far from optimal. Had I not, say, written an article, I
might have watched an interesting youtube video instead with no relevance to my
daily life. The incentives stir you towards spending your time smarter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also got me thinking. If 1729 can incentivize me in this way, can&amp;#39;t I do the
same to me? I can certainly chunk task in manageable bits, and set deadlines. I
can also use &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/stop-procrastinating-seinfeld-strategy&quot;&gt;the seinfeld
method&lt;/a&gt; and build
on top of a series of small wins. Paying yourself gets more tricky, however. I
think I know how to make it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key is that I&amp;#39;m cheap. So there are a few not-so-unresonable expenses that I
don&amp;#39;t make because they are not strictly necessary or an improvement to my
day-to-day life. Now say there&amp;#39;s something I want to get done, or a behaviour I
want to promote. If I care enough about that, I can justify paying to speed it
up. On the other end, I get the reward if I complete the task within the
deadline. It&amp;#39;s a smart way to get in alignment with yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a snag though — what if you don&amp;#39;t make the deadline? Do you just put the
reward back in play? As the payer this makes sense — you want the thing done
after all. But on the other end, this is the wrong lesson: you can slip the
deadline but still get the reward (albeit later). I think the key here is to
reward yourself for consistency. So if you slip, the previous reward might be
out of play for the next task, which will grant a smaller (or more generic)
reward. But if you succeed at that one, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; at the next one, then you get the
original reward. That way, you get the nice rewards only if you keep succeeding
consistently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will try to experiment with these micro-incentive structures in the near
future.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-04-29T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/incentives</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/incentives</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bonds Bonanza 1: Bonds Basics</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;in &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;Finance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the second part of February, US treasury bonds yields rose sharply, from
1.13% to more than 1.6%. (If you have no idea what that means, everything will
become clear after reading this article.) While these levels are historically
very low, the move was quite sudden, and this had big repercussions in the stock
market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, it triggered (or accelerated) a &lt;em&gt;rotation into value&lt;/em&gt; where
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/g/growthstock.asp&quot;&gt;growth stocks&lt;/a&gt; got beat down, while &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Value_investing&quot;&gt;value stocks&lt;/a&gt; soared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As previously &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/heat&quot;&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt;, the change caught me by surprise and wiped out
the investment gains I made over the past three months. I didn&amp;#39;t understand —
and to be honest, still don&amp;#39;t really — how these movements in the bond market
could affect the stock market so much. It did cause me to read a lot about the
bond market however, and today I&amp;#39;m sharing what I learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this article I&amp;#39;ll cover the basics of bonds and the bond market. In a
subsequent article, I&amp;#39;ll look at some explanations for the sudden surge of bonds
yield, and finish with some clues about how such bond market moves can impact
the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-bonds-and-how-do-they-work&quot;&gt;What are bonds, and how do they work?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The clearest explanation of the bond market I&amp;#39;ve found is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_Treasury_security#Marketable_securities&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Marketable
Securities&lt;/em&gt; section of the wikipedia page on US bonds&lt;/a&gt;. I encourage
you to read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the US government (like all governments) is partly financed via
debt. The treasury emits &lt;em&gt;treasury securities&lt;/em&gt; of various maturities — from 4
weeks to 30 years. &lt;em&gt;Treasury bonds&lt;/em&gt; are theoretically 30-years securities, but
the terms &amp;quot;treasury bond&amp;quot; is frequently used to refer to all treasury
securities. The most watched security is the 10-years bond — the 1.13% and 1.6%
yield rate mentionned in the intro are 10-years yield rates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bonds have a &lt;em&gt;face value&lt;/em&gt; (e.g. 100$) and a &lt;em&gt;coupon rate&lt;/em&gt;, for instance 2%,
meaning the bond holder is entitled to a 2% payment every year (e.g. 2$ for a
100$ bond). In practice, these payments are made every 6 months, but that&amp;#39;s not
super important. At the end of its maturity period, the bond &amp;quot;matures&amp;quot; and the
&lt;em&gt;principal&lt;/em&gt; (face value) is paid back. Shorter-term bonds (less than 2 years)
have no coupon payments and the coupon is paid in full when the bond matures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More interestingly, you can&amp;#39;t purchase bonds at their face value. In fact, you
can&amp;#39;t purchase bonds directly from the treasury at all — only select
institutional investors (pension funds, banks, etc) can, and they take part in
an auction. This is because the &amp;quot;real&amp;quot; (or rather, estimated) value of a bond
with 100$ face value is not 100$ — it&amp;#39;s 100$ + the present discounted value of
the coupon payments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s that discounted value? Well 1$ in a year is worth less than 1$ now —
because if you had this dollar now you could invest it and maybe have 1.10$ in a
year or something. So the present value of 1$ in one year is the sum that, if
invested today, would grow to 1$ in a year&amp;#39;s time. So for a 100$ bond with 2%
coupon rate, we know it is worth more than 100$, but less than 120$. (*)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After being purchased by an institution, the bond can be traded on the open
market, where its price fluctuates. The price of the bond determines the &lt;em&gt;yield
rate&lt;/em&gt;, which is the rate you can effectively earn by purchasing the bond at the
market price. So for instance, our 100$/2% bond is worth 120$ in 10 years. If
its market price rises to 110$, the effective yearly rate (the yield rate) is
now (120$-110$)/110$ = 0.9%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The somewhat unintuitive effect of this is that the yield goes up when people
sell bonds (and the bond price goes down), and the yield goes down when people
buy bonds (and the bond price goes up).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(*) It&amp;#39;s possible for a 100$ 2% coupon bond to be worth more than 120$, if the
bond has negative yield (negative real returns). While this means that you lose
money holding the bond compared to holding cash, it can happen because
institutional investors may be forced to hold bonds regardless of price. In the
long term, some countries&amp;#39; treasury bonds are also regarded safer than the banks
holding your cash, which may default (this is mostly an issue for institutions,
which manage a boatload of money).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-yield-curve&quot;&gt;The Yield Curve&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s one detail left to clarify. So far we&amp;#39;ve been talking about bonds as
though they&amp;#39;re a singular security with a single price. In reality, there are
thousands of types of bonds in circulation! The bonds may have different coupon
rates and different maturities: not only are there 5-years bonds and 10-years
bonds, but a 10-years bond emitted 6 months ago does not trade at the same price
as a 10-years bond emitted today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do we abstract all this mess? And how are we able to quote a single 10-years
yield rate, when there are many 10-years maturity bonds (emitted in 2019, 2020,
2021, ...) and many bonds with 10 years left on the clocks (newly minted
10-years bonds, 20-years bonds from 2011, 30-years bonds from 2001, ...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is elegant: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yield_curve&quot;&gt;the yield curve&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This curve gives the yield for a
given maturity. Here &lt;em&gt;maturity&lt;/em&gt; is to be understood not as the maturity at the
time when the bond was emitted, but as the remaining time until the bond matures
and the principal is paid back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds/yieldcurve.png&quot; alt=&quot;yield curve now, one and two years ago&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you have to recognize that any bond with the same time left until
maturation has the same yield — no matter what the original maturity and coupon
rates were! If that wasn&amp;#39;t the case, anyone who owns the lower-yield bond would
sell it to buy the higher-yield bond. This very process pushes the lower-yield
bond price down (and therefor its yield up) and the higher-yield bond price up
(and therefore its yield down) — until the two bonds have the same yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, bonds with different time left until maturation do have different
yield rates. Typically (but not always, see below), higher remaining maturity
bonds have higher yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is due to risk. Imagine inflation rises to 5% per year. Suddenly, earning
2% yearly does not seem so good anymore, as the return in inflation-adjusted
terms is now about -3%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you just bought a 1-year bond for 103$ at 2% yield, and the yield rises to 5%,
it means the bond price must decrease to 100$. A ~3% loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you just bought a 10-years bond for 130$ with 2% yield (given a
fixed yield, a longer term bond is necessarily more expensive, because it pays
coupons for longer), and the yield rises to 5%, the bond price must decrease to
100$ — a ~23% loss!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So longer-term bonds are riskier in case inflation flares up. For this reason,
they tend to command a higher yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, it is occasionally possible for shorter-term bonds to command a
higher yield rate than long-term bond, leading to &lt;em&gt;an inverted yield curve&lt;/em&gt;.
This happens when people expect deflation (money increasing in purchasing power,
a negative inflation rate) or desinflation (a lowering of the (still positive)
inflation rate), in which case purchasing long-term bonds allows you to &amp;quot;lock
in&amp;quot; the current yield rate. Other &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yield_curve#Normal_yield_curve&quot;&gt;unusual scenarios&lt;/a&gt; are possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An inverted yield curve is often treated as a sign announciating a recession,
and did for instance happen in 2006, more than a year before the start of the
great financial crisis. That being said, I feel like an inverted yield curve is
unlikely to recur any time soon. The US government just injected trillions into
its economy, so inflation, not deflation, is on all the lips.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can consult the official yield rates &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/interest-rates/pages/textview.aspx?data=yield&quot;&gt;on the US treasury
website&lt;/a&gt; and you can visualize the curve &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gurufocus.com/yield_curve.php&quot;&gt;on gurufocus&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s it for today! &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/bonds-2&quot;&gt;The next article&lt;/a&gt; looks at what might have
caused the surge in bond yields in February. We&amp;#39;ll also look at some hypothesis
explaining why this affected the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this article, you might enjoy other articles about &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;finance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-04-29T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/bonds</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/bonds</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GameStop: Anatomy of a Short &amp; Gamma Squeeze</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Part of a series of posts on &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;finance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of January the stock price of GameStop (GME), a brick-and-mortar
video game retailer, went completely crazy. This has been chronicled in a lot of
details in the press, but I feel like shedding light on a few points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m motivated to do so because (a) I have discussed/explained the events quite a
bit with some friends and colleagues, and (b) the common narratives around the
events are quite misleading, whether they come from the people who think we
witnessed greatness, those who think we witnessed madness, those who think
internet randos stuck it to Wall Street, or those who think Wall Street yet
again took advantage of the little folks. Me? I believe all of the above. It&amp;#39;s
complicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, the year-to-date chart of the GME stock price (click the picture
for a bigger version):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/gamestop/gme.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/gamestop/gme.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not going to write a summary of the events, you can find that online, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GameStop_short_squeeze&quot;&gt;on
wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.is/02nxI&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (warning for that second link: lots
of unreasonable speculation). If you&amp;#39;re not familiar with the matter, I highly
recommend you give those a read, otherwise the rest of this article won&amp;#39;t make
much sense. You can also try to google around for other takes, to see what the
media coverage was like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tldr&quot;&gt;tl;dr&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;here is a short summary of the key points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Short-selling is borrowing a share to sell it, hoping to repurchase it later at
a smaller price, hence booking a profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A short squeeze occurs when the stock price increases instead, forcing
short-seller to &amp;quot;purchase to cover&amp;quot; at loss, further driving the price up.
Read to understand why they were forced to do so in this case, and how GME
could be shorted at more than 100%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Short-selling make the market more efficient by making prices reflect
material information faster. This is not to say that markets are ultimately
efficient (that much should be obvious), but they would be less efficient
without short-selling. Short-selling also can&amp;#39;t bankrupt a business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;What happened: retail investors hyping the stock, notably on the
WallStreetBets reddit board, driving the price up. This triggered a short
squeeze (which was part of the explicit plan of at least some redditors).
This did in turn trigger a gamma squeeze.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A gamma squeeze is an increase in the stock price driven by market makers
(who sell options) &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/options/#option-greeks&quot;&gt;delta&lt;/a&gt;-hedging their option contracts. This makes them
insensitive to change in the stock price and lets them pocket the option
premium. Having sold call options, the increase in stock price caused them to
purchase more stock to maintain the hedge, further driving the price up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Contrary to the prevalent narrative, there was a lot of fast, non-retail
money at play in GME while the stock was acting crazy in January.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;short-selling-mechanics&quot;&gt;Short-Selling Mechanics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GME&amp;#39;s incredibly run is often attributed to a &amp;quot;short squeeze&amp;quot;. But what is that
even?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short-sellers believe a stock&amp;#39;s price will go down. They act on this believe by
borrowing the stock, selling it, and planning to repurchase it later, at a lower
price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short squeeze occurs when the price of a stock rises sharply, forcing
short-sellers to purchase back the stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If they believe the stock is worthless and will eventually crash back down, do
they have to cover? Long story short: yes, because of margin requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, unlike purchasing stock, short-selling exposes you to potentially unlimited
losses: there is no limit to how high a stock can go, but it can&amp;#39;t go lower than
0. As the share price increase, you become insolvent on paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brokerage firms do not like their clients to be insolvent, even if &amp;quot;it&amp;#39;s only
temporary&amp;quot;. So they impose margin requirements, which dictate how much
collateral you must own to offset the losses incurred by increase in the price
of a stock you sold short.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brokerage can also require that short sellers return the loaned share &amp;quot;with
minimal notice&amp;quot;. It is my understanding that they do not tend to do this
excepted in extraordinary situations, because they profit from lending the
shares, and doing this abusively would lead to short-sellers to take their
business elsewhere. The GME short-squeeze certainly qualifies as an
extraordinary situation, but I haven&amp;#39;t heard any report that brokers recalled
loaned shares. In general, the margin requirements will fulfill the same purpose
in a more transparent manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If short-selling mechanisms are unclear for you, I recommend reading &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Short_(finance)#Mechanism&quot;&gt;the
&lt;em&gt;Mechanism&lt;/em&gt; section of the wikipedia page on shorting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that&amp;#39;s very unusual and salient in the GameStop story is that GameStop
had a short interest greater than 100%. Said otherwise, &lt;strong&gt;there were more shares
being sold short than actually existing shares&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is this possible? It&amp;#39;s quite simple. When you sell a share short, you borrow
it from person A, promising to return it, and sell it to person B. Person B does
not know you&amp;#39;re a short-seller and perceives this as a completely normal
transaction. Person B is entirely free to borrow his share to another
short-seller, who will in turn sell it to person C. This process can
theoretically continue forever. Now, persons A, B and C all own the same share.
Note however that persons A and B, having loaned their shares, do not have the
associated voting rights.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-short-sellers-evil&quot;&gt;Are short-sellers evil?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WallStreetBets crowd — and many other people too, including some that should
have known better, sadly — were quick to formulate all kind of spurious
narratives regarding the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those narratives is that short sellers are evil greedy capitalists out to
destroy companies like GameStop. Well, they are probably greedy capitalists —
who on the stock market isn&amp;#39;t?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a new idea. Would it surprise you that people blamed short-sellers
for the 1929 stock market crash? Politicians passed restrictions on short
selling at various time that systematically failed to have any impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little bit of common sense should be sufficient to understand this. If
short-sellers drive the price down, they are offering a bargain to those who
believed the prevous price to be fair. The stock is now under-valued and there
is a profit to be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short-sellers also cannot literally destroy a business. What they can do is
severely impede the company&amp;#39;s ability to finance itself by emitting new shares
(since the value of those is much lower). However, a stock offering is not the
only means to finance a company, and you get the idea that if the company can&amp;#39;t
even secure a loan, the short-seller might have a point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, short-sellers fulfill a useful function in the market — they help make
price more accurate. (This is not to say that market prices are generally very
accurate, but they would be even less so without short-sellers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, if a stock is mostly owned by slow-moving &amp;quot;instutional&amp;quot; investors (banks,
pension funds, etc), a negative piece of news (lackluster earnings report,
business problems, ...) might take some time to be reflected in the stock price.
For a stock that used to be up, retail (= normal people) investors would also be
reluctant to sell without seeing that the stock is actually dropping.
Short-sellers provide that impetus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the longer term, imagine a &amp;quot;growth&amp;quot; company. Its proponents affirm it will be
the next Amazon/Apple/Tesla. Other people believe it be a scam. Without
short-selling, the second group has no bearing on the stock price, which will
only reflect the bull view. But with short-selling, this group now has a
financial incentive to express its opinion in the market. This is particularly
important because while the stock price should ideally be the endpoint of
reflection about a company&amp;#39;s value, the price (and its history) is in practice
also a big data point in the investment decision. Would you rather purchase a
company whose valuation has consistently been high compared to fundamentals, or
one whose valuation has consistently been low? The former is typically (and with
reason) interpreted has a sign of optimism regarding the company&amp;#39;s prospects,
and vice-versa for the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, short-selling is quite risky — since the market is skewed to
the upside (thankfully!), and has been particularly so in recent years, given
historically high company valuations, and rampant speculation in growth stocks
(I&amp;#39;m not judging, I did my part).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;short-squeeze-gamma-squeeze&quot;&gt;Short Squeeze? Gamma Squeeze?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GME&amp;#39;s incredibly run is often attributed to a &amp;quot;short squeeze&amp;quot; (the wikipedia
article is even titled &lt;em&gt;GameStop short squeeze&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that picture is incomplete. Retail interest, causing the price to go up, and
the subsequent short squeeze were certainly the initial drivers of the stock&amp;#39;s
stratospheric rise. But it&amp;#39;s not the only thing that sustained its growth to
almost 500$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was at least one other major component to the price action, and that was a
&lt;em&gt;gamma squeeze&lt;/em&gt; (also known as &lt;em&gt;gamma trap&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gamma is a second-order stock option greek. If you don&amp;#39;t know anything about
stock options, I wrote &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/options&quot;&gt;a primer here&lt;/a&gt;. The primer covers first-order
options greeks, including &lt;em&gt;delta&lt;/em&gt;, but not the second-order &lt;em&gt;gamma&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/options/#option-greeks&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Delta&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in brief: if the delta is 0.5, that means if the stock price
increases by 1$, the call option price will increase by 0.5$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So delta is the derivate (in the mathematical sense) of the price of the option
with respect to the price of the underlying stock — just like speed is the
derivative of the distance with respect to the elapsed time: at 10km/h the
travelled distance increases by 10km for every hour travelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gamma&lt;/em&gt; then, is the second derivative of option price with respect to the stock
price. Gamma tell you how much &lt;em&gt;delta&lt;/em&gt; varies when the underlying stock price
increases by 1$ — just like acceleration is the second derivate of the distance
with respect to elapsed time: a 10 km/s^2 acceleration means that your speed
increases by 10 km/s every second!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;#39;s a gamma squeeze, then?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most options are sold by market makers, which are large institutions such as
investment banks, and they hedge the options they sell by purchasing (or
selling) stock in order to be &amp;quot;delta neutral&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for instance, if they sell a call option at the money (&amp;quot;ATM&amp;quot;, strike price =
current price), the delta is 0.5, and they will also purchase 50 shares of the
underlying to hedge the option. Now if the price increases by 1$, they are up
50$ on the stock, down 50$ on the call, and they can profit by pocketing the
premium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because delta changes as the price changes, the market maker needs to manage its
stock position to keep its hedge. As an option gets in the money (strike price &amp;lt;
current stock price), its delta increases, meaning the market maker must
increase the number of stock it purchases to continue being delta-neutral on the
call option it sold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the GME case, what what happened is that redditors purchased a lot of cheap
out of the money call options (these have a low delta), and as the stock price
rose and rose, these ended up far in the money, meaning the market makers had to
ultimately purchase many shares for each of these calls, driving the stock price
higher, and pushing all calls farther in the money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, why did they purchase out of the money calls? Because they were
cheap, and a rising share price would increase their price too. Slowly at first
(delta is low), but increasingly so as the price increases. If you believe the
price will increase a lot (which people on WallStreetBets obviously did), this
is the best kind of option to be holding (if you believe the price will increase
only moderately, you should hold ATM options instead).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s circle back — why is this called a &lt;em&gt;gamma&lt;/em&gt; squeeze? Because it&amp;#39;s caused by
the delta increase in the ATM options, which causes market makers to increase
their purchases to preserve their delta hedge. The rate at which delta increases
as the price rises is given by gamma, the derivative of gamma with regard to
price. (Note that gamma is not itself a constant but a function!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://norswap.com/gamestop/gamma.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How much of the squeeze vas due to shorts being squeezed vs gamma?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s hard to say, and I don&amp;#39;t know. Obviously the whole thing was started as a
short squeeze, and then gamma amplified the movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also a ton of capital that piled on once the GME price anomaly caught
everyone&amp;#39;s attention. More on this in a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why is it so hard to say? Let&amp;#39;s take the short part of the equation. Large
enough funds have to report positions (including shorts) to the SEC, but such
fillings are only made quarterly. The short ratio for a stock (the percentage of
outstanding shares that have been sold short) is published by the exchange at
the end of each month. The end result is that on any given day, we don&amp;#39;t really
know the short situation in a volatile environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if we had daily numbers, we still would be ignorant of the short turnover.
For instance, a constant short ratio might mean that new short sales were made
as prevous short positions were covered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the gamma side of things, we have more information, but only slightly. For
each contract, we know the &amp;quot;open interest&amp;quot;, which is the number of open
contracts at the end of the previous day. We also know the number of
transactions involving the contract made so far during the current day. So we
could in theory scrape that data, assume that the counterparty for every call
purchased was a market maker (an approximation which I believe to be close
enough to the truth) and come up with a guesstimate of how much buying resulted
from hedging the positions. There is a lot of imprecision and unknowns there,
and buy volume does not give you, by itself, price impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-retail-frenzy&quot;&gt;A Retail Frenzy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widely reported narrative was that GME was mostly traded by retail traders
(normal people, not institutions). This was certainly true at first. Retail
involvement caused the stock to rise, which in turns caused the short and gamma
squeezes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, once the event made headlines, a lot of people poured in — both retail
and institutional. But institutions (hedge funds, quant shops, etc) have a lot
more money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that retail traders didn&amp;#39;t drive all the momentum is easy to see when
you realize that after many brokers, including Robinhood, temporary banned or
severely limited trading on the stock, there was still high volumes of trading
occuring. Interestingly, it seems like retail traders, on aggregate, sold as
much as they bought on the week of 25 Jan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;#39;t say more about this, because Matt Levine did so better than I could &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2021-01-29/reddit-traders-on-robinhood-are-on-both-sides-of-gamestop&quot;&gt;in
his Money Stuff column&lt;/a&gt;, including supporting evidence for the points I
make above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;thats-it-folks&quot;&gt;That&amp;#39;s it folks!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, &lt;strike&gt;gamble&lt;/strike&gt; invest responsibly, and don&amp;#39;t believe
everything you&amp;#39;re told. Do your own research!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Read more things I&amp;#39;ve written on &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/finance&quot;&gt;finance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-04-13T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/gamestop</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/gamestop</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Favourite Quotes from &quot;Your Music and Your People&quot;</title>
      <description>
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sive.rs/m&quot;&gt;Official Book Homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/reviews&quot;&gt;More Reviews Written by Me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/hell-yeah&quot;&gt;My Favourite Quotes from &amp;quot;Hell Yeah, or No&amp;quot; (same author)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got so much enjoyment out of &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/hell-yeah&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Hell Yeah Or No&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; that I decided to
read Derek Sivers&amp;#39; other book &amp;quot;Your Music and Your People&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first glance, the book isn&amp;#39;t really for me: it&amp;#39;s a treatise on how to market
yourself in the music business. However it&amp;#39;s written in this terse and
delightfully-to-the-point Sivers style. And really, most of the lessons
generalize to any kind of marketing, which we all need from time to time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boxing this into &amp;quot;marketing&amp;quot; also doesn&amp;#39;t seem to cut it. Some of the lessons
are much more broadly applicable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;#39;s because I haven&amp;#39;t really thought much about marketing before, but I
excerpted a lot of this one. Just like last time, titles are chapter titles, and
what follows are quotes (mostly) and paraphrases from that chapter. Sometimes
the chapter title is enough!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;business-is-creative&quot;&gt;Business is creative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But turning off your creativity—trying to play it safe—is the worst thing you
could do. Just like with music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;this-is-only-a-test-see-what-happens&quot;&gt;This is only a test. See what happens&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s actually impossible to fail if your only mission was to see what happens!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;restrictions-will-set-you-free&quot;&gt;Restrictions will set you free&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-mystery--make-people-wonder&quot;&gt;Make mystery : make people wonder&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t be so plain or obvious that there’s nothing left to wonder. But don’t be
so cryptic that they give up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once people start wondering, they can’t stand not knowing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;marketing-just-means-being-considerate&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Marketing&amp;quot; just means being considerate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing means listening for what people need, and creating something
surprisingly tailored for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marketing means getting to know people, making a deeper connection, and keeping
in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;constantly-ask-what-they-really-want&quot;&gt;Constantly ask what they really want&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;touch-as-many-of-their-senses-as-you-can&quot;&gt;Touch as many of their senses as you can&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more senses you touch in someone, the more they’ll remember you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;life-is-like-high-school&quot;&gt;Life is like high school&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can approach this strategically, as if you were a new kid going to a new
school, with a goal to be popular. It sounds shallow, but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be who they want to be. In your role as a musician, it’s actually considerate!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But people want someone to look up to. Someone who’s not of their normal boring
world. Someone who’s being who they wish they could be, if they had the courage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-personal&quot;&gt;Get personal&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People send business to people they like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if it starts professional, get personal as soon as possible. Be a friend.
That’s how things are done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;always-think-how-you-can-help-someone&quot;&gt;Always think how you can help someone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask them what’s the hardest part about their job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-be-afraid-to-ask-for-favors&quot;&gt;Don’t be afraid to ask for favors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People like doing favors!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By making them feel important, connected, and needed, you’ll be doing them a
favor, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;small-gifts-go-a-long-way&quot;&gt;Small gifts go a long way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get presents for the people you’ve met that are probably under-appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;persistence-is-polite&quot;&gt;Persistence is polite&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in the business world, it’s the opposite. If you don’t keep trying, you’re a
loser!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone doesn’t get back to you, it probably wasn’t intentional. Everyone is
busy, and their situation has nothing to do with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;repeatedly-follow-up-to-show-you-care&quot;&gt;Repeatedly follow-up to show you care&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pedestals-prevent-friendships&quot;&gt;Pedestals prevent friendships&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-get-through-the-gates&quot;&gt;How to get through the gates?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get someone with access to the inside to promote you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;have-someone-work-the-inside-of-the-industry&quot;&gt;Have someone work the inside of the industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;get-specific&quot;&gt;Get specific!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;call-the-destination-and-ask-for-directions&quot;&gt;Call the destination, and ask for directions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know where we want to be, but we don’t know how to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Work backwards. Just contact someone who’s there, and ask how to get there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;flip-it-in-your-favor&quot;&gt;Flip it in your favor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The old saying, &amp;quot;It’s all who you know,&amp;quot; used to feel so defeating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[after he bought pizza for a hungry music exec visiting school] For the next two
years, he took my calls and gave me all kinds of advice about the music
business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything that seems depressing can beﬂipped to work in my favor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every deal that’s bad for someone is good for someone else. So instead of
moaning about the bad side, you can take the good side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-curious-answer-to-the-most-common-question&quot;&gt;A curious answer to the most common question&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&amp;quot;What kind of music do you do?&amp;quot; - but works for other questions too]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With one interesting phrase to describe your music, you can make total strangers
wonder about you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-people-curious-in-one-sentence&quot;&gt;Make people curious in one sentence.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;without-a-good-reason-they-wont-bother&quot;&gt;Without a good reason, they won’t bother&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(checking your music, business, ...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they ask what kind of music you do, they’re actively hoping you’ll give
them a reason to care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t give them a reason in that very moment, the opportunity is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-know-how-to-describe-your-music&quot;&gt;Don’t know how to describe your music?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask people how they would describe. Look at the description / reviews of other
music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’ve got one you like, try it out on people. See if their face lights up.
See if they get curious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-the-tricks-that-worked-on-you&quot;&gt;Use the tricks that worked on you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself why a certain headline or photo or article caught your attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;proudly-exclude-most-people&quot;&gt;Proudly exclude most people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Loudly reject 99%. It signals who you are. When someone in your target 1% hears
you proudly excluding the rest, they’ll be drawn to you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;well-rounded-doesnt-cut&quot;&gt;Well-rounded doesn’t cut&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only problem is, if you’re well-rounded, you can’t cut through anything. You
need to be sharply deﬁned, like a knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the long careers of David Bowie, Miles Davis, Madonna, Prince, Joni
Mitchell, or Paul Simon. Each went through sharply-deﬁned phases, treating each
album as a project with a narrow focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do this every year or two, and you will have a wide variety in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;doing-the-opposite-of-everyone-is-valuable&quot;&gt;Doing the opposite of everyone is valuable&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s supply and demand. The more people do something, the less valuable it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone else is multi-tasking. So it’s more valuable to single-task.
Everyone else is hyper-connected. So it’s more valuable to disconnect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t try to beat them at their game. Play a completely different game. Be
radically opposite. Don’t be associated with them in any way. Be so different
that people don’t even think to compare you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;selling-music-by-solving-a-speciﬁc-need&quot;&gt;Selling music by solving a speciﬁc need&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;people-search-harder-for-the-obscure&quot;&gt;People search harder for the obscure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fans of the obscure niches search harder for it. Make sure they canﬁnd you. You
want the passionate fans of your niche, not the casual fans of mainstream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-you-need-a-database&quot;&gt;Why you need a database&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(for tracking people)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;stay-in-touch-with-hundreds-of-people&quot;&gt;Stay in touch with hundreds of people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[This chapter include a short description of a system for keeping in touch with people.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are so bad at keeping in touch that they will really appreciate you
doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;meet-three-new-people-every-week&quot;&gt;Meet three new people every week&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we assume your music is great, and you are a likeable person that people
enjoy helping, I’ll make this prediction: The number of people you meet will
determine your success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-in-touch&quot;&gt;Keep in touch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between success and failure can be as simple as keeping in touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;every-breakthrough-comes-from-someone-you-know&quot;&gt;Every breakthrough comes from someone you know&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take some of that searching time, and spend it on keeping in touch with your
existing contacts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;put-your-fans-to-work&quot;&gt;Put your fans to work&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;include-everyone-in-your-success&quot;&gt;Include everyone in your success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(that helped you get there or treated you well)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-to-attend-a-conference&quot;&gt;How to attend a conference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trade contact info within a few minutes of meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Send them a message immediately, connecting the digital you to the physical you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the conference, come up with one interesting sentence that says what you
do—including a curious bit that will make them ask a follow-up question. For
example: “Bassist of the Crunchy Frogs—the worst punk bluegrass band ever. We’re
headlining the showcase tonight. Our singer is a pirate.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Real business is done in the follow-up, not the conference itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best time to get down to business is when they’re alone, back at their
ofﬁce, a week or two after the conference, and can give you their full
one-on-one attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-be-a-mosquito&quot;&gt;Don’t be a mosquito&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn what they love. Learn what they want. Figure out what you can do for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;valuable-to-others-or-only-you&quot;&gt;Valuable to others, or only you?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But money only comes from doing something valuable to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on making your music more valuable to others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop expecting it to be valuable to others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;emphasize-meaning-over-price&quot;&gt;Emphasize meaning over price&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It changes the request from a commercial pitch to an emotional connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-people-like-to-pay-let-them&quot;&gt;Some people like to pay. Let them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you’re offering something for free, don’t forget that there are lots of
people that like to pay! Appeal to this side of people, giving them a reason to
pay that feels good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-higher-the-price-the-more-they-value-it&quot;&gt;The higher the price, the more they value it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it’s considerate to charge more for your work. People will appreciate it
more, and get better results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-fans-telling-friends-if-not-dont-promote&quot;&gt;Are fans telling friends? If not, don’t promote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-promote-until-people-can-take-action&quot;&gt;Don’t promote until people can take action&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;move-to-the-big-city&quot;&gt;Move to the big city&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Living in the big city, and being where everything is happening, will help your
career the most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;detailed-dreams-blind-you-to-new-means&quot;&gt;Detailed dreams blind you to new means&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;are-you-at-the-starting-line-or-the-ﬁnish-line&quot;&gt;Are you at the starting line or the ﬁnish line?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some artists, releasing their music is like the starting line in a race. The
gun goes off! They work it! They spend hours a day pushing, promoting, and
selling—reaching new people by any means necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;ignore-advice-that-drains-you&quot;&gt;Ignore advice that drains you&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;compass-in-your-gut&quot;&gt;Compass in your gut&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever excites you, go do it.
Whatever drains you, stop doing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But nothing is worth losing your enthusiasm. Nothing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s almost nothing that you must do.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-04-12T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/your-music</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/your-music</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
