<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>norswap</title>
    <description></description>      
    <link>http://norswap.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://norswap.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Cruising Blues</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;Completing my series of posts about Robert Pirsig&amp;#39;s
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_and_the_Art_of_Motorcycle_Maintenance&quot;&gt;Zen and the Art of motorcycle Maintenance&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;/stuckness-and-understanding&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/peace-of-mind&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/gumption-arete&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;), here&amp;#39;s a
        fantastic expert from an article of Pirsig, titled
        &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moq.org/forum/Pirsig/cruisingblues.html&quot;&gt;Cruising Blues and Their Cure&lt;/a&gt; and published in Esquire in 1977.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Virtue here comes from childhood reading about the old days of sailing ships
        when young men were sent to sea to learn manliness and virtue. I remember being
        skeptical about this. &amp;quot;How could a monotonous passage across a pile of water
        produce virtue?&amp;quot; I wondered. I figured that maybe a few bad storms would scare
        hell out of the young men and this would make them humble and manly and virtuous
        and appreciative of life ever afterward, but it seemed like a dubious
        curriculum. There were cheaper and quicker ways to scare people than that.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Now, however, with a boat of my own and some time at sea, I begin to see the
        learning of virtue another way. It has something to do with the way the sea and
        sun and wind and sky go on and on day after day, week after week, and the boat
        and you have to go on with it. You must take the helm and change the sails and
        take sights of the stars and work out their reductions and sleep and cook and
        eat and repair things as they break and do most of these things in stormy
        weather as well as fair, depressed as well as elated, because there&amp;#39;s no choice.
        You get used to it; it becomes habit-forming and produces a certain change in
        values. Old gear that has been through a storm or two without failure becomes
        more precious than it was when you bought it because you know you can trust it.
        The same becomes true of fellow crewmen and ultimately becomes true of things
        about yourself. Good first appearances count for less than they ever did, and
        real virtue - which comes from an ability to separate what merely looks good
        from what lasts and the acquisition of those characteristics in one&amp;#39;s self - is
        strengthened.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Self-discovery is as much a philosopher&amp;#39;s imponderable as reality, but when one
        takes away the external stimuli of civilization during long ocean hours at the
        helm far from any land, and particularly on overcast nights, every cruising
        sailor knows that what occurs is not an evening of complete blankness. Instead
        comes a flow of thought drawn forth by the emptiness of the night. Occurrences
        of the previous day, meager as they may have been, rise and are thought about
        for a while, and then die away to return again later, a little less compelling,
        and perhaps another time even weaker, until they die away completely and are not
        thought of again. Then older memories appear, of a week past, a month past, of
        years past, and these are thought about and sometimes interrelated with new
        insights. A problem that has been baffling in the past is now understood
        quickly. New ideas for things seem to pop up from nowhere because the rigid
        patterns of thought that inhibited them are now weakened by emptiness and
        depression. Then in time these new thoughts wear town too, and the empty night
        dredges deeper into the subconscious to tug at, loosen and dislodge old
        forgotten thoughts that were repressed years ago. Old injustices that one has
        had to absorb, old faces now gone, ancient feelings of personal doubt, remorse,
        hatred and fear, are suddenly loose and at you. You must face them again and
        again until they die away like the thoughts preceding them. This self that one
        discovers is in many ways a person one would not like one&amp;#39;s friends to know
        about; a person one may have been avoiding for years, full of vanity, cowardice,
        boredom, self-pity, laziness, blamingness, weak when he should be strong,
        aggressive when he should be gentle, a person who will do anything not to know
        these things about himself - the very same fellow who has been having problems
        with cruising depression all this time. I think it&amp;#39;s in the day-after-day,
        week-after-week confrontation of this person that the most valuable learning of
        virtue takes place.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-09-19T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/cruising-blues</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/cruising-blues</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gumption and Areté</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;This post is part 3/3 in a series about Robert Pirsig&amp;#39;s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_and_the_Art_of_Motorcycle_Maintenance&quot;&gt;Zen and the Art of
        motorcycle Maintenance&lt;/a&gt;. See also &lt;a href=&quot;/stuckness-and-understanding&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/peace-of-mind&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This post will talk about two notions that Pirsig puts forward: &lt;em&gt;gumption&lt;/em&gt; and
        &lt;em&gt;areté&lt;/em&gt;. Gumption is originally a Scottish term, meaning &amp;quot;common sense,
        shrewdness&amp;quot;, but also &amp;quot;drive, initiative&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A person filled with gumption doesn&amp;#39;t sit around dissipating and stewing about
        things. He&amp;#39;s at the front of the train of his own awareness, watching to see
        what&amp;#39;s up the track and meeting it when it comes.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Gumption-filling occurs when one is quiet long enough to see, hear and feel the
        real universe, not just one&amp;#39;s own stale opinions about it.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s common in people returning from long fishing trips. They seemingly have put
        a lot of time for nothing, but in reality they come back with an abundance of
        gumption, usually for the very same things they were sick to death of a few
        weeks before. It&amp;#39;s not wasted time.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Gumption is the psychic gasoline that keeps the whole thing going.&amp;quot; It is
        necessary to all psychic tasks of interest. If you don&amp;#39;t have it, you might as
        well not start. Similarly, its level must be monitored at all times.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;When gumption loss occur: take a long break, don&amp;#39;t rush in to make up for lost
        gumption.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;One of the gumption &lt;em&gt;traps&lt;/em&gt; is ego:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;To the untrained eye ego-climbing and selfless climbing may appear identical.
        Both kinds of climbers place one foot in front of the other. Both breathe in
        and out at the same rate. Both stop when tired. Both go forward when rested.
        But what a difference! The ego-climber is like an instrument that’s out of
        adjustment. He puts his foot down an instant too soon or too late. He’s likely
        to miss a beautiful passage of sunlight through the trees. He goes on when the
        sloppiness of his step shows he’s tired. He rests at odd times. He looks up
        the trail trying to see what’s ahead even when he knows what’s ahead because
        he just looked a second before. He goes too fast or too slow for the
        conditions and when he talks his talk is forever about somewhere else,
        something else. He’s here but he’s not here. He rejects the here, he’s unhappy
        with it, wants to be farther up the trail but when he gets there will be just
        as unhappy because then it will be “here”. What he’s looking for, what he
        wants, is all around him, but he doesn’t want that because it is all around
        him. Every step’s an effort, both physically and spiritually, because he
        imagines his goal to be external and distant.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;(Thanks to my friend Stanislav for bringing this quote to my attention.)&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Areté&lt;/em&gt; is a greek notion that refers to excellence, acquired not as a duty to
        others but to oneself.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Areté implies excelling in many domains in life, a respect for the wholeness of
        one&amp;#39;s life. It implies contempt for efficiency, or rather a higher idea for
        efficiency, an efficiency which exists not in one department of life but in life
        itself.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-09-19T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/gumption-arete</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/gumption-arete</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Publication</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Context-Sensitive Languages with Principled Stateful Parsing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;To appear at &lt;a href=&quot;http://conf.researchr.org/track/sle-2016/sle-2016-papers&quot;&gt;SLE 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://norswap.com/pubs/sle2016.pdf&quot;&gt;Pre-print here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-09-16T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/pub-context-sensitive</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/pub-context-sensitive</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stuckness and Understanding</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;The second big idea (1) I got out of reading
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_and_the_Art_of_Motorcycle_Maintenance&quot;&gt;Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance&lt;/a&gt; is how getting stuck is a
        common part of most work processes, and how to deal with it. The tidbits below
        are from my own notes, with some phrases lifted or paraphrased from Pirsig.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;(1) &lt;a href=&quot;/peace-of-mind&quot;&gt;First one here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Getting stuck is common. Getting stuck is trying to do too many things at once.
        To get unstuck, separate the things and do them one at a time. Separate thinking
        about what to say and saying things. Make a list of things to say in any order.
        If there are too many, pick the best things.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Hypotheses generation is the realm of quality. The difference between a good and
        a bad mathematician or mechanic is the ability to select the good facts from the
        bad ones on the basis of quality. The scientific method operates only after you
        have an hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Stuckness isn&amp;#39;t the worst of all possible situations: zen buddhists go to much
        throuble to induce it (through koans, meditation, etc). It&amp;#39;s called &amp;quot;begginer&amp;#39;s
        mind&amp;quot;. This moment is not to be feared but cultivated. If your mind is truly
        stuck, you might be much better off than when it was loaded with ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you try to hold onto the stuckness, it is bound to disappear. Your mind will
        naturally and freely move toward a solution. The longer you stay stuck, the more
        you see quality and it gets you unstuck every time. What&amp;#39;s getting you stuck is
        frantically trying to get unstuck by rummaging through your knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Stuckness is the psychic predecessor of all understanding. An egoless acceptance
        of it is key to understanding quality. Self-taught mechanics are often superior
        to instructed ones because they can handle new situations.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Harry Truman on adminstration programs:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll just try them - and if they don&amp;#39;t work &amp;mdash; why then we&amp;#39;ll just try
        something else.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The skill of the inventor is to choose the convenient facts. There is an
        inconscient selection (subliminal self) where many possible but useless
        facts/conventions are rejected.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Look at things that ties up with the theory... then looks at things that are
        very different, to gain insight. Maybe they are the same, maybe not. Select
        facts with harmony and mathematical beauty in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-08-12T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/stuckness-and-understanding</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/stuckness-and-understanding</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Good Work is Peace of Mind</title>
      <description>
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve a set of instructions at home which open up great realms for the
        improvement of technical writing. They begin, &amp;#39;Assembly of Japanese bicycle
        require great peace of mind.&amp;#39;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Over the past few months, I have been reading
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zen_and_the_Art_of_Motorcycle_Maintenance&quot;&gt;Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance&lt;/a&gt; by Robert Pirsig. This post
        collects a few quotes on one of the big idea I got out of the book, namely that
        doing good work is synonymous with tending to your peace of mind.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Peace of mind isn&amp;#39;t at all superficial [...] It&amp;#39;s the whole thing. That which
        produces it is good maintenance; that which disturbs it is poor maintenance.
        [...] The ultimate test&amp;#39;s always your own serenity. If you don&amp;#39;t have this
        when you start and maintain it while you&amp;#39;re working you&amp;#39;re likely to build
        your personal problems right into the machine itself.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The test of the machine is the satisfaction it gives you. [...] If the machine
        produces tranquility it&amp;#39;s right. If it disturbs you it&amp;#39;s wrong until either
        the machine or your mind is changed. The test of the machine&amp;#39;s always your own
        mind. There isn&amp;#39;t any other test.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Sometime look at a novice workman or a bad workman and compare his expression
        with that of a craftsman whose work you know is excellent and you&amp;#39;ll see the
        difference. The craftsman isn&amp;#39;t ever following a single line of instruction.
        He&amp;#39;s making decisions as he goes along. For that reason he&amp;#39;ll be absorbed and
        attentive to what he&amp;#39;s doing even though he doesn&amp;#39;t deliberately contrive this.
        His motions and the machine are in a kind of harmony. He isn&amp;#39;t following any set
        of written instructions because the nature of the material at hand determines
        his thoughts and motions, which simultaneously change the nature of the material
        at hand. The material and his thoughts are changing together in a progression of
        changes until his mind&amp;#39;s at rest at the same time the material&amp;#39;s right.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I say inner peace of mind. It has no direct relationship to external
        circumstances. It can occur to a monk in meditation, to a soldier in heavy
        combat or to a machinist taking off that last ten-thousandth of an inch. It
        involves unselfconsciousness, which produces a complete identification with
        one&amp;#39;s circumstances, and there are levels and levels of this identification
        and levels and levels of quietness quite as profound and difficult of
        attainment as the more familiar levels of activity.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;This inner peace of mind occurs on three levels of understanding. Physical
        quietness seems the easiest to achieve, although there are levels and levels of
        this too, as attested by the ability of Hindu mystics to live buried alive for
        many days. Mental quietness, in which one has no wandering thoughts at all,
        seems more difficult, but can be achieved. But value quietness, in which one has
        no wandering desires at all but simply performs the acts of his life without
        desire, that seems the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve sometimes thought this inner peace of mind, this quietness is similar to if
        not identical with the sort of calm you sometimes get when going fishing, which
        accounts for much of the popularity of this sport. Just to sit with the line in
        the water, not moving, not really thinking about anything, not really caring
        about anything either, seems to draw out the inner tensions and frustrations
        that have prevented you from solving problems you couldn&amp;#39;t solve before and
        introduced ugliness and clumsiness into your actions and thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;You don&amp;#39;t have to go fishing, of course, to fix your motorcycle. A cup of
        coffee, a walk around the block, sometimes just putting off the job for five
        minutes of silence is enough. When you do you can almost feel yourself grow
        toward that inner peace of mind that reveals it all. That which turns its back
        on this inner calm and the Quality it reveals is bad maintenance. That which
        turns toward it is good. The forms of turning away and toward are infinite but
        the goal is always the same.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Zen Buddhists talk about &amp;quot;just sitting,&amp;quot; a meditative practice in which the idea
        of a duality of self and object does not dominate one&amp;#39;s consciousness. What I&amp;#39;m
        talking about here in motorcyele maintenance is ``just fixing,&amp;#39;&amp;#39; in which the
        idea of a duality of self and object doesn&amp;#39;t dominate one&amp;#39;s consciousness. When
        one isn&amp;#39;t dominated by feelings of separateness from what he&amp;#39;s working on, then
        one can be said to &amp;quot;care&amp;quot; about what he&amp;#39;s doing. That is what caring really is,
        a feeling of identification with what one&amp;#39;s doing.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;So the thing to do when working on a motorcycle, as in any other task, is to
        cultivate the peace of mind which does not separate one&amp;#39;s self from one&amp;#39;s
        surroundings. When that is done successfully then everything else follows
        naturally. Peace of mind produces right values, right values produce right
        thoughts. Right thoughts produce right actions and right actions produce work
        which will be a material reflection for others to see of the serenity at the
        center of it all.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The social values are right only if the individual values are right. The place
        to improve the world is first in one&amp;#39;s own heart and head and hands, and then
        work outward from there. other people can talk about how to expand the destiny
        of mankind. I just want to talk about how to fix a motorcycle.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;hr&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The real cycle you&amp;#39;re working on is yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-07-22T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/peace-of-mind</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/peace-of-mind</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building a static website with Ribosome and Node.js</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve transitioned the website from &lt;a href=&quot;https://jekyllrb.com/&quot;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; to a custom system based on
        &lt;a href=&quot;http://ribosome.ch/&quot;&gt;Ribosome&lt;/a&gt;. I wasn&amp;#39;t updating the website very regularly, and each
        time I picked it up again, I had to spend an hour or so battling the
        particularly horrible Ruby dependencies on Windows.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Ribosome is essentially a templating engine driven by a script language
        (JavaScript, Python or Ruby &amp;mdash; I went with Javascript). It takes a js/py/rb
        script as input, which also contains lines starting with a dot. The script is
        run, but whenever a dotted line is encountered, it is sent to an output file. It
        supports embedded expression within dotted lines, special directives to change
        the file to which the output is redirected and include other files. This makes
        it possible to generate your whole website from a single script
        (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/norswap.github.io/blob/master/.factory/generate.js&quot;&gt;have a look at mine&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Something I really like about Ribosome is how it respects whitespace, resulting
        in really nice-looking output, unlike most templating engines (have a look at
        the html for this page). It&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;http://ribosome.ch/documentation.html#advanced-layout-management&quot;&gt;block layouting&lt;/a&gt; capability is also quite
        handy.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m also very pleased about the Node.js ecosystem. I was really easy to find
        libraries to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/gray-matter&quot;&gt;parse YAML front matter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/marked&quot;&gt;parse Markdown&lt;/a&gt;,
        &lt;a href=&quot;http://momentjs.com/&quot;&gt;manipulate dates&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/escape-html&quot;&gt;escaping html&lt;/a&gt; and
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/package/tmp&quot;&gt;create temporary files&lt;/a&gt;. They were easy to use too.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;All in all, updating the website was a surprisingly pleasant experience.
        Ribosome in particular is great, I encourage you to try it.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-07-12T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/ribosome-static-site</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/ribosome-static-site</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building Java with Make</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/violin&quot;&gt;violin&lt;/a&gt;, I set up the build using the good old &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; tool (you might have
        gathered that &lt;a href=&quot;/rant-java-build&quot;&gt;I harbor no love&lt;/a&gt; for Java build systems).&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;For examples of how to perform common Java build tasks by calling command line
        tools from make, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/violin/blob/master/makefile&quot;&gt;have a look at the makefile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-07-08T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/build-java-with-make</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/build-java-with-make</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Micro-Rant: Java Build Systems</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;Ant is Make in XML.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Maven is an over-engineered, yet castrated build system. You can&amp;#39;t do
        fundamental stuff (such as specifying which version of Java you want to use or
        &lt;strong&gt;moving files&lt;/strong&gt;) without importing a plugin or calling Ant. Want to do something
        slightly different? Build you own plugin (this process is more painful than it
        sounds). On the plus side, Maven does have a handy (but not best-in-class)
        dependency system, which is why we still have to suffer it.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Gradle allows custom build tasks (&lt;strong&gt;finally!&lt;/strong&gt;). It&amp;#39;s also huge, bloated, and
        comes with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.gradle.org/current/userguide/userguide.html&quot;&gt;70-chapters manual&lt;/a&gt; that still manages to be lacunary and
        confusing. Understanding Gradle is not the work of an afternoon but of weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Scala is not served better. To think sbt once stood for &amp;quot;simple build
        tool&amp;quot; (now retconned to &amp;quot;scala build tool&amp;quot;) is enough to choke on the irony.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/build-java-with-make&quot;&gt;One might as well build Java using Make.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;h2 id=&quot;hope-&quot;&gt;Hope?&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://beust.com/kobalt/&quot;&gt;Kobalt&lt;/a&gt; is a sane build system for Kotlin &amp;amp; Java by Cedric Beust (the
        author of TestNG). However it&amp;#39;s still in its infancy.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pluto-build.github.io/&quot;&gt;pluto&lt;/a&gt; is a prototype from academia (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.informatik.uni-marburg.de/~seba/publications/pluto-incremental-build.pdf&quot;&gt;related paper&lt;/a&gt;)
        that enables incremental, minimal, and safe builds (no need to &lt;code&gt;make clean&lt;/code&gt;).
        You can&amp;#39;t really use it as is, but the idea only asks to be picked up.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-07-08T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/rant-java-build</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/rant-java-build</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Released: Violin, a human-sized Kotlin utility library</title>
      <description>
        &lt;p&gt;I just released &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/violin&quot;&gt;violin&lt;/a&gt;, a small Kotlin utility library that features
        simple streams and some other stuff too.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-07-08T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/violin-release</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/violin-release</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Path to Wisdom</title>
      <description>
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The path to wisdom is like this: each time you get one step closer, the target
        moves two steps away.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2016-07-07T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/path-to-wisdom</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/path-to-wisdom</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
