<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>norswap</title>
    <description></description>      
    <link>http://norswap.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://norswap.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reviews 10</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Part of the &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews&quot;&gt;Reviews Series&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;overgeared&quot;&gt;Overgeared&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to chapter 57&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;overgeared.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bunch of new webtoons this time around, still in the same &amp;quot;leveling&amp;quot; genre. It&amp;#39;s
crazy that there does not seem to be a name for those, even though they&amp;#39;re all
build around the same mold. It&amp;#39;s crazy to me how they seemingly &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; seem to
feature these floaty alert panels with skills, quests, etc - even when the story
doesn&amp;#39;t not really demand it. Sometimes the protagonist is the only one to see
them. I&amp;#39;m really curious where this all started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, I&amp;#39;ll try to be brief as most of these are not really adding saying of
substance. It&amp;#39;s mostly mindless entertainement still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overgeared, then. Basically, this time the protagonist is a craftsman, who
manages to become very powerful (mostly) through his items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The protagonist also distinguished itself by not being the most savvy, and often
greedy in a base way. This is generally the setup for some light comedy.
Personally, I didn&amp;#39;t think it works all that well, but it&amp;#39;s not too bothersome
either. A fairly standard entry in the genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;omniscient-readers-viewpoint&quot;&gt;Omniscient Reader&amp;#39;s Viewpoint&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to chapter 36&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise of this one is quite interesting: the protagonist has been the only
redear of a light novel for years, depicting a sort of apocalypse where
otherwordly entities descend on earth and make humans compete for them
(featuring of course, skills &amp;amp; leveling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our man finishes the light novel, the scenario it describes comes to passes.
He now has a very important advantage: he already knows what will happen. This
includes the rules of this brave new world, but also specific events that will
happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, the light novel did have a hero, which is also present in the
story. One cool consequence is that the protagonist must ensure the hero
survives, as the light novel followed the hero, and future events are tied to
him. It&amp;#39;s by no mean the only cool idea in a series that I found a bit smarter
than average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There aren&amp;#39;t that many chapters out currently, but I&amp;#39;m curious to see where this
will go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-am-the-sorcerer-king&quot;&gt;I Am The Sorcerer King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to chapter 123&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, everybody levels to fight appearing monsters, blah blah blah. This time the
protagonist is a reincarnated sorcerer, from a dimension where people can grow
in power but do not level in the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is as pure as a power trip as I&amp;#39;ve ever seeen, featuring a mixing of the
genres, between RPG skills, non-RPG magic, and even science. Suffice to say that
at some point, magical nuclear weapons are being fired.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-motivation-hacker&quot;&gt;The Motivation Hacker&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Nick Winter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read this book because it was quoted extensively from &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-9/#gateless&quot;&gt;Gateless&lt;/a&gt;, and those
quotes were some of the most interesting parts of that book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was honestly a bit of a letdown. Not that the book is bad. In fact, I&amp;#39;m glad
I read it, and found it generally interesting and relevant. But it wasn&amp;#39;t what I
had imagined / hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hoped for a book that would outline very precisely a great number of
&amp;quot;motivation hacks&amp;quot; that could be called on. In reality, there are less than I
hoped (12-15 or so) and they aren&amp;#39;t discussed in any great depth. The book is
mostly concerned with how the authors used those in practice — which is
legitimately impressive and inspiring. Those still can be a game changer, but I
had passing familiarity with most of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I hoped beyond that was for a more technical angle, in particular with
regards to the psychology of these motivation tricks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another objection I have is that very clearly the author is someone that was
very accomplished to begin with, before tackling all the challenges in the book.
A great part of what makes those hacks successful, in my opinion, is the
groundwork laid by a consistent productivity habit. This means the techniques
might be less effective than it seems in people who do not have this record of
accomplishment and consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, if you cannot immediately name some motivation hacks and you&amp;#39;re in the
mood to get some motivation into you to tackle some important projects, this is
recommended reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-laws-of-human-nature&quot;&gt;The Laws of Human Nature&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Robert Greene&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started this, but I do not know if I will finish it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not the first book by Robert Greene that I read. I&amp;#39;ve read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/13589182-mastery&quot;&gt;Mastery&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/1303.The_48_Laws_of_Power&quot;&gt;The 48 Laws of Power&lt;/a&gt;. I started &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/20995.The_Art_of_Seduction&quot;&gt;The Art of Seduction&lt;/a&gt;, but did
not finish for exactly the same reason as this book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greene is a pretty good author in my estimation. He writes well, in an
authoritative style whose old-fashionedness gives him charm. It is well
researched, and the historical examples are interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My problem with Greene is that the books are positionned as advice or education (or
to use a less charitable term, self-help). Personally, I find it hard to get
something very useful out of them besides inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strange thing is, Greene is generally correct. And when the ideas he
proposes veer machievellian (in the sense of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Prince&quot;&gt;the original&lt;/a&gt;), the
perspectives he proposes need to be considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, the ideas offered are rarely thought-provoking (at least I&amp;#39;ve
you are somewhat well-read), and difficult to operationalize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s talk about &amp;quot;The Laws of Human Nature&amp;quot; in particular. In it, Greene
examines fundamental human tendencies - how they can betray us, how they can be
exploited (by ourselves or others, for good or for evil).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the first few chapters, he recommends such things as listening deeply to
others, noticing when body language disagress with spoken language and setting
the tone for your team. All excellent ideas, albeit hardly anything I haven&amp;#39;t
heard before. The problem is that first, nobody would disagree that these are
good ideas, and second - even once you&amp;#39;ve resolved to, for instance, listen
deeply - how do you actually remember to do it in the heat of conversation?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, the book is entertaining to some extent, albeit massive. But
don&amp;#39;t expect too much in the way of terms of wisdom that you can act on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though, I am compelled to add... I appreciate there is a public for which
Greene&amp;#39;s perspective is foreign, and would be profusely useful. In a sense, I
think too much like the author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-age-of-em&quot;&gt;The Age of Em&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Robin Hanson&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vision of the future, which purports to be (more) based on scientific theories
than published alternatives. The author acknowledged this is very much only a
tiny possibility for the future, but at least one that does not seem grossly
contradictory with current scientific knowledge, both in the exact and social
sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally - I found myself thoroughly bored at the initial description of that
future. I might have been unfair to the book, as Hanson explicitly warns that he
will first describe the end point, then justify why he thinks this endpoint is
plausible — which is arguably the interesting part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, I don&amp;#39;t know if I&amp;#39;ll pick this again. Truth is this was a
moonshot, not something I&amp;#39;m fundamentally interested in. A big reason I gave it
a shot, was that Hanson is famous for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.overcomingbias.com/&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt; and in particular his writing
on biases and signalling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have other books that interest me more, but I needed some audiobooks to listen
to while running, and this proved easier to find than some other things on my
list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;basic-economics&quot;&gt;Basic Economics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Thomas Sowell&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basic Economics proved a tad too basic for me. It&amp;#39;s essentially a watered down
version of the political economy course I got in my first year at uni. It&amp;#39;s well
written, but it&amp;#39;s a bad fit for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I however very much recommend following &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ThomasSowell&quot;&gt;the twitter account&lt;/a&gt; that
tweets out quips quoted from Thomas Sowell&amp;#39;s books. They&amp;#39;re biting, usually
true, and often about simple ideas that are often misunderstood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;great-pretender&quot;&gt;Great Pretender&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seasons 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;great-pretender.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow! Here&amp;#39;s an anime that felt different. From the international setting and
bright pastel color palette to the amazing story-telling — there were so much
that was unique about this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It follows a group of conmen in a series of ambitious cons. Twists abounds! It&amp;#39;s
almost a trick — there are enough twists that it becomes difficult to call any
one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not going to dither much — just watch this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tomb-raider-king&quot;&gt;Tomb Raider King&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Up to chapter 186&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pitch of this one is that suddenly &amp;quot;tombs&amp;quot; start to appear in the world,
holding sentient relics which can bestow their owner great powers, though the
relics generally try to take advantage of their owners.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hero is part of a tomb raiding team, gets betrayed, but by the magic of
scenario, gets sent back 15 years in the past, at the start of the relic
phenomenon. There, he can use his knowledge to get ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and, &lt;em&gt;of course&lt;/em&gt; he also gain special abilities that he can level. Duh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setup leads to inventive situations, exploiting all kind of relics&amp;#39; power.
The story does not try to be &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; clever or overly consistent, but the
relentless action helps suppress potential suspension of disbelief.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest difference from other webtoon however is that the main character is
kind of a dick. He&amp;#39;s not evil in the sense of murdering people in cold blood,
but he&amp;#39;s not a nice person either, never hesitating to use other people to his
advantage. Story-wise, that&amp;#39;s not particularly good or bad, but it&amp;#39;s different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Entertaining enough, but doesn&amp;#39;t crack my top list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-untethered-soul&quot;&gt;The Untethered Soul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Michael Alan Singer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s starting to be a theme, but here is yet another book and started and put
back almost immediately. I had picked up the recommendation from somewhere and
it&amp;#39;s saving grace was that I was able to find an audiobook on it easily.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a book about mindfulness, but the start of it felt rather very basic, and
offering zero insights to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re looking for books on mindfulness, I&amp;#39;d recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/6708.The_Power_of_Now&quot;&gt;The Power of Now&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22878980-you-are-here&quot;&gt;You Are Here&lt;/a&gt;. The first one is more &amp;quot;mystical&amp;quot;, but quite interersting, while
the second one is a down to earth guide to more mental calm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some quotes of the &lt;em&gt;The Power of Now&lt;/em&gt; made it into my &lt;a href=&quot;/unconstraining&quot;&gt;Unconstraining&lt;/a&gt; post from
way back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;beastars&quot;&gt;Beastars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;beastars.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a world of anthropomorphized animals, a socially awkward wolf falls in love
with a spunky rabbit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The animals are ostensibly vegetarian (interestingly - not vegan), but the
carnivores&amp;#39; instincts leads to what can only be described as &amp;quot;frayed race
relationships&amp;quot;. The whole thing is also quite Japanese to boot, including a
hefty dose of what I&amp;#39;d call &amp;quot;societal cynicism&amp;quot; (though they might not see it
the same way, I suppose).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this setup speak little to the goodness of the show. And good it is. I&amp;#39;d
say its strength are really unusual and highly interesting characters.
Recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought season 2, while still quite good, was a bit weaker. The ending, in
particular, left me super perplexed. I&amp;#39;m not sure why the director believed
going in the chosen direction would make for a good, engaging or satisfying
conclusion to the storyline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;better-call-saul&quot;&gt;Better Call Saul&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;better-call-saul.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better Call Saul is as good as ever. I haven&amp;#39;t written about the show before,
but I&amp;#39;ve been a fan of the first four seasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I love about BCS is how, on the surface, not much is happening, but
thanks to the incredible acting, you perceive that the characters are going
through all sorts of emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or at least, it feels like not much is happening. This is not an action show,
but the plot is engrossing, and frankly excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Better Call Saul is of course a Breaking Bad&amp;#39;s spinoff. I always felt Better
Call Saul was a notch above. It&amp;#39;s been a while since I saw Breaking Bad, so who
knows. It might also be that Breaking Bad is much more conflicted, in a sense.
You want to root for Walt, but you also dislike him (and the same is true, to a
lesser extent, for Jesse). Better Call Saul, despite having plenty of conflict,
is easier to enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this review is not doing justice to the show at all, but trust me, it&amp;#39;s
worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;wandavision&quot;&gt;WandaVision&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started watching this because so many people were talking about it. I was
hoping it was going something a bit un-marvelish (it&amp;#39;s about Wanda the Scarlet
Witch and Vision the android - MCU characters) - and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sj9J2ecsSpo&quot;&gt;trailer&lt;/a&gt;
was intriguing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, in the end, it wasn&amp;#39;t to be. The trailer essentially gives you the plot
of the first three episodes, which are parodies of old TV shows, with ominous
signs interspersed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised to find out that quite a few reviewers found these parodies
delightful... I personally found them to be a bit of a drag. If you like old
shows, go watch them directly, it&amp;#39;s bound to be much better — the jokes weren&amp;#39;t
particularly great either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if you make it past the first three episodes, the intrigue kicks into
high gear and things get interesting. That being said, what you&amp;#39;re left with is
a typical Marvel experience: entertaining, eminently watchable, but not
particularly profound, fascinating, or delightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the show entertains until the end, I think the ending peters out a little
bit. Contrary to one might have hoped, there&amp;#39;s very little mystery being
unveiled (or rather, the mystery is disappointing). Whatever twists there are,
are ... unexpected, but not in a particularly good way. This is no Westworld.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not a must watch, but if you&amp;#39;re bored and like the MCU, then maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;cobra-kai&quot;&gt;Cobra Kai&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1 &amp;amp; 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;cobra-kai.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cobra Kai is absolutely delightful. This 34-years-after sequel of &lt;em&gt;The Karate
Kid&lt;/em&gt; offers to follow Johnny Lawrence — the main antagonist of the movie, and
rival of hero Daniel LaRusso — as he picks back Karate and resumes his rivarly
with Daniel, involving a bunch of local kids along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a cute idea, straigtht from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Nrzqc7F-Ans&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;How I Met Your Mother&lt;/em&gt; episode&lt;/a&gt;
episode. And if you watch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xCwwxNbtK6Y&quot;&gt;the trailer&lt;/a&gt;, cute and naive and
goofy is what it looks like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But people, this thing has depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is, still, in a sense a very innocent show. Innocent is probably not the
right word, but it has this earnestnest that you don&amp;#39;t see much in TV shows
these days — the stuff the original was made of. There&amp;#39;s good reasons we see
little of it. It&amp;#39;s been done successfully many time before, and if you fail at
earnestness, then the failure always looks all the more ridiculous and
out-of-touch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cobra Kai wears its earnestness on its sleeve, but, surprisingly does not seek
to subvert it, at least not in the usual way. Instead of sticking to the usual
manichean schema (hero vs villain — whoever that may be), the show is
surprisingly nuanced. Both Johny and Daniel are often wrong-headed hotheads, but
both are essentially good people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The usual subversion of the classical story is that the (anti-)hero is an
asshole too. Here it&amp;#39;s that everyone is human. That sounds adorkable and a bit
too warm and fuzzy — which makes the show&amp;#39;s ability to pull it out so much more
impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show really runs with that theme, and it extends far wider than just Johnny
and Daniel. One particularly interesting way in which it does this is by
recasting the events of the original movie as essentially traumatic for our two
protagonists. While Daniel &amp;quot;wins&amp;quot; in the movie, he still remember being a
bullied kid. And of course, Mr Miyagi&amp;#39;s (his wise Japanese sensei in the movie)
teachings become the cornerstone of his life philosophy. But Johnny sees Daniel
as up-an-comer who stole his girlfriend and his karate title — an endeavour in
which he had invested his whole personal (and fragile) self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That brings to maybe the thing that makes me the most uneasy about the show —
it&amp;#39;s reliance on misunderstandings between characters. Because everyone involved
is essentially good, it often feels like if everyone could sit together and say
their piece, most issues would be solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Normally I hate misunderstanding-driven plots. Romeo &amp;amp; Juliet is hot garbage in
my book. The show walks a tight line regarding misunderstandings. Characters do
sometimes talk things out. Things never spiral out of control on the back of
increasing misunderstandings. But the misunderstandings keep happening,
necessary to carry a conflict that perhaps can&amp;#39;t sustained solely on the basis
of the philosophical disagreements. I must say that so far I&amp;#39;m impressed with
the show&amp;#39;s ability to perform this balancing act. I just hope they can keep it
up for the next three seasons!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not sure you&amp;#39;ll be as impressed by Cobra Kai as I was (though I sure hope
so), but if you enjoyed The Karate Kid, you certainly need to try this one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Season 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the above was written before watching season 2. I think season 2 holds up
pretty well. It definitely keeps toeing the line with misunderstandings - but
nothing show-ruining. Having actually seen two episodes of the third season
already, I&amp;#39;m very curious as to where this takes two characters that feature
prominently in season 2 — namely Kreese and Tory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was surprised by the attempt to also flesh these characters, given them a more
sympathetic side (and early in season 3, more backstory). This is particulary
true for Kreese, which the shows sets up as a clear-cut antagonist, playing
ominous music every occasion it gets. It&amp;#39;s interesting and certainly not what
you expect. Though I must say compared to something like Game of Thrones, where
you actually get to &amp;quot;see&amp;quot; the inner thought process of &amp;quot;bad&amp;quot; characters, it can
sometimes feel a bit weird. Curious to see what season 3 does with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mushoku-tensei-jobless-reincarnation&quot;&gt;Mushoku Tensei (Jobless Reincarnation)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;mushoku-tensei.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easily one of my favourite anime of the winter season (a tie with Attack on
Titans, probably). It&amp;#39;s not exactly surprising, it&amp;#39;s about a loser who dies and
gets revived in a fantasy world as a fully-intelligent toddler. That just sound
like all these webtoon I keep reviewing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides plot affinity, the thing is extremely well done. It looks georgeous.
It&amp;#39;s too short (only 11 episodes, though a second season should come later this
year), but the pacing is tight. The show doesn&amp;#39;t repeat itself, nor does it
longer too long in one place. Character development is had.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gigguk published excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tDh5Us8rl80&quot;&gt;video praise&lt;/a&gt; for the anime, which I wholeheartedly
agree with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Truly, one of the better isekai in recent memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rezero&quot;&gt;Re:Zero&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 2, pt. 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/#rezero&quot;&gt;S1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#rezero-season-2-part-1&quot;&gt;S1, pt. 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my review of &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#rezero-season-2-part-1&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;, I said I was unsure what to make of this
season, that it would entirely depend on how part 2 delivers on the setup from
part 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well folks, I&amp;#39;m disappointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like I feared, cutting in the middle with the balls hanging in the air was
a terrible idea. I couldn&amp;#39;t understand what was going on for the first few
episodes, and absolutely no summary (explicit or implicit) was offered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was made worse by the fact that the plot is needlessly convoluted. My major
beef is with the characters&amp;#39; motivations. Despite all the revelations, I still
have no idea what Roswal wants or stands for. It&amp;#39;s not even a mystery that works
well — there are multiple conversations where this could (should, really) come
out, but somehow Subaru never asks the right questions. He doesn&amp;#39;t even seem to
think he&amp;#39;s missing anything. Beatrice&amp;#39;s motivation is paper-thin and frankly
dumb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author&amp;#39;s brain just seem wired to another dimension (like all adaptations,
the question remains whether the fault lies with the original or the
adaptation). A few times I realized that something I had taken to be some
harmless exposition was actually an important piece of context — and you were
apparently supposed to get it. Again, this is made worse by the fact that the
show makes no effort whatsoever to help you make sense of things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this point it feels lazy, almost sleazy. The mystery feels artificial,
added on just for effect, not as something that makes sense within the plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add to this a bunch of completely nonsensical (and frankly boring) speeches, and
the result quite tepid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some good part to the story though. Emilia finally gets some character
development. The ending does feel satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;log-horizon&quot;&gt;Log Horizon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/every-anime/#log-horizon&quot;&gt;S1 &amp;amp; S2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not even disappointed, I&amp;#39;m devastated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve told many people that Log Horizon is one of my favourite anime. I evend
said in my review: &amp;quot;The only bad thing about Log Horizon is that it is
unfinished.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well I jinxed it, because this third season is absolutely terrible and devoid of
the charm of the previous instalments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly, the show commits the gravest sin of violating &amp;quot;show, don&amp;#39;t tell&amp;quot;. We are
being told stuff con-stant-ly. We are being told how characters feels. How
decisions will impact them. There is absolutely no good reason to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arcs are pretty boring too. It feels like there&amp;#39;s very little at stake. The
pacing is completely unbalanced: the first 5 episodes or so are characters
talking and thinking without any action whatsoever. There is no overarching
theme to the season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game mechanics still feature, but in a pretty uninimaginative way, and without
the accompanying broad consequences on the world that made the first two seasons
so interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, to be fair, Sasha watched the first two seasons recently and claims that
season 2 is much more like this than I remember. I do remember a couple
excellent episodes, but it&amp;#39;s been like 6 years at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;that-time-i-got-reincarnated-as-a-slime&quot;&gt;That Time I Got Reincarnated as a Slime&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/#that-time-i-got-reincarnated-as-a-slime&quot;&gt;S1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slime is just being slime: a zero-calories snack, entertaining but not
particularly impactful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a sense that&amp;#39;s too bad. You just know Rimuru the slime can&amp;#39;t lose, and that
does undercut the show&amp;#39;s attempt at drama. Frankly, I would have loved for the
show to go dark all of a sudden, but it was not the be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;&lt;summary&gt;Mild &lt;b&gt;spoiler&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/summary&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The show does in fact get &amp;quot;dark&amp;quot;, but not in tone. Mass-murder is just done
matter-of-factly, but the show is still on the same trajectory: the rise of the
ever-growing, ever-more-powerful alliance of Rimuru&amp;#39;s band of nice monsters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-promised-neverland&quot;&gt;The Promised Neverland&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/#the-promised-neverland&quot;&gt;S1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Season 2 cuts on the three-level deep plots, and adds some action/adventure. It
was generally solid, ... but something felt missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it was because this is only 11 episodes long. Even though the episodes are
well-done, you can&amp;#39;t help but feel rushed. I&amp;#39;m not incredibly satisfied with
this explanation — we should not seek length for length&amp;#39;s sake. But I&amp;#39;m not
entirely sure what they should have done to add weight and emotional impact to
the plot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friends had told me that the show cut some arcs form the story, but
apparently &lt;a href=&quot;https://comicbook.com/anime/news/the-promised-neverland-season-2-bad-anime-credit/&quot;&gt;the issues run deeper&lt;/a&gt; and, at the very least, the
show&amp;#39;s screenwriters seem unsatisfied with the show&amp;#39;s direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dr-stone-stone-wars&quot;&gt;Dr Stone: Stone Wars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5/#dr-stone&quot;&gt;S1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I continue to very much like Dr Stone. The second season is a continuation of
the story of the first season, and the themes and vibes are similar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stand by what I said in &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5/#dr-stone&quot;&gt;my season 1 review&lt;/a&gt;, so you can
go read that if you&amp;#39;re interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;attack-on-titans&quot;&gt;Attack on Titans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 4, part 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/every-anime/#attack-on-titan&quot;&gt;S1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;/more-anime/#attack-on-titan-season-2&quot;&gt;S2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/#attack-on-titans-season-3-part-1&quot;&gt;S3
pt. 1&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4/#attack-on-titans-season-3-part-2&quot;&gt;S3 pt. 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;attack-on-titans.webp&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Season 3 felt like a lull, but season 4 delivers an electroshock. Holy shit! I
didn&amp;#39;t expect this final season to be one of the best of the winter season, but
it was, and easily at that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is tight, and engrossing from the start. Things feel fresh, due in
part to a multi-years time skip, and the decision to center the first few
episodes on the introduction of completely new characters that have an important
role to play in this final season.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is Attack on Titans at its best, not only are the action scenes as good as
ever (although perhaps there will be too little of them for some people), but
the season tells an interesting story in its own right, and the final pieces of
the puzzle finally fall into place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, a master class in how to do character&amp;#39;s motivations and mystery right.
Take that, Re:Zero!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, I&amp;#39;m glad that Attack on Titans probably won&amp;#39;t end up in the &amp;quot;Game of
Throne bucket&amp;quot; of good shows that are hard to recommend because of their shitty
ending.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, you&amp;#39;ve got to admire the gall of the studio, who only let out that this
was &lt;em&gt;part 1&lt;/em&gt; of &amp;quot;Attack on Titans: &lt;strong&gt;The Final Season&lt;/strong&gt;&amp;quot; after the last episode
was released. (At that point, most people&amp;#39;s money was on there being a movie that
would wrap up the story.) What a troll.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-wow-diary&quot;&gt;The WoW Diary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book by John Staats&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s no secret that World of Warcraft is close to my heart. I sank countless
hours in it as a teenager, and I even dabbled in private servers programming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As such, The WoW Diary is an invaluable (and in fact, one of the only) source of
information on how the game was actually made, written by someone who worked on
it. John Staats designed and build the looks of most of the dungeons in the
original game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not sure a review makes much sense, but I thought the book was great, given
my interest in the topic. I&amp;#39;m not sure someone who doesn&amp;#39;t really care about how
games are made would find it interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here a few things I learned from reading the book that also surprised me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite Blizzard&amp;#39;s fame as one of the top video game studios, and one comitted
to quality at that, the working conditions seemed terrible. The team was
crunching on and off for &lt;em&gt;years&lt;/em&gt;. The salary is said to be only competitive
after bonuses, of which there were little while the game was still in
development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The flip side is how familial the structure felt small and familial, and
internal mobility was not only possible but common. Many if not most of the
slots that opened in the team were filled directly from the &lt;abbr
title=&quot;Quality Assurance&quot;&gt;QA&lt;/abbr&gt; department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had in mind that the team that made the game was relatively small, but in
fact it did number some 80-90 people towards the end of development, among
which at least half were developers. There was also a sizeable number of 3D
artists, texture artists, item designers, quest designers, etc. I wonder if
the same work could be done by fewer people today or if it still would require
around the same number of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The team did not use version control until the tail end of development! Long
periods of &amp;quot;broken build&amp;quot; is a common refrain in the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The labor of some of the non-developers workforce looked to me like it was
excruciatingly manual and repetitive. There were some pretty impressive
in-house tools, but getting new features in those was apparently a struggle.
To me, hiring four &amp;quot;helping hands&amp;quot; instead of a new tool developer seems like
an obvious oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;casablanca&quot;&gt;Casablanca&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is rated by some as the best movie of all times. I&amp;#39;m not sure it&amp;#39;s all
that, but the movie&amp;#39;s reputation is well deserved - it has aged remarkably
gracefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of listening to me talk about it, go watch this video on Humphrey Bogart
— it&amp;#39;ll make you want to watch some of his movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;720&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/dVs4-91xduY&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-03-27T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/reviews-10</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/reviews-10</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Running Myself Ragged</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;The past few months have been some of the hardest in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is not saying too much — I&amp;#39;ve had, by and large, a very happy life. But as
far as I ever came close to something maybe remotely resembling burn out, that
time is now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was due to a combination of factors. Mostly it was the added workload of
&lt;a href=&quot;/compilers&quot;&gt;teaching a class&lt;/a&gt; on top of main job (and doing it in my own effort-intensive
way), and picking up a hobby of very (and not entirely intentionally) &lt;a href=&quot;/heat&quot;&gt;stressful
trading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, for all the unpleasantness, I think there is a silver lining too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one, it feels like my work capacity has permanently increased. I feel much
more confident in my ability to stay on track and consistently work towards a
long-term project. In particular, I think I might now be able to move faster by
being able to spend more time on a project per time unit (day/week/...) than I
did previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also learned a lot. About finance, teaching, and compilers even. I got to
improve &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/autumn&quot;&gt;existing software projects&lt;/a&gt; and even create new ones (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/uranium&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;,
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/sigh&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These benefits did come at the cost of running too close to the red line, for
too long. I think a &lt;a href=&quot;/training&quot;&gt;lifting&lt;/a&gt; metaphor is in order. If you want to get stronger
or bigger, you need to train hard. But if you push yourself &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; hard or for
too long, you indulge in &lt;em&gt;overtraining&lt;/em&gt;, which is detrimental to your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So another lessons from all this is that I might push myself hard in the future,
but I&amp;#39;ll avoid to making it quite this intense. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/yLLkWMDbC9ZNKbjDG/slack&quot;&gt;Only with slack can one be a
righteous dude.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the situation had me do a lot of hard thinking about where I was at,
and where I wanted to go. &amp;quot;Never waste a good crisis&amp;quot;, as they say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, when you&amp;#39;re &amp;quot;working&amp;quot; all the time and most of the respite goes out the
window, you&amp;#39;re really forced to consider whether you actually like what you&amp;#39;re
doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, some of what I did (in which I include my job, teaching, and trading) I
liked, and some I liked less. I&amp;#39;m planning to make changes. But first, maybe
I&amp;#39;ll take a breather.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS&lt;/strong&gt;: I hesitated to write this post. The reason is that, while I write for myself
first, I like to write things that are useful for other people, even if the
style is a bit rough. This is mostly about my state of mind, there are not too
many details (on purpose), and I&amp;#39;m not entirely sure the lessons transpose that
easily to other people in other situations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this blog acts as a public record of what&amp;#39;s going on with me, and this
felt momentous enough that it deserved a mention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, I&amp;#39;ve read similar things form other people in the past. Not only do I
remember them, but they have helped shape how I think about such things (in
particular, Sebastian Marshall&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;/celerity/#06-pace-maximum-vs-maximum-sustainable-speed&quot;&gt;writings on Celerity&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://podbay.fm/p/the-ultraworking-podcast/e/1571375400&quot;&gt;his
personal account on pushing himself too far&lt;/a&gt;). So maybe it&amp;#39;s not that
useless.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-03-25T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/ragged</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/ragged</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stock Market Adventures: Heat</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/options/&quot;&gt;Stock Market Adventures: Options &amp;amp; The Wheel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/options/&quot;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, I presented the wheel option strategy (and gave a whole
bunch of background on options).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also said that personally, I was mostly selling puts on growth stocks, using a
wide margin of safety afforded by their high implied volatility. (You do not
know what any of these words mean? Go read &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/options/&quot;&gt;the last article&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This did not work out too well. Or rather, it worked fantastically well, but I
failed to execute a proper pivot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t worry, I&amp;#39;m not ruined. In fact, I haven&amp;#39;t even lost money compared to when
I started trading with this strategy — a whopping 4 months ago. But I am also
not up much, while I was up 30% at some point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What happened? The market was bullish on growth, and the strategy was making
bank. Then, at then end of February, there was unrest in the bond market, and
that spilled over to the stock market. This hit tech stocks the hardest, with
the Nasdaq 100 shedding more than 10% from its high, back to where it was last
December.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It did hit growth stocks even harder. (&lt;em&gt;Growth stock&lt;/em&gt; nice euphemism generally
used for the stock of companies that do not yet make money and/or is very
overvalued — speculative stocks, really). Not everything was affected — many
people talked of &amp;quot;a rotation into value&amp;quot; (where a &lt;em&gt;value stock&lt;/em&gt; is essentially
the opposite of a growth stock).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My puts quickly dropped in value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I messed up. I should simply have taken my losses and liquidated
my positions. Why? Things were outside expected parameters. They were dropping,
but I did not understand why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I have two new rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exit out of your positions when your assumptions are violated in a way that
puts your capital in danger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you do not understand what is happening and you&amp;#39;re losing money, close your
positions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, it&amp;#39;s better to try to understand what is happening. I did, and I now
know much more about the bond market than previously (expect an article on that
topic soon). But I still did not really understand (or maybe believe) the causal
link between the bond market and the stock market. I thought &amp;quot;certainly, it
can&amp;#39;t be that people are panicking over bond yields raising to a measly 1.5%
(way below March 2020&amp;#39;s already low 2.5%)&amp;quot;. But apparently, it is possible — and
of course selling begets more selling through &lt;em&gt;deleveraging&lt;/em&gt;: as losses mount,
those who trade on margin are forced to liquidate assets to maintain their
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Margin_(finance)&quot;&gt;margin ratio&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So instead, I thought this was a temporary spike down (albeit a particularly
virulent one), as there had been a few, and the market would pick up again.
#buythedip was trending on Twitter, so I wasn&amp;#39;t the only clueless person out
there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;#39;t a temporary spike down, and so that&amp;#39;s that. Add to that a dumb (but
totally unrelated) trading mistake I made, and I&amp;#39;m back at square one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This whole adventure reminded me of the titular sequence from the (awesome)
movie &lt;em&gt;Heat&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot;
src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/rGPWW9Pjzto&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video
player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write;
encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil McCauley: A guy told me one time, &amp;quot;Don&amp;#39;t let yourself get attached to
anything you are not willing to walk out on in 30 seconds flat if you feel the
heat around the corner.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vincent Hanna : What are you, a monk?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil McCauley : I have a woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vincent Hanna : What do you tell her?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil McCauley : I tell her I&amp;#39;m a salesman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vincent Hanna : So then, if you spot me coming around that corner... you just
gonna walk out on this woman? Not say good bye?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neil McCauley : That&amp;#39;s the discipline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heat came around the corner, and I did not walk out. That was as much part
of the strategy as everything else, but I realized it only too late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not all that bad. I &amp;quot;lost money&amp;quot;, but also I didn&amp;#39;t lose anything I didn&amp;#39;t
gain in the market. And I learned a ton. How often do you get paid to learn? The
only thing I regret is that it did bring a lot of stress into my life at a time
where I could have done without it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s next? Interesting times for sure. With the market uncertain for growth
stocks, the previous strategy is out of the question. I will probably retreat to
running a wheel-like scheme on safer stocks. Time to put the theory to the test
and see if I&amp;#39;m abel to beat the index. This should also be a bit easier on my
blood pressure. And I&amp;#39;ll keep learning and experimenting. Maybe some other
system will prove superior in the current market conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-03-23T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/heat</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/heat</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cardio Training</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;This post is part of the &lt;a href=&quot;/training/&quot;&gt;Training Series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-8/&quot;&gt;Last time&lt;/a&gt;, the gyms had just closed again and I was looking at bodyweight
movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up training my handstand for a few weeks (complemented by a rather usual
set of home exercises - see &lt;a href=&quot;/training/&quot;&gt;previous posts&lt;/a&gt; for flavour), but
I&amp;#39;m ashamed to report that while I improved, I&amp;#39;m still incapable of a
free-standing handstand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something I failed to appreciate is how much strength a handstand actually
requires, and so ramping up was no luxury. In the end, my real Achilles&amp;#39; heel is
balance however. But practice makes perfect, and I expect I&amp;#39;ll revisit this
sooner rather than later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the heels of this, I decided to work on my cardio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many people think that weight lifting (particularly the heavy kind) and cardio
sit on opposit ends of the exercise continuum, but I think this is far from the
truth. Weight lifting does actually engage your aerobic (aero = air) system
quite a bit. Try squatting your maximum weight, then see how winded you get!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, it is true that weight lifting tends to be a more intense kind
of effort (more akin to sprinting) rather than steady over a long period of
time. (Note that &lt;em&gt;cardio&lt;/em&gt; does not imply long session, that&amp;#39;s more specifically
&lt;em&gt;steady-state cardio&lt;/em&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve recently read &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-9/#tactical-barbell&quot;&gt;Tactical Barbell&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-9/#tactical-barbell-2-conditioning&quot;&gt;Tactical Barbell 2:
Conditioning&lt;/a&gt; (links are to my short reviews of them). The first didn&amp;#39;t
teach me much, but the second was intriguing, and so I decided to follow its
&amp;quot;base-building&amp;quot; 8-weeks program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-program&quot;&gt;The Program&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The program is relatively simple. For the 5 first week, you&amp;#39;ll do &lt;em&gt;strength
endurance&lt;/em&gt; circuits on Monday and Thursday, and &lt;em&gt;endurance&lt;/em&gt; training (i.e.
steady-state cardio) on Tuesday, Wednesday and Saturday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The amount of work is designed to increase progressively. The weekly suggested
endurance session duration is 30/40/50/60/45-60 minutes (for week 1 to 5,
respectively). For strength endurance, the program has you do 3 circuits on
Monday and 2 on Thursday (excepted on the fourth week, where you&amp;#39;ll do a single
one each day), with 20/30/40/50/50 repetitions per exercise for each circuit
(from week 1 to 5, respectively).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Saturday endurance session is bracketed by two recovery days and is meant to
push yourself. The goal is last longer than you did during the week, but not to
exceed two hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the thre last week, you&amp;#39;ll do &lt;em&gt;max strength&lt;/em&gt; training (roughly classical
strength training) on Monday and Thursday, and HIC (High Intensity Circuits) on
Tuesday and Friday). Saturday is for &lt;em&gt;endurance&lt;/em&gt;, but not longer than one hour.
Wednesday and Sunday are for recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;exercise-selection&quot;&gt;Exercise Selection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My prime pick for endurance training was running. The book proposes many
alternatives, but most of them still involve running (sometimes interspersed
with bouts of exercises, or modified, such as running while carrying weight).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are also indoors alternative, but those typically require access to a gym.
We inherited my sister&amp;#39;s elleptical bike at home, and so I did use that a couple
time. It didn&amp;#39;t feel quite right - in fact, it was too easy. I never really got
winded, and making it hard means increasing the resistances which makes your
ass-cheeks work more than your heart. In the end, something that did work
decently well was continuous running while stopping every 6 minutes to do a
couple of burpees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the time though, I did vanilla running. I own a pair of running shoes
(that have relatively little use over the years), and I thought I might as well
focus on the basics. At first, and quite to my surprise, cardio wasn&amp;#39;t a
limiting factor at all. Instead, I developed mild muscular pain as I was
running, mostly at the front of my shin (the tibialis anterior?) and, to a lower
extent, on the inner side of the tight, right above the kneecap (the vastus
medialis, or &amp;quot;teardrop&amp;quot; muscle). It did take two weeks, but the pain did go
away. Maybe the consequences of spending the whole year mostly at home and
walking a whole lot less?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running still wasn&amp;#39;t that easy though. At the end, I was running for about 75
minutes over a bit less than 10km, for a 7:45 min/km average pace. That&amp;#39;s
nothing to brag about. The average male time for running a marathon is 4 hrs 13
minutes — which is faster than my pace for more than 4 times the distance. I&amp;#39;m
probably lugging around more mass than most marathon runners, but I still have a
ways to go. It was also very hard not to walk for a few minutes of the whole
duration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For &lt;em&gt;strength-endurance&lt;/em&gt;, the book suggests picking any full-body routine that
can be done for high amount of reps. I picked something dumbell-based, doing
romanian deadlifts, squats, floor presses, overhead presses, trap shrugs and
rows. I used 10kg barbells. Not all of those were equally easy. Doing 50 floor
presses was easy enough for me (especially given the ramp-up in the number of
sets), but for overhead presses, I had to take two short breaks in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For max strength, I went fairly classic. See &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-6&quot;&gt;my July post&lt;/a&gt; if you need some exercise
ideas, but I did actually include less variety than back then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I introduced was the single-arm pushed. I&amp;#39;m quite proud to finally
have gotten the hang of it. Doing handstand practice and archer pushups in the
recent past must have helped build for the foundation. Then what was needed was
for the form to click: I start like a diamond pushup, but with legs spread far
apart, then I move one arm to be straight along my body, hand grabbing the leg
on the same side. You also have to, on some level, understand you can do it: you
can&amp;#39;t half-ass push through a one-arm pushup. If you don&amp;#39;t manage, using fingers
from the non-working arms as support is a nice hack — you can progressively
remove fingers until you don&amp;#39;t need that arm anymore. Once it clicked, it wasn&amp;#39;t
that hard, and I can do 10 reps without too much difficulty now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercise is tiring though, and I probably made a mistake to run the same
session twice a week. One-handed pushups + bulgarian split squats twice a week
had me really beat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the HIC (High Intensity Circuit) session, I shopped around a little bit, but
ended up mostly rope skipping. The first mode was simply rope skipping with
maximal effort for about two minutes, with long breaks (3+ minutes) in between,
6 times. A variant was to rope skip (or run on the elliptical, though that is
much easier), and alternate with dumbell swings and dumbell snatches (those were
suppose to be done with kettlebells, but dumbbells is all I had).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rope skipping (and I suppose, all the running that preceded it) did wonder for
my calves. I think calf raises are dead to me now, it&amp;#39;s all about skipping,
baby!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Theoretically, the bad thing about rope skipping is that the shocks are not
optimal for muscle hypertrophy. However, they can reinforce the bones, which has
a lot of cross-talk with the muscle. So theretically, a regiment of rope
skipping can ultimately benefit leg hypertrophy, if you can accept to take easy
on your squat for a little while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;next&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What&amp;#39;s next? I yearn for the gym to reopen, but in the meantime I&amp;#39;m programming
something that looks like a &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-7&quot;&gt;DUP&lt;/a&gt; at home. It&amp;#39;s more difficult to vary intensity
for the same exercise at home, so I&amp;#39;m mostly varying the exercises. Here&amp;#39;s a
copy of the listing of what I&amp;#39;ve planned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-org&quot;&gt;* One
** Bulgarian Split Squats, 20kg
** Regular Pushups
** Single Leg Deadlift
** Dumbell Overhead Press, 20kg
** Hollow Man Crunches
** Twisting Situps

* Two
** Romanian Deadlift, 20kg
** Pike Pushups
** Pistol Squats
** Floor Press, 20kg
** Black Widow Knee Slide
** Butterfly Situps

* Three
** Single Arm Pushup
** Barbell Swings
** TXR Face Pulls
** Bodyweight Squats
** W Ab Raises
** Threading The Needle

* Four
** Pullups (spread accross the session)
** Biceps Curl / Standing Triceps Extension
** Lying Leg Curls / Reverse Hypers
** Seated Corkscrew
** Leviation Crunches
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m doing one exercise of each of four types every session: squat-like,
deadlift-like, arms and shoulders. I finish every session with two small ab
exercises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My heavy squat move is the bulgarian split squat, the heavy deadlift is the
romanian (it&amp;#39;s not really heavy, but I don&amp;#39;t have a better idea — maybe when I
load the one leg version?), the heavy arms exercise is the one-arm pushup, and
the heavy shoulder exercise is the pullup (though the pike is no joke!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan to run this for a block until performance starts to degrade or plateau
significantly, so probably around 8 weeks (at which point I&amp;#39;ll also accept a
small pleateau as a reason to stop).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For after that, I&amp;#39;m thinking of re-working the handstand in the mix. Maybe some
other bodyweight exercises too?&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-03-17T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/cardio</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/cardio</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Favourite Quotes from &quot;Hell Yeah Or No&quot;</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sive.rs/n&quot;&gt;Book Homepage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Derek Sivers&amp;#39; writing style is incredibly terse and pithy. And frankly, it&amp;#39;s a
pleasure to read. The book is very short, and I would recommend you read it in
full.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still here is my favourites quotes. Titles are chapter titles, and what follows
are quotes (mostly) and paraphrases from that chapter. Sometimes the chapter
title is enough!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-if-you-didnt-need-money-or-attention&quot;&gt;What if you didn’t need money or attention?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-are-you-doing&quot;&gt;Why are you doing?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can’t diffuse your energy, trying to do a little bit of everything, or
you’ll always be in conﬂict with yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;imitate-we-are-imperfect-mirrors&quot;&gt;Imitate. We are imperfect mirrors.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your imitation will turn out much different from the original. Maybe even
better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;small-actions-change-your-self-identity&quot;&gt;Small actions change your self-identity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;if-youre-not-feeling-hell-yeah-then-say-no&quot;&gt;If you’re not feeling “hell yeah!” then say no&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;im-a-very-slow-thinker&quot;&gt;I’m a very slow thinker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People say that your first reaction is the most honest, but I disagree. Your
first reaction is usually outdated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don’t need to answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can say, &amp;quot;I don’t know,&amp;quot; and take your time to answer after thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-will-this-game-end&quot;&gt;How will this game end?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you start something, think of the ways it could end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the smart choice is to say no to the whole game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;relax-for-the-same-result&quot;&gt;Relax for the same result&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So apparently all of that exhausting, red-faced, full-on push-push-push I had
been doing had given me only a 4 percent boost. I could just take it easy and
get 96 percent of the results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] Then I notice that I’m all stressed out about something or driving myself
to exhaustion, I remember that bike ride and try dialing back my effort by 50
percent. It’s been amazing how often everything gets done just as well and just
as fast, with what feels like half the effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;disconnect&quot;&gt;Disconnect&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the best, happiest, and most creatively productive times in my life have
something in common: being disconnected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silence is a great canvas for your thoughts. That vacuum helps turn all of your
inputs into output. That lack of interruption helps you ﬂow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often ask me what they can do to be more successful. I say disconnect.
Even if just for a few hours. Unplug. Turn off your phone and Wi-Fi. Focus.
Write. Practice. Create. That’s what’s rare and valuable these days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You get no competitive edge from consuming the same stuff everyone else is
consuming. It’s rare, now, to focus. And it gives such better rewards&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;think-like-a-bronze-medalist-not-silver&quot;&gt;Think like a bronze medalist, not silver&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of comparing up to the next higher situation, compare down to the
next-lower one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-assume-im-below-average&quot;&gt;I assume I’m below average&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To assume you’re below average is to admit you’re still learning. You focus on
what you need to improve, not your past accomplishments&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;obvious-to-you-amazing-to-others&quot;&gt;Obvious to you. Amazing to others.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everybody’s ideas seem obvious to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;subtract&quot;&gt;Subtract&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to think I need something else. It’s hard to look instead at what to
remove. Most of us have too much baggage, too many commitments, and too many
priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;seeking-inspiration&quot;&gt;Seeking inspiration?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The word “inspiration” usually means “something that mentally stimulates you.”
But “inspiration” also means to breathe in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meanings poetically combine when you think of yourself breathing in
thoughts, filling your body with ideas. But don’t forget to breathe out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;possible-futures&quot;&gt;Possible Futures&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve got seventy-two different futures in there as of today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few times a year, I read through them all. Some seem stupid now, but some get
more and more enticing with time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I ﬁnish a big project and I’m feeling ready for a new future, I open this
folder and pick one to make real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;whatever-scares-you-go-do-it&quot;&gt;Whatever scares you, go do it.&lt;/h3&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-03-08T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/hell-yeah</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/hell-yeah</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stock Market Adventures: Options &amp; The Wheel</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/stock-market-intro/&quot;&gt;Intro&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said last time I mostly trade using options. In this article I will explain my
main strategy, known as &lt;em&gt;the wheel&lt;/em&gt;. But first, I&amp;#39;ll have to give you a bit of
backgrounds on options. I&amp;#39;ll finish by a more technical explanation of option
pricing and linking to a few other intersting option strategies - in case you&amp;#39;re
interested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a long post, with a lot of words (and a few numbers). If
you&amp;#39;d rather watch videos instead, I strongly recommend &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLI2eVMd1wtdGwFXMFya1jHpWLvWw6a07X&quot;&gt;Growing Wealth&amp;#39;s
Options Trading Course&lt;/a&gt;. It will teach you option fundamentals, the
wheel strategy, and a few others beside. Also no one says you can&amp;#39;t read the
post &lt;strong&gt;and&lt;/strong&gt; watch the videos ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;option-basics&quot;&gt;Option Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;call option&lt;/em&gt; is a contract that allows (but does not force) you to buy 100
shares of a stock at a pre-determined price (the &lt;em&gt;strike price&lt;/em&gt;) until some
point in the future (the &lt;em&gt;expiration date&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conversely, a &lt;em&gt;put option&lt;/em&gt; allows you to sell 100 shares at a pre-determined
strike price until the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually buying or selling is called &amp;quot;exercising&amp;quot; the option. Options can be
American-style — exercisable at any time until expiration, or European-style —
exercisable only at expiration. In practice this does not make much of a
difference because, excepted in two specific cases, it is always more profitable
to sell an option than to exercise it before the expiration date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Exceptions explained. Feel free to skip!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first exception are that when the stock is going to pay a dividend, the
holder of an option may wish to exercise the option to benefit from the
dividend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second exception is when the option is not very liquid, meaning there is no
one interested in buying it at a greater price than the profit you would make by
exercising the option. This should be extremely rare, as I expect these market
inefficiencies to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/a/arbitrage.asp&quot;&gt;arbitraged&lt;/a&gt; away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Options must be purchased for a price which is called &lt;em&gt;the premium&lt;/em&gt;. This
premium is usually lower than the stock price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a simple scenario, if you buy a call option and hold it until expiration, you
will profit if the price of the stock ends up being superior to the sum of the
strike price and the premium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;call_profit_or_loss = stock_price - (strike_price + premium_paid)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For put options, the logic is reversed, you profit if the stock price goes down
enough:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;put_profit_or_loss = strike_price - (stock_price + premium_paid)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try to understand these formulas. The key idea for a call option is that it
allows you to purchase the stock at the strike price. If the current stock price
is above the strike price, you can buy the stock (through the call option) and
sell it for an instant markup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a put option, you can sell stock at the strike price. If the stock price is
under the strike price, you can buy the stock and sell it (through the put
option) for an instant markup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who do you buy these options from? Well, anyone really. Anyone that can buy
options can also sell options. An option is a contracts formed between two
parties, one that &amp;quot;buys&amp;quot; the option, and one that &amp;quot;sells&amp;quot; (or &amp;quot;writes&amp;quot;) it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The person selling the option is making a different bet than the buyer. She is
betting that the stock price will not be high enough for a call option to be
profitable, or that the stock price will not be low enough for a put option to
be profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that turns out true, the option is said to expire worthless. The buyer does
not execute the option (as that would be a money-losing move) and so lost the
premium he paid in the trade. The seller, on the other hand, profits by
pocketing the premium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Options are characterized by the triplet [underlying stock, strike price,
expiration date], so there a lot of possible combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three useful abbreviations are used to talk about strike prices: an option can
be &lt;em&gt;at the money&lt;/em&gt; (ATM) when the strike price is more or less equal to the
current stock price, &lt;em&gt;out of the money&lt;/em&gt; (OTM) when the strike price is
over/under (call/put) the stock price, and &lt;em&gt;in the money&lt;/em&gt; (ITM) when the strike
price is under/over (call/put) the stock price. When an option expires ITM, you
profit, if it expires OTM, you made a loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that OTM options are not worthless (before expiring) — they represent the
potential for the stock price to move in desired direction until the expiration
date. It&amp;#39;s even possible to make money by trading OTM options that have never
been ITM: it suffices to buy an OTM option, and sell it when the stock price has
moved in the right direction (up for call, down for put) - so when the option is
&amp;quot;less OTM&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-use-options&quot;&gt;Why Use Options&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why use options rather than buy and sell shares? There are multiple reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On the buy side&lt;/strong&gt;, options offer &lt;em&gt;leverage&lt;/em&gt;. We said option premiums are much
cheaper than stocks. To give you an idea, let&amp;#39;s consider ATM options on
Microsoft stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Such an option expiring in 20 days currently sells for ~3% of the stock price
(in reality, 300% of the stock price, since an option commands 100 shares, but
to make things convenient, option prices are usually denominated relative to a
single share). For an option expiring in 50 days, the price is ~4.5%. And for
January next year, it is ~13%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s quite a discount! Of course, it comes at a price. First - there is an
expiration. If the option expires worthless, you lose the premium, whereas you
can hold stock indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;msft-header.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;msft-28-01.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, your profit margin on the 100 shares commanded by the option is reduced
by the premium you paid. It is always more profitable to buy 100 shares than a
call, in absolute terms (absolute meaning &amp;quot;if you ignore the amount that you
need to invest&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s where leverage comes in: because options are much cheaper, you can buy
more of them compared to the stock - and so if you profit, the profit typically
ends up much higher for the same amount of money invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The sell side&lt;/strong&gt; is where, according to me, options really shine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While buying options (or shares) lets you make money by betting whether the
stock will go up or down, selling options lets you make money by betting that
the stock price will not fall below a certain price, or rise above a certain
price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me at least, that&amp;#39;s a much easier bet. Stock prices are swingy and hard to
predict, but I find it much easier to find conservative bounds for the price
movement (especially on the down side).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even better, this has the magical property of letting you profit &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; a stock
has run up in price. For instance, say a stock flies up from 10$ to 20$. You
think it won&amp;#39;t go back under 13$, and/or you wouldn&amp;#39;t mind owning it as that
price (as it is likely to go flying back up at some point in the future). Then
you can sell a put with a 13$ strike price expiring in a few feeks. The best
thing is, because of the recent price spike, there will be high demand
(&lt;em&gt;volatility&lt;/em&gt;) for the options and you&amp;#39;re likely to sell it a a higher price
compared to a similarly-priced, but stable stock. Of course, selling the put
when the stock was worth 10$ or 13$ would have been even more profitable, but
back then it was much more risky (as its upside was still uncertain).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, selling option lets you do all kind of fancy &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoptionsguide.com/option-trading-strategies.aspx&quot;&gt;options combo
strategies&lt;/a&gt;. I will list a few at the end of the article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-wheel&quot;&gt;The Wheel&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I&amp;#39;m dying to tell you more about option pricing. Because I&amp;#39;m
apparently a finance nerd now, and I find this super cool, but also because it
enables very interesting trading strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, that wasn&amp;#39;t quite the premise of this article, which was to describe a
fairly conservative strategy using options. I still think you should understand
option pricing if you&amp;#39;re going to use them, but you don&amp;#39;t need to understand all
the intricacies to understand the strategy. So here it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strategy is called &lt;strong&gt;the wheel&lt;/strong&gt;. It proceeds as follow:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You pick a series of stock you like. These stock should be stable (mostly:
very unlikely to go down a lot). They don&amp;#39;t need to be very volatile, but they
do need to be just volatile enough that the whole thing is worth your risk
(I&amp;#39;ll discuss numbers later). I wouldn&amp;#39;t recommend running this on market-wide
&lt;a href=&quot;/stock-market-intro/&quot;&gt;ETFs&lt;/a&gt; for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You sell cash-secured puts on the stocks you identified. A cash-secured put is
just a put where you own the cash to buy the shares should you get assigned.
You should pick a strike where you feel the stock is fairly- or under-valued.
The expiration should in ~30 days (after that, the price of options start
declining faster towards expiration, see section on option pricing).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You wait 30 days, and one of two things happen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stock is over the strike at expiration. You get to keep the premium.
You can re-start the process and again sell some puts on the stock (or on
another stock if you prefer).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The stock did go down, you get assigned, and you now own 100 shares of
the stock. The next phase of the strategy begins here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You now sell covered calls on the stock. A covered call is when you sell a
call where you own the underlying stock. This is very safe since, should you
get assigned, you can sell the stock you already own. The downside is that if
the stock skyrockets, you will lose the upside, since the call you sold forces
you to sell at the specified price. The game here is to select a strike that
is a bit above where you think the stock could reach. If you think the stock
could skyrocket, then just don&amp;#39;t sell the covered call - that&amp;#39;s fine (and
smart) too. Like before, pick a ~30 days expiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Like before, after 30 days, either the call expired worthless, and you can
sell another covered call — or you&amp;#39;ve been assigned. In that case you make a
double profit: the premium which is yours no matter what, plus the difference
between the price at which you bought the shares and the strike price. Your
capital is now freed to start another wheel cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, I should really give you an example trade. I&amp;#39;m lazy, so I will
simply redirect you to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IFYrFeAygfc&amp;amp;list=PLI2eVMd1wtdGwFXMFya1jHpWLvWw6a07X&quot;&gt;appropriate video&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLI2eVMd1wtdGwFXMFya1jHpWLvWw6a07X&quot;&gt;course&lt;/a&gt; I linked
earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s talk numbers. You should aim for the premium collect when selling the
options to be high enough. Jun Hao from the videos I linked before recommends a
minimum of 2%. That comes up to a 24% of profit a year, which is fairly
reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now in pratice, you&amp;#39;ll often achieve much better returns than 24%. That&amp;#39;s
because at some point your covered calls get assigned, you you get the pocket
the increase in the stock price. Even for a stock that isn&amp;#39;t too volatile, that
could be a ~10% increase (it is &lt;em&gt;possible&lt;/em&gt; for it be much more, if the stock
price increases consistently but never reaches the strike of the calls that
you&amp;#39;re selling month after month).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about the downside? Well the downside is the downside of the stock. You can
only lose money in this strategy if the stock loses value. That&amp;#39;s why picking
good stocks is important. There is a lot to be written about stock picking and
fundamental analysis, but that won&amp;#39;t be in this blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I&amp;#39;m not currently very inclined to write about valuation - I don&amp;#39;t feel
like I could tell you much more than a few good youtube channels. In fact here
are three recommendations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/GrowingWealth/playlists&quot;&gt;Growing Wealth&lt;/a&gt; - the source of the videos linked before. Solid
advice, nothing super exciting, but this is what I would recommend to most people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/AdamKhoo/playlists&quot;&gt;Adam Khoo&lt;/a&gt; - fairly basic and repetitive, but basic is what you want to
start at. He&amp;#39;s a fairly entertaining speaker, so maybe this could go down
better for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/c/AswathDamodaranonValuation/playlists&quot;&gt;Aswath Damodaran&lt;/a&gt; - a NY Stern professor no less, who shares his
valuation and corporate finance classes online. I intend to follow the 2021
class as it is being posted. From what I&amp;#39;ve seen so far, it&amp;#39;s top-notch, but
slightly technical. Maybe not for complete beginners, unless you&amp;#39;re quite
curious. Otherwise, follow some lighter content (podcasts etc) on the market first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back to the downside of the strategy. The downside is strictly less than owning
stock. Think about it: not only do you enter at an advantageous point (low
price), but you get paid a premium monthly before and after holding. Even in
case of loss, you will lose as much as the stock lost, minus all the premium you
collected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real price of the strategy is missing out on profits. If you really believe
in a stock, don&amp;#39;t wait until you puts are called, just buy out, or you could
miss out. Similarly, if a stock is really poised for growth, selling covered
call could amount to selling away most of your profits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I said, this strategy pays on stable stocks where you like the fundamentals
and/or the prospects, but where you also don&amp;#39;t that the stock is currently
selling at a bargain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;honestly-what-ive-been-doing&quot;&gt;Honestly, What I&amp;#39;ve Been Doing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the wheel strategy is sort of my base plan. However, in practice, I&amp;#39;ve
deviated from it significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In particular, I mostly sell puts, and I rarely get assigned. And second, I
mostly sell puts on relatively hyped stocks, and consequently collect more
premium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seems relatively contradictory, but in fact isn&amp;#39;t necessarily. Because the
stocks are popular, they have high volatility, meaning the premiums are higher.
Because of that, I can afford to pick a lower strike price (hence also a lower
premium) and still make a respectable profit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it must be said that the market right now is an euphoric bull market. I
would be foolish, I feel, to assume that this will last forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;stonks.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another difference from the wheel strategy is that my puts are not all
cash-secured (this is only possible if you trade &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/m/margin.asp&quot;&gt;on margin&lt;/a&gt;). Since my puts
mostly don&amp;#39;t get called, this is fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I must be wary of a particular risk: if the market &lt;em&gt;turns&lt;/em&gt; and goes
into a downtrend, I could potential be facing assignment on many/most of my
puts, which would &amp;quot;blow my account&amp;quot; (since this is more money than I have
because the puts are not cash-secured). I&amp;#39;m actively monitoring for such a
risk - it can be avoided by buying back the puts while there is still time
(which isn&amp;#39;t necessarily easy to do — trading psychology is fascinating and
would probably deserve a blog post, a book review, or both).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve also been relatively bummed by my experiences with selling cash-covered
calls. There were a few stocks I really liked, that I acquired by selling puts
very close to the money (I didn&amp;#39;t mind getting called since I liked the stock).
I wanted to follow the strategy and sold the puts, but ultimately I would have
done better to just let them ride - I was cut out of a major part of the gains
that the stocks made immediately after I was assigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another experience was a much more stable stock, where I felt like the amount of
premium collected didn&amp;#39;t justify the risk taken by the stock going down (and it
was going down).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, this is also due to the market being so hyper recently. If things
tend to go up, selling covered calls is probably not the best move. I expect
this leg of the strategy will make more sense in boring times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;option-pricing&quot;&gt;Option Pricing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think a key thing to be able to trade effectively with options is to
understand what influences the price of options (the premium).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s very important to understand that the price of the options, just like the
price of the underlying stock, is set by the market. i.e. the price is what
someone is willing to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, though this is not super important here, there are two components
to the price: the bid (what someone is willing to pay) and the ask (what
someone is willing to sell for). When the two component meet, an option is
sold. The different between the bid and the ask is called &amp;quot;the spread&amp;quot;. In a
liquid market with a lot of transaction volume, the spread is small. In an
illiquid market where not much is happening, the spread is wide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the price of options is influenced by four key factors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the price of the underlying stock (obviously)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the time remaining until expiration&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the risk-free rate&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the price of options can be modelled using these factors, plus a fourth
one (&lt;em&gt;volatility&lt;/em&gt;). The most popular model is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black%E2%80%93Scholes_model&quot;&gt;Black-Scholes model&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;volatility&quot;&gt;Volatility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volatility is the last factor that helps to fit the model to the market price.
You can think of volatility as &amp;quot;demand&amp;quot;: when volatility is high there is a lot
of trading activity, hence demand for options, meaning the premium rises.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volatility is typically correlated with sudden changes or swings in the
underlyings stock price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because volatility helps the model fit to reality, it is called &lt;em&gt;implied
volatility&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;strong&gt;IV&lt;/strong&gt; for short. External conditions influence the demand for
options, which is reflected in the price, and then we use the Black-Scholes
model to extract a quantified measure of &amp;quot;volatility&amp;quot; from the price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each stock has its own implied volatility. What qualifies as &amp;quot;high&amp;quot; IV varies
from stock to stock. Some stocks are inherently more stable than other.
Volatility can also be measured at the level of the market — this is notably
done through &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VIX&quot;&gt;the VIX index&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also theoretically possible to have a stock that has high IV without
exhibiting erratic price movements in the underlying stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implied volatility is expressed in percentage. This percentage represents the
predicted standard deviation range for the price of the underlying in the next
year. So a 100$ stock with an IV of 25% is expected to end within the 75-125$
price range after a year, with 68% probability (one standard deviation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does the implied volatility predicts the expected price? Essentially, the
higher market participants are willing to bid on an option, the higher the
expected price movement — traders are willing to pay more because they expect a
big move.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An open question (that I can&amp;#39;t answer): why is the range traditionally centered
on the current stock price? This is obviously wrong for many stocks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-risk-free-rate&quot;&gt;The Risk-Free Rate&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, before we dive in the really important stuff, let&amp;#39;s evacuate something
that is (currently) not very important: the risk-free rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The risk-free rate represents the rate of return of a risk-free investment. It&amp;#39;s
typically embodied by the yield of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.treasury.gov/resource-center/data-chart-center/interest-rates/pages/textview.aspx?data=yield&quot;&gt;US treasury bonds&lt;/a&gt; — which can&amp;#39;t default
unless the US government defaults, at which point we&amp;#39;d all have other worries
than the marginal return rates of our options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s mostly a non-factor because this rate is at the moment relatively stable,
and relatively low. The American federal reserved has vowed to keep this rate
low for at least the next two years. I&amp;#39;m a bit in over my head here, but from
what I understand, it is widely considered that letting the interest rate
increase would do bad things to do economy, and nobody seems particularly eager
to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; of the risk-free rate as a factor in option price is simple: when the
risk-free rate of return increase, you will demande increased returns for the
risk that you actually take — which in this case takes the form of decreased
premiums. It&amp;#39;s also interesting to note that since the option seller pockets the
premium up front (and not at expiration), an increased risk-free rate implies a
greater ability for him to compound the premium until expiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;option-greeks&quot;&gt;Option Greeks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most commonly used tool to analyze option prices are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greeks_(finance)&quot;&gt;option greeks&lt;/a&gt;.
The option greeks represent the variation of the option price relative to the
factor we listed before (so they are derivatives).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the first-order greeks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delta&lt;/strong&gt; (Δ): the most important one, how much does the price of the option increase
(or decrease) when the price of the underlying stock moves by 1$ (like most
numbers used with options, you actually need to multiply the quoted number by
100 to obtain the correct figure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theta&lt;/strong&gt; (Θ): represents how the price of the option drops as time passes. It
is expressed as a drop per year, but that number is actually meaningless,
because theta increases constantly (and predictably) until expiration (more
about this in a bit). To get a more useful figure, you should divide the
quoted number by 365 (or by 3.65, remember the 100 factor) to get a daily
drop. Note that options drop in value (all else being equal) even during the
weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vega&lt;/strong&gt; (𝑉): represents how the price of the option increases/decreases when
the implied volatility increases/decreases 1%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this may sound a bit weird, because we said earlier that IV is computed
from the option price and not the other way round. Indeed, getting the value
of vega is as simple as plugging the a reduced IV value in the Black-Scholes
model and getting out the new price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is nevertheless useful, because it helps us visualize how the option
price would move if demand for the option were to increase/decrease (which in
everyday talk will often be said as &amp;quot;if volatility were to increase&amp;quot;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting anecdote: vega is not a greek letter. It is typically represent by
a variant uppercase representation of the greek nu (ν) which doesn&amp;#39;t even have
a dedicated unicode character (I used the best approximation &amp;quot;mathematic
italic capital V&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rho&lt;/strong&gt; (ρ): the least used one, representing how much the price
increases/decreases if the risk-free rate increases/decreases by 1%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key considerations when dealing with greeks is that they all represent a rate
of change relative to a given variable (price, time, volatility, risk-free rate)
&lt;strong&gt;when all else stays equal&lt;/strong&gt;. Said otherwise, the value of every greek depends
on every variable. This is why not every option with 30 days until expiration
has the same theta - of course the option price for a 10$ stock isn&amp;#39;t going to
drop as much over time as the option price for a 1000$ stock! The same goes for
every other variable. Let us now go over some of these interesting correlations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start with delta. Delta is about 0.5 when the option is at the money. The
more the option gets in the money, the more delta increases, and the more it
gets out of the money, the more it decreases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;delta-vs-price.gif&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? If you own a 10$ call on a 1000$ stock, there is almost no option-specific
risk involved in holding the option, so every extra dollar in the underlying
price will translate to extra dollar in the option price.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, we can show that the price of an ITM call option must exceed
&lt;code&gt;stock_price - strike_price&lt;/code&gt;. It that weren&amp;#39;t the case, you could exercise the
option and immediately make a profit by selling the shares (in reality you would
need for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.optionstrading.org/introduction/how-options-really-work/settlement/&quot;&gt;settlement&lt;/a&gt; of the shares after exercising the option). A similar
logic applies for put option, where the intrinsic value is &lt;code&gt;strike_price - stock_price&lt;/code&gt; instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The price of options can be divided into two parts. First, the &lt;strong&gt;intrinsic
value&lt;/strong&gt;, which is the aforementiond &lt;code&gt;stock_price - strike_price&lt;/code&gt; factor (or
vice-versa for puts). This factor is capped at 0, however: ATM and OTM shares
have a 0 intrinsic value, not a negative one. Second, the &lt;strong&gt;time value&lt;/strong&gt; which
represents the potential for the option to appreciate and potentially get in the
money (or further in the money).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For call options, the intrinsic value is maximal at the 0 strike price, a point
where the time value is also minimal. For puts, it&amp;#39;s a bit more complicated, but
if far enough strikes are available (*), you will also find put options where the
option price is roughly equal to the intrinsic value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(*) The exchange decides how far the available strikes go, as well as the
increment between two available strike prices!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time value is maximal at the money, and decreases the further out in the
money or at the money the option goes. We said the time value represent the
potential for appreciation of the option. It does make sense that an option far
out of the money is unlikely to ever go into the money, while an option far in
the money will more or less move in lockstep with the underlying stock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s tackle this from another angle. Buying a deeply ITM option is like holding
stock: there is not much more risk than holding the stock. For this reason, the
time value is small — the price of the option will move in lockstep with the
underlying. But because the option is far in the money, the intrinsic value is
large, and the option is pricey compared to an ATM option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buying a deeply OTM option, on the other hand, is more like buying a lottery
ticket. It&amp;#39;s very likely it will expire worthless. Even if the underlying moves
in the right direction and you sell before expiration, the price increase will
be small because the further OTM an option is, the smaller delta is. This is
therefore mostly a bet on an explosive change in the underlying price. For such
a bet to make sense, the option price has to be very low. The intrinsic value is
zero, and the time value is low, since the bet is very unlikely to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhere in the middle, ATM options have 0 intrinsic value, but maximal time
value. That&amp;#39;s because they are the most &lt;em&gt;swingy&lt;/em&gt; of options. Since delta is also
maximal (0.5) at the money, the price of ATM options will respond the fastest to
changes in the price of the underlying. If your option is ATM a few days before
expiration, even a 3% price move is often the difference between a 100% loss and
100% profit at expiration. This potential for a quick profit is what makes the
time value high at the money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we should mention that, just like time value, theta (the time decay) is
greatest at the money. This is because an option has 0 time value at expiration,
so the time value must tend to zero over time. When there is more time value
(because the option is ATM), it therefore has to decrease faster over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;theta-vs-price.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Theta vs Price&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the chart above, the options are ATM and the underlying price is 6. Notice
how the curve flattens when the remaining time diminishes — because the time
value does too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we mentionned somewhere above, the time values decays increasingly fast as
expiration nears, and so does theta accelarate:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;theta-vs-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;price-vs-time.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Time Value vs Time&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the chart above &amp;quot;option value&amp;quot; should really be &amp;quot;time value&amp;quot;. The option
may still have intrinsic value at expiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In passing, note that delta also varies with time. At expiration, ITM options
(no matter how far) have a delta of 1 (intrinsic value == price), while OTM
options have a delta of 0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;delta-vs-time.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sources for the charts: &lt;a href=&quot;https://options-knowledge.com/the-greeks/&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://smart-options.blogspot.com/2007/11/option-delta.html&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.stockinvestor.com/36959/definition-greek-letter-theta-options-trading/&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And with this, I conclude my rather long exposition on options pricing. The
topic is even broader than this. For instance, we didn&amp;#39;t talk about the
second-order greek gamma (Γ) which played a major role in the recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GameStop_short_squeeze&quot;&gt;GameStop
rally&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope this article has been useful. See you next time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PS: Some Simple Option Strategies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoptionsguide.com/bull-put-spread.aspx&quot;&gt;Bull Put Spread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoptionsguide.com/bull-call-spread.aspx&quot;&gt;Bull Call Spread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoptionsguide.com/diagonal-bull-call-spread.aspx&quot;&gt;Diagonal Bull Call Spread&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoptionsguide.com/iron-condor.aspx&quot;&gt;Iron Condor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-02-18T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/options</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/options</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2021 Compiler Class Live</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;This year, I&amp;#39;m teaching a master-level compiler class at &lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/&quot;&gt;Université catholique
de Louvain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is now live &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLOech0kWpH8-njQpmSNGSiQBPUvl8v3IM&quot;&gt;on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve also created &lt;a href=&quot;/compilers&quot;&gt;a new page&lt;/a&gt; on this website intended to collect all
informations about the course.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-02-06T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/compiler-class-2021</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/compiler-class-2021</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chosen Tidbits 7</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-1/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-2/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-3/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-4/&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-5/&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-6/&quot;&gt;Six&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://habitatchronicles.com/2004/04/you-cant-tell-people-anything/&quot;&gt;You Can&amp;#39;t Tell People Anything&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s going on is that without some kind of direct experience to use as a
touchstone, people don’t have the context that gives them a place in their
minds to put the things you are telling them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The things you say often don&amp;#39;t stick, and the few things that do stick are often
distorted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, most people aren&amp;#39;t very good at visualizaing hypothetitcals, at imagining
what something they haven&amp;#39;t experienced might be like if it were somewhat
different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing might help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you create things that you can keep on the market at a very low cost
(including your time), you almost cannot fail. Worst case scenario is a slow
success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your running costs are high, time becomes your enemy. Your profits must
beat the clock, or you go bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your running costs are negligible, time becomes your friend. You cannot go
bust, and the passage of time exposes you to luck 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dvassallo/status/1278563747435446273&quot;&gt;Daniel Vassallo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1209794.html&quot;&gt;The Asshole Filter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself wondering, or just feeling, &amp;quot;Why is everyone I wind up
dealing with an asshole?&amp;quot; you might want to consider the possibility that you
have set up an asshole filter. Asshole filters are an extremely common
phenomenon, and an extremely common problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An asshole filter happens when you publicly promulgate a straitened contact
boundary and then don&amp;#39;t enforce it; or worse, reward the people who transgress
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example: promulgate that mails mails must go through team mail, but still answer
your private emails or even &lt;em&gt;expedite&lt;/em&gt; the requests your receive there, thereby
rewarding transgressors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://putanumonit.com/2020/07/04/kelly-bet-on-everything/&quot;&gt;Kelly Bet on Everything&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post because of my endless frustration with my friends who have
the most slack in life also being the most risk averse. They have plenty of
savings but stay in soul-sucking jobs for years. They complain about the
monotony of social life but refuse to instigate a change. They don’t travel,
don’t do drugs, don’t pick fights, don’t flirt, don’t express themselves. They
don’t want to think about kids because their lives are just so comfortable and
why would you mess with that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://devonzuegel.com/post/the-silence-is-deafening&quot;&gt;The Silence is Deafening&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Angry Alice tweets something obnoxious or unproductive, reasonable people
just scroll past it. If Alice develops a pattern of bad behavior, reasonable
people will just unfollow, mute, or block her. The result is that it&amp;#39;s hard for
Alice to notice the silent majority of people who saw the trash fire and walked
away when they recognized that engaging would only fuel its flames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets worse—Angry Alice only sees feedback from extremists, so she doesn&amp;#39;t
receive more nuanced signals that might actually cause her to reflect on her
behavior. If no reasonable people give feedback, only the unreasonable people
are left. From Alice&amp;#39;s perspective, the only people who disagree with her are
jerks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a coordination problem. Reasonable people understand that if they join
the fray alone, they&amp;#39;ll most likely be drowned out by the yelling, or worse
they&amp;#39;ll get dragged deeper into it. As a result, they choose stay out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge part of the problem is that digital spaces generally have no equivalent
of a disapproving glare. You&amp;#39;re stuck choosing between staying silent and
entering the fray, with few options in between. If you have little reason to
believe that other reasonable people will back you up, you&amp;#39;re going to stick
with the default: silence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://extranewsfeed.com/tolerance-is-not-a-moral-precept-1af7007d6376&quot;&gt;Tolerance is Not A Moral Precept&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tolerance is not a moral precept, it&amp;#39;s a peace treaty (or at least non-agression).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One can&amp;#39;t tolerate the intolerant, that would be a suicide pact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sonyasupposedly/status/1280903954872676352&quot;&gt;lisatomic5 on Children&amp;#39;s Rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thread illustrates that telling your children the functional lie that they
have bodily autonomy is exhausting to stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yashkaf/status/1281406459855634437&quot;&gt;Fuck Victimhood Identity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is that long ago I noticed that the less I saw and presented
myself as a victim, the less I was victimized. This kicked off a virtuous
cycle that I’m not going to jeopardize. Now my life is much improved, and I’ve
developed a very strong allergy to victim identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spiral of victim identity is incredibly seductive. Once you step in it
your identity will be reinforced by everyone around you and your own
confirmation bias. I’ve seen this spiral claim people, groups, nations. It
didn’t make them better off, and it didn’t make them better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victimhood blinds you to the suffering of others. My dating life improved when
I stopped thinking about how women malign me and became able to understand
their own fears and frustrations with guys. Before, I literally couldn’t
fathom that dating can be hard for hot young women&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victimhood blinds you to your own mistakes, the only part you can change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants their suffering validated, but you will never get this
validation from those who hurt you if that’s what you seek. If you let go of
this doomed desire, you may eventually find the validation you crave among
friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t have to argue about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; you’re fighting, &lt;em&gt;while&lt;/em&gt; you’re fighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to do both at once is a quick way to compound your frustration with each
other and make things worse for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smart thing to do is to schedule relationship maintenance in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1168145452379729921&quot;&gt;Visa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nabeelqu.co/understanding&quot;&gt;How to Understand Things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My father has zero intellectual insecurities... It has never crossed his mind
to be concerned that the world thinks he’s an idiot. He’s not in that game. So
if he doesn’t understand something, he just asks you. He doesn’t care if he
sounds foolish. He will ask the most obvious question without any sort of
concern about it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are not willing to do this — looking stupid takes courage, and
sometimes it’s easier to just let things slide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is striking how many situations I am in where I start asking basic
questions, feel guilty for slowing the group down, and it turns out that
nobody understood what was going on to begin with (often people message me
privately saying that they’re relieved I asked), but I was the only one who
actually spoke up and asked about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://garybasin.com/one-week-project-management/&quot;&gt;One Week Project Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a big project is tricky. I usually have some sense of what needs to
be done, but my time estimates tend to be… a little off. There’s one thing
worse than underestimating the time it’ll take: doing unnecessary work. I hate
getting traction on a project only to realize that a bunch of work was wasted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a trick that often works for me: Rescope the project to complete it
within the next week. Even when unrealistic, trying to apply that tight
constraint can get you to notice things you wouldn’t otherwise. It forces me
to consider what is absolutely necessary and what can be skipped. It forces me
to spend one of my days planning so I know exactly what I need to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Parkinson’s Law] states that a project takes as much time as you allow it.
Once in a while, try allowing much less time than you think is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My cynical view of humanity at large informs my sympathetic view of actual
humans. By the standards of horny status-obsessed murder monkeys, even my
outgroup enemies are often doing the best they can consider the fears and
insecurities that plague them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you believe that humans are by nature benign and kind and
are only &amp;quot;corrupted&amp;quot; by culture, you will have a very negative view of the
prevailing culture and most people. This will tempt you to dream of revolutions
or a return to some golden age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yashkaf/status/1284244774199988227&quot;&gt;Jacob&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-01-04T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-7</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-7</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stock Market Adventures: Introduction</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;In recent months, I&amp;#39;ve taken an interest in the stock market, and started
trading. Now that I&amp;#39;ve figured a few things about it, I want to share a bit of
information about how I trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before I get there, I want to give you the backstory of how I came to trade.
It involves many details that I find interesting &amp;amp; relevant, like index funds
and market cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;invest-in-etfs&quot;&gt;Invest in ETFs?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interest in the stock market started very pragmatic. I had some money set
aside, and it was gathering dust. My bank&amp;#39;s savings account nets me a 0.10%
interest, which is both a joke in poor taste, and a competitive market rate. I
needed better yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually already knew the answer: invest in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exchange-traded_fund&quot;&gt;ETFs&lt;/a&gt; (Exchange Traded Funds), in
particular funds tracking a broad market index (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Index_fund&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;index funds&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;). The target
index could be the ever-popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S%26P_500_Index&quot;&gt;S&amp;amp;P 500&lt;/a&gt; (indexing the 500 biggest US
companies), or if I wanted to be more diversified than just the US, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MSCI_World&quot;&gt;MSCI
World index&lt;/a&gt;, which tries to be representative of the world&amp;#39;s economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the boring-as-it-gets investment strategy. It&amp;#39;s quite safe too. Sure,
there are recessions. But the S&amp;amp;P 500 has grown historically at &amp;gt; 5% on average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How safe is it? Pretty safe, barring a zombie apocalypse or a nuclear holocaust.
All thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/compounding.asp&quot;&gt;compounding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled on an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pFgPNVytlwA&quot;&gt;what-if video&lt;/a&gt; the other day: &amp;quot;What if you
invested only at market peaks?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, even if you had invested a sum of 230k$ (2k$ annual payment, increased
by 2k$ every decade) &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; at the peak that preceded each recession for the
period starting in 1977, you&amp;#39;d still end up with 1M$ by retirement. It bears
repeating this is the absolute worst-case scenario. If instead, you&amp;#39;d just
invested every year, you&amp;#39;d end up with 2.5M$ instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a simple solution to my problem. But at the time, I had some
misgivings. First, the market was at an all-time high, and there was a lot of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://letstalklovetoday.wordpress.com/2017/04/01/the-definite-indefinite-optimist-and-pessimist/&quot;&gt;indefinite&lt;/a&gt; unease floating around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, since the Coronavirus crisis, more definite criticism has emerged.
Legendary investor Charlie Munger &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tO5kr0r9g58&quot;&gt;is afraid&lt;/a&gt; about record-like valuations and
inflation by means of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantitative_easing&quot;&gt;quantitative easing&lt;/a&gt;. Other people worry about many
companies (and in particular tech companies) being valued at historically high
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/earningsmultiplier.asp&quot;&gt;P/E multipliers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(By the way, I&amp;#39;ve written &lt;a href=&quot;/munger/&quot;&gt;about Charlie Munger&amp;#39;s philosophy&lt;/a&gt; before.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there was a possibility that market would take a hit for ~10 years. If you
look at the S&amp;amp;P 500 chart, this is what happened after 2000. The index only
recovered in 2008, then plunged again to only recover in 2012. 0% profit over 12
years is a long time with no returns, even if the market growth has since made
up for that slump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sp500.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you look at the slope of that graph in recent years, you can
understand why people are uneasy about us being at the peak of a bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there was, maybe, a way out: you could time the market. One option is wait
for the crash to get in. The only issue is that it might be in 1 years or in 10,
and your fear of losses could end up costing you more in lost profits. Another
strategy is to sell at the start of the crash and buy back at the bottom. But
that&amp;#39;s hard to distinguish a normal retracement from a temporary panic, and from
the start of a crash. Timing the bottom is similarly not so easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also common wisdom that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w_aOERmUWdA&quot;&gt;timing the market is typically a bad
idea&lt;/a&gt;. (Just like it is it &amp;quot;common wisdom&amp;quot; that trading is ruinous.
Yet some people do both consistently and successfully. We&amp;#39;ll get back to that later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, only one thing was clear: I had to learn more before I came out
with a plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-the-ball-rolling&quot;&gt;Getting the Ball Rolling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything I&amp;#39;ve laid out so far had mostly been background thinking, but I&amp;#39;d
been busy with other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally decided to give myself a shove and start doing something. An extra
motivation here was that a family member had made quite a bit of money investing
in Tesla options. Him and my brother were very bullish on the company and
claimed of a ton of upside. I found myself agreeing about that for the
short-term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so I decided to get my feet wet with brokers, and to buy a Tesla share (1.6k$
at the time) as well as investing very small amounts in ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to be said for getting the ball rolling like this. This was a
small enough amount of money that I could afford to lose it all (and obviously,
that was almost impossible anyway), but more than enough for me to care. I
started having questions and googling around for answers, and found quite a
treasure trove of information online, in particular on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some on these videos were on active investing, and some were on trading. I
started entertaining the notion that I could make some money in this way, and I
began running some small experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;penny-stocks&quot;&gt;Penny Stocks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started buying some stocks, for no more than 200€. Because that&amp;#39;s quite a low
amount, I was driven to buy &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penny_stock&quot;&gt;penny stocks&lt;/a&gt;. Those are also often volatile —
very risky, but potentially profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn&amp;#39;t go incredibly well, but that wasn&amp;#39;t particularly unexpected. If common
wisdom treats trading like gambling, penny stocks are treated like Russian
roulette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lost some money (not too much, less than I&amp;#39;d made on my Tesla trade and on a
couple other &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/bluechipstock.asp&quot;&gt;blue-chip stock&lt;/a&gt; trades). But I did learn a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I think&amp;#39;s it&amp;#39;s very hard to learn to trade penny stocks other than by
trading them. You can&amp;#39;t really learn anything by looking at past scenarios:
you&amp;#39;ll get a full dose of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindsight_bias&quot;&gt;hindsight bias&lt;/a&gt;. And penny stock trading is all about
timing entries (buying) and exits (selling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could potentially learn by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/papertrade.asp&quot;&gt;paper trading&lt;/a&gt;, but you need to be very
disciplined and not make any excuses like &amp;quot;I was busy with X so this trade
doesn&amp;#39;t count&amp;quot;. You&amp;#39;re still going to be busy with X when you trade your own
money — even if X is an emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s also a dearth of literature on the topic of penny trading. The topic is
not very conducive to theorization, but rather to some sort of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fingerspitzengef%C3%BChl&quot;&gt;fingerspitzgefühl&lt;/a&gt; intuition. Basically, you learn to be more paranoid, and
understand the (many) ways in which a penny stock trade can go south, or at
least no go how you predicted. You also learn to manage your emotions, and cut
your losses early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not facilitated by the fact that penny stock trading is extremely
speculative. To give you a very simple explanation, it&amp;#39;s often based around
&amp;quot;catalysts&amp;quot; that are expected to move the stock price. For instance: a drug
being approved for a pharma company. This causes the price to run up in
anticipation of the decision, and then to crash right before, or right after the
decision, as people sell to secure profits. Even if the drug was approved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s sometimes even worse than this — there are a number of stock market pundits
running &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pump_and_dump&quot;&gt;pump and dump&lt;/a&gt; schemes. It&amp;#39;s sometimes hard to tell apart from &amp;quot;regular
speculation&amp;quot;. When a pundit with many followers hypes a stock due for a
catalyst, you get a de facto, quite unintentional, pump-and-dump. A whole new way
to &amp;quot;monetize your audience&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t find trading penny stocks to be the most pleasant activities, but I
don&amp;#39;t begrudge it either. I think it&amp;#39;s quite possible to make a consistent
profit doing so — if one is willing to be careful and learn from mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;irrational-fears&quot;&gt;Irrational Fears&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to an important sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said before that the &amp;quot;common sense&amp;quot; opinion was that trading was ruinous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to be sure, I think that for most people, dissuading them from trading is
the correct position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s because most people are dumb. It&amp;#39;s not a nice thing to say, and it isn&amp;#39;t
to say they&amp;#39;re not also nice and valuable people. But it&amp;#39;s true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, trading tends to attract particularly dumb people. Just have a look at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/pennystocks/&quot;&gt;r/pennystocks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/wallstreetbets/&quot;&gt;r/wallstreetbets&lt;/a&gt;, and you&amp;#39;ll see off-the-charts stupidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trading requires you to plan, think things through, manage risk/exposure, and,
most of all, manage your own emotions. It&amp;#39;s hard. Too hard for people that
haven&amp;#39;t developed these skills and virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flip side is that if you are able to do all that, trading can be a viable
avenue to generating extra money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody that says that &amp;quot;trading is ruinous&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;trading is too risky&amp;quot; should
feel the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_dissonance&quot;&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/a&gt; with the fact that they are quite a lot of people
who make a consistent profit or even a living trading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, there should be nuance. &amp;quot;Trading is too risky for most people&amp;quot;. I
agree with that. This leads to an interesting question: what sets the successful
traders apart from the rest of us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led to me to this interesting thought: Imagine someone that has praised you
for being smart and level-headed. But when you tell them you&amp;#39;re going to trade;
they try to dissuade you out of it. Either they&amp;#39;re thoroughly confused in the
sense outlined above, or their real opinion of you is that you&amp;#39;re not, in fact,
smart and level-headed enough to take on this endeavour. (Fortunately this
remains a hypothetical scenario for me. Nobody has thrown shade on my trading so
far).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;finally-options&quot;&gt;Finally, Options&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trading penny stocks could have been profitable, but it wasn&amp;#39;t my favourite
thing. For one, the activity has inherent uncertainty. I once saw a stock trader
that made hundreds of thousands of dollars in profit a year run the numbers on
his trading, and his trade win rate was &amp;quot;only&amp;quot; 68%. The average profit was only
~20% higher than the average loss. Considering that these wins and losses are
not distributed uniformly, it does take some mental fortitude to ride through
the highs and lows. I&amp;#39;m really risk-averse, and even though I think I can muster
the mental fortitude, I&amp;#39;d rather not deal with the stress if I don&amp;#39;t have to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I found a method much better suited to my taste. And it involves
dealing in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/stockoption.asp&quot;&gt;stock options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Options are incredibly more flexible than stock, which you can merely buy and
sell. Options enable very safe plays (though with lower payout), but also
getting more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/l/leverage.asp&quot;&gt;leverage&lt;/a&gt; when you want to make aggressive moves. They can also be
used to manage/lower your losses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This increased flexibility also makes options much more interesting — and
frankly more fun to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In future articles, I will explain various kinds of trades I undertake using
options. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-12-26T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/stock-market-intro</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/stock-market-intro</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviews 9</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/every-anime/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/more-anime/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-6&quot;&gt;Six&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-7&quot;&gt;Seven&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8&quot;&gt;Eight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solo-leveling&quot;&gt;Solo Leveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volume 1+, up to chapter 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;solo-leveling.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another webtoon, somewhat similar &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#skeleton-soldier-couldnt-defend-the-dungeon-up-to-chapter-109&quot;&gt;Skeleton Soldier&lt;/a&gt;, albeit more popular (given
it&amp;#39;s the only webtoon anyone&amp;#39;s ever told me about besides the even more popular
&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#tower-of-god-webtoon---up-to-episode-485&quot;&gt;Tower of God&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this universe there are &amp;quot;gates&amp;quot; that appear regularly, which lead to dungeons
full of monsters. These dungeons must be cleared under a certain number of days,
lest the monsters pour out in the real world. However, at the same time these
gates appeared, some people started developing powers, basically turning them
into RPG characters with superior physical abilities and/or magical powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main character is not very strong, but through the vicissitudes of
&lt;del&gt;narrative facility&lt;/del&gt; fate, he gets to power up pretty quickly (I&amp;#39;m sure you were
able to guess that from the title).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is a massive power trip, but somehow it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, I don&amp;#39;t really know why, but I&amp;#39;m a bit of a fan of the aesthetics and
the genre (just like Isekai). I guess I wasted too much time grinding in
World of Warcraft and now my brain is permanently damaged. Expect to see many
more review of &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; similar anime (as it turns out, there are a ton).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know whether to recommend it, I obviously enjoyed it very much, but at
the same time I have no specific glowing praise for it. It&amp;#39;s not clever in any
particularly unique way. Give it a few chapters and drop it if it doesn&amp;#39;t speak
to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat more interestingly, I think this webtoon doesn&amp;#39;t compare super
favorably to &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#skeleton-soldier-couldnt-defend-the-dungeon-up-to-chapter-109&quot;&gt;Skeleton Soldier&lt;/a&gt;. The fact that the main character can die
(albeit temporarily) in Skeleton Soldier does tend to make the stakes higher.
The story is also more involved, with characters coming in and out of the story.
In general, I&amp;#39;m also intrigued in Skeleton&amp;#39;s universe. The mystery in Solo
Leveling is rather singular for my taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;jujutsu-kaisen&quot;&gt;Jujutsu Kaisen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched 5 episodes of this, but it just didn&amp;#39;t click for me. It&amp;#39;s a very
generic shonen that punches under its weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being generic is not a death sentence. Nobody will accuse [My Hero Academia] of
being incredibly original, yet it&amp;#39;s the best thing since sliced bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jujutsu Kaisen completely failed to pull me into its universe. I found the
moments of tension completely unbelievable. For instance, at some point early in
the series, the main character loses a hand, and I didn&amp;#39;t believe it for even a
second. A bit later in the same episode, something even more egregious happens,
and same thing, didn&amp;#39;t believe it one bit. It&amp;#39;s not like there are amazing
fights, or really interesting character designs / personalities either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the contrast with Hero Academia is stark: some of the key fights in the
anime so far really got me invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did like the ending theme however, it&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6riDJMI-Y8U&quot;&gt;quite funky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;zenkyou-no-terror-terror-in-resonance&quot;&gt;Zenkyou no Terror (Terror in Resonance)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;zenkyou-no-terror.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been on my list for quite a while, and I&amp;#39;m happy I finally got around
to watching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story follows two teenagers committing various acts of terrorism in Tokyo.
The big question: what&amp;#39;s their purpose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it works on two plans. First, it&amp;#39;s a &amp;quot;planned crime&amp;quot; show. Early Death
Note comes to mind (sorry, I&amp;#39;m lacking better references here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second there is the mystery of purpose. You can kind of infer it as the story
unfolds, but I still found it very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d classify alongside &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4/#parasyte&quot;&gt;Parasyte&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-7/#erased-boku-dake-ga-inai-machi&quot;&gt;Erased&lt;/a&gt; in the list of seinens that are
worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show is short (only 11 episodes). This is good, as no time is wasted. But on
the other hand, some aspects feel neglected. In particular the character of Lisa
Mishima, a girl that finds herself entangled with the terrorists, lacks in
depth. I understand why she&amp;#39;s in the story, but it feels like a bit more
attention could have made her into more than simply a plot device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-returners-magic-should-be-special&quot;&gt;A Returner&amp;#39;s Magic Should Be Special&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1-2, up to chapter 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here we are again, with a webtoon that has an RPG-like setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setting is surprisingly similar to &lt;a href=&quot;#solo-leveling&quot;&gt;Solo Leveling&lt;/a&gt;: dungeons appear in the
world. If they are not cleared, they absorb the surrounding land in some kind of
void. Clearing the dungeons is not just about killing monsters, but also
fulfilling various quests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, the main character is part of an elite group that defeated the final
boss of the worst dungeon to ever appear - only to be killed by the blowback.
Consequently, he wakes up a student in an academy for dungeon-fighters, 10 years
before the appearance of the disastrous dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the quests inside the dungeons, the RPG element is toned out here: there
is no XP and attributes here, only good old training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s also a political dimension as the hero tries to fix what&amp;#39;s wrong with
the continent (namely literal class warfare) to unite people against the coming
threat. Enjoyable, but a bit too much on the nose for my taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like before: I&amp;#39;m susceptible to this genre, and I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;barakamon&quot;&gt;Barakamon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;barakamon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another anime recommended by my girlfriend Sasha, and another very pleasant
surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is about a professional calligrapher in lack of inspiration and
professional turmoil. His father ships him out a tiny island to shore up his
inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There he befriends the local townspeople and in particularly the kids. He falls
for the pastoral charm of the country life and learns from the folksy wisdom of
the people. etc. etc. The pitch is not very original — but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the cute story, the show is pretty hilarious. It&amp;#39;s honestly one
of the funniest showsI&amp;#39;ve seen so far. Probably in my top 2, up there with
&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#kaguya-sama-love-is-war-season-2&quot;&gt;Love is War&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also a short one (12 episodes), so don&amp;#39;t hold back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;gateless&quot;&gt;Gateless&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Sebastian Marshall &amp;amp; Kai Zau&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Marshall is a &amp;quot;productivity expert&amp;quot;. That sounds pretty corny, but I
don&amp;#39;t know how else to describe him. It might be better to say he&amp;#39;s someone
obsessed with peak performance, who built a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ultraworking.com/&quot;&gt;whole business&lt;/a&gt; around that
obsession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&amp;#39;s also one I respect immensely, despite not always agreeing with him. That
doesn&amp;#39;t preclude me from mining for useful insights, of which there are many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been following Sebastian for a while, in particular &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestrategicreview.net/&quot;&gt;The Strategic Review&lt;/a&gt;
(I&amp;#39;ve posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/celerity/&quot;&gt;a summary of one of the series&lt;/a&gt; back in 2017), his
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ultraworking.com/podcast&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sebastianmarshall.com/&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also not the first book by Sebastian I&amp;#39;m reading. Besides &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23642948-gateless&quot;&gt;Gateless&lt;/a&gt; - I&amp;#39;ve
previously read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/25535056-roguelike&quot;&gt;Roguelike&lt;/a&gt; which extracts lessons and analogies from classical
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roguelike&quot;&gt;roguelikes&lt;/a&gt; with application towards real-life endeavours. (I guess you&amp;#39;d see
how that would talk to me!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Gateless was co-authored by Sebastian&amp;#39;s co-founder and friend Kai Zau.
Unfortunately, I have much fewer interesting things to tell you about Kai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, about this book himself. Well, I didn&amp;#39;t learn much. But that&amp;#39;s also because
I&amp;#39;m well acquainted with Sebastian&amp;#39;s idea, as I think I&amp;#39;ve established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is basically a manual in how to improve in your endeavours. It&amp;#39;s
probably most directly useful if that endeavour is something that resembles &amp;quot;a
career&amp;quot;, but it is general enough to be useful in other areas too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is short enough, but I worry that if you&amp;#39;re at the level where most of
these basics are news to you, then it might actually be a bit much to take in.
It&amp;#39;s also not the funniest read, and it&amp;#39;s notably less fun to read than most of
the Marshall stuff I&amp;#39;ve read before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, recommended if you&amp;#39;re a dutiful person looking to fill the gaps in your
strategy. But I&amp;#39;d advise to start with the Marshall productions linked in this
summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I find myself concurring with this (4/5 stars!)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1377037687&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; from GoodReads, which will also give you a bit more
details about the book itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of blog-like essays on thinking about and developing personal
(&amp;quot;Capacity&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Meaning&amp;quot; sections), social (&amp;quot;Signal&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Network&amp;quot;) and
financial capital (&amp;quot;Assets&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing terribly new here and large chunks of the book are verbatim
quotes taken from other sources. Meaning and Assets sections are largely
cursory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, I quite enjoyed it - though nothing particularly new, their
particular formulation of the ideas resonated with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, recommendable - especially for fresh graduates just entering the
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tactical-barbell&quot;&gt;Tactical Barbell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now for something completely different, a book about weightlifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must say this one disappointed me. First, because I heard the Tactical Barbell
approach integrated conditioning (i.e. cardio &amp;amp; high intensity endurance work),
but it turns out that part is outlined in the second book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, because the book says very little about lifting, and does so in too many
words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core approach is to train only big compound lifts (squat, bench press,
deadlift, pullups, ...) at submaximal intensities (i.e. maybe a &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-5/#reactive-training-systems-rts&quot;&gt;7-8 RPE&lt;/a&gt;)
with plenty of rest (up to 5 minutes) between sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s pretty boring, though I have no doubts that it works, at least up to a
certain point (but far enough for most people, including me currently).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important point is that the book is targeted to an &amp;quot;operational&amp;quot; audience:
police, army, SWAT, firefighters, ... (hence the &amp;quot;tactical&amp;quot; in the title). A big
point is that these people may already have some fairly intense physical
workloads (in the course of work, or because of work-mandated training), so the
strength work should be as efficient as possible and not leave them too tired to
perform well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, the book goes so much out of its way to evoke out this
&amp;quot;operational&amp;quot; image that it had me wonder if it wasn&amp;#39;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; marketed at
people who have a tactical fetish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few parts of the book also inspire distrust. The author claims to have reached
4% body fat at some point, for instance. The section on supplements is as best a
N=1 field report, and contains no actual scientific facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll see if book 2 is better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tactical-barbell-2-conditioning&quot;&gt;Tactical Barbell 2: Conditioning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked the second book much better. One reason is that it actually contained
things I wasn&amp;#39;t really much informed about. It also contains an actionable plan
(a program, really). It&amp;#39;s easy to find good quality strength programs online
(e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://stronglifts.com/5x5/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://builtwithscience.com/best-full-body-workout/&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;), but I haven&amp;#39;t stumbled on a program aiming to
develop and maintain conditioning before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is also better organized, with the principles outlined in the first
part (+ still quite a bit of fluff) and the extensive exercise plan in the
second part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, reviewing the book is not that useful — I ought to try this and
review the program. I&amp;#39;m thinking I might do the &amp;quot;base-building&amp;quot; 8-week block
after I redo a strength block when the gym re-opens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-dusk-till-dawn&quot;&gt;From Dusk Till Dawn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;from-dusk-till-dawn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the last &amp;quot;Tarantino movie&amp;quot; that I hadn&amp;#39;t seen. It isn&amp;#39;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; a
Tarantino movie, as Tarantino only wrote the script (and plays a major acting
role in the movie), but the movie was directed by Robert Rodriguez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flick is fast-paced and pretty fun. At first glance, it looks like it&amp;#39;s
going to be classical rough-n-dirty Tarantino flick, but the genre of this movie
is actually action horror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so things take a turn for the weird at some point. And it&amp;#39;s great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a bit hard to say if it&amp;#39;s a B-movie or an homage to B-movies. It&amp;#39;s
certainly a bit of parody, albeit of nothing in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good time that happens to involve a lot of gore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;gone-girl&quot;&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This movie is tricky to describe. Wikipedia says it&amp;#39;s a &amp;quot;psychological thriller&amp;quot;
and I think that does fit the bill. To me, it&amp;#39;s one of those &amp;quot;guess movies&amp;quot;,
where I can&amp;#39;t prevent myself from annoying the hell of whoever I&amp;#39;m watching it
with (in this case, Sasha) by interjecting all my hypothesis about what the hell
could be going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, the pitch: writer Nick Dunne finds his wife missing and contacts the
police. A search is organized, and troublesome truths about the relationship
come to light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does sound a bit dull, but there is a mystery, and the twist and turns are
quite satisfying. This movie will have you wondering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s only really one thing I disliked about it: the very ending. Not that I
objected to it, I just thought it was poorly justified and didn&amp;#39;t make a lot of
sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In making this review, I realized that (a) this is a David Fincher, and (b) I&amp;#39;ve
actually consumed most of Fincher&amp;#39;s cinematographic output: Seven, The Game,
Fight Club, Benjamin Button, The Social Network, The Girl With The Dragon
Tattoo, Zodiac, and now Gone Girl - as well as House of Cards. Most of those are
pretty good. If you haven&amp;#39;t seen them, I&amp;#39;d particularly recommend Gone Girl, The
Game, Fight Club, and the first season of House of Cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;zero-to-one&quot;&gt;Zero to One&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book outlines Peter Thiel&amp;#39;s (a founder of PayPal and Palantir) business
philosophy - especially regarding startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#39;s well worth reading for anyone interested in eventually starting a
business (especially an ambitious one), or just interesting in business in
general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you an idea, here&amp;#39;s my very short summary of a few ideas I took away
from the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Startups should aim to become monopolies — because a monopoly is not
constantly under threat and thus has the space to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the ways to establish a monopoly is networks effects. And paradoxically,
network effect monopolies must get started with a small market — one that the
startup can completely corner. For instance, Facebook started serving only
Harvard students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A startup&amp;#39;s most important asset is new thinking. A startup needs &amp;quot;a secret&amp;quot; —
something it believes to be true, while the consensus (not just the majority)
thinks that it is false. What valuable company is no one else building?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sales &amp;amp; distribution matter more than they&amp;#39;re made out to in the startup
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sales is always hidden. &amp;quot;Salesman&amp;quot; is nobody&amp;#39;s title, instead it might be
&amp;quot;customer happiness office&amp;quot; for a very transparent example. You don&amp;#39;t know
any sales grandmaster - because you don&amp;#39;t think of them as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computers will not replace humans - the future is complementarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solo-bug-leveling&quot;&gt;Solo Bug Leveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1, up to chapter 40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veteran MMO player dies, gets reincarnated in the game. Can&amp;#39;t be more classic
than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here though, the hero gets reincarnated as an (adult) lord of some small
province. Armed with his encyclopedic knowledge of the game (and, as the title
implies, of its bugs), he sets out to make right everything that is wrong, and
to prepare adequately for future turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not sure I have too much to say about this one. The setting and the
execution are both solid. An enjoyable read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;slave-b&quot;&gt;Slave B&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1, up to chapter 50&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;slave-b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this one departs &lt;em&gt;a little bit&lt;/em&gt; from the leveling webtoons I&amp;#39;ve been reading,
but it&amp;#39;s not too far away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s the story of slave kid who, after some mishap, finds the opportunity to
attend a prestigious caster/fighter military academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus is not too much on leveling or skill acquisition (although there is a
bit of that), but more on inter-personal relationships and in particular the
ostracism towards the slaves. In that it&amp;#39;s a bit similar to &lt;a href=&quot;#a-returner-s-magic-should-be-special-webtoon&quot;&gt;Returner&lt;/a&gt; and its
commoner/noble distinction — except way worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is also different in that it&amp;#39;s not a clean nice power trip drive. The
hero does experience quite a few setbacks, and a lot of suffering. The story is
also interested in dealing with the resulting anger (instead of featuring a
noble hero that would brush it off instantly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d say this story has more ambition than what I&amp;#39;d read so far. Or if not that,
at least it takes more risk by dealing with emotions and more complex
relationship dynamics. It&amp;#39;s not quite as masterful as some of these others (like
Skeleton or Solo Leveling), perhaps precisely because of these dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all in all, quite interesting, and might appeal to a more mainstream
audience that doesn&amp;#39;t have some kind of leveling fetish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-beginning-after-the-end&quot;&gt;The Beginning After The End&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1-3, up to chapter 85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another webtoon in the same vein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this one, our hero is nothing less than a conqueror king, reincarnated. His
original lifetime seemingly had magic but also a futuristic setting, while his
reincarnated life happens in a more medieval type of settings, complete with
elves and dwarves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt like this webtoon did itself a service by taking some breathing room.
Over 85 chapters, the plot advances much less than some other webtoons in the
same genre. Amusingly, we see the reincarnated hero age from 0 to 13 years old -
and he is just now about to join some kind of magic school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This space is mostly potentiality - it means the webtoon does not commit faults
by rushing the plot and the relationships between the characters, but it also
means that the number of plot points has been limited so far. If done correctly
though, the greater familiarity we have acquired with the characters will lead
to a much more satisfying punch down the line, and the character development
will feel meaningful. We can only hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s not to say that nothing happened, and it&amp;#39;s been a very enjoyable read so
far, it&amp;#39;s not exactly a tapestry of intrigue, but I have nothing critical to say
about it either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;a href=&quot;#slave-b-webtoon-up-to-chapter-50&quot;&gt;Slave B&lt;/a&gt;, this one is also much less leveling oriented (though the
theme is present as skill acquisition and mana mastery).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I got a very &lt;em&gt;cozy&lt;/em&gt; vibe from this toon. The hero&amp;#39;s original (and
still mysterious) life was lonely, as an orphan that somehow made it to the top.
The webtoon emphasizes, on the other hand, how precious his family and friends
are to him in his new life. And you know what, I&amp;#39;m all for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, very recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mandalorian-season-2&quot;&gt;The Mandalorian Season 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5/#the-mandalorian&quot;&gt;Season 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second season does not disappoint — it&amp;#39;s still great. It does tell us more
about the character of the show, however. Sasha sent me this comic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;mandalorian.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it is - it&amp;#39;s an episodic show. The second season doesn&amp;#39;t launch in grand
intrigues any more than the first one does. With only 8 episodes and a flair for
showing great action sequences, maybe that&amp;#39;s preferable (the counterexample
here would be John Wick - great first movie, terrible franchise).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did get a bit frustrated by the 6th episode, however. There were too many
frustrations of the type where I go like &amp;quot;why didn&amp;#39;t you do this? you literally
did it 5 minutes ago! but now it&amp;#39;s useful!&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;of course that&amp;#39;s precisely the
moment where X would happen!!&amp;quot;. Probably this is actually a weakness of the show
and this happens more than I realize — I&amp;#39;m typically an easy audience. But in
that episode, it was really hard to overlook. Fortunately, the show made up for
it with an excellent 7th episode and an adequate, if
not-quite-as-good-as-first-season&amp;#39;s, finale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney is apparently very intent on milking the Star Wars cow, and in particular
the Mandalorian cow (probably especially so after they drove the main series
into the ground). Next year we can expect, in addition to season 3, a show on
Bobba Fett. But there&amp;#39;s more! Disney is working on two more Mandalorian spinoffs,
one on Jedi &lt;a href=&quot;https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Ahsoka_Tano&quot;&gt;Ahsoka Tano&lt;/a&gt; (from the animated movies and appearing in this season
of Mando), one on the New Republic Rangers. And there&amp;#39;s also one on Lando
Calrissian. I expect a mixed bag, but let&amp;#39;s hope for one or two gems in there.
This is the way.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-12-24T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/reviews-9</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/reviews-9</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
