<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>norswap</title>
    <description></description>      
    <link>http://norswap.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://norswap.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Looking for Work</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m slated to finish my PhD thesis by September (give or take) and I&amp;#39;ve started
to look for work opportunities after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have made contact with some interesting companies/institutions, but since
I have a few months left before I need to make up my mind, I thought I would
sollicit further offers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you have something that might interest me, send information my way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m interested in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;research or R&amp;amp;D-type work, especially on programming languages&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;senior technical positions, preferably including some management
responsibilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;computer science teaching positions in higher eduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have uploaded my resume &lt;a href=&quot;/resume&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;/resume.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;Be also sure to check my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/&quot;&gt;Github account&lt;/a&gt; and my &lt;a href=&quot;/publications&quot;&gt;publications&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2018-03-12T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/looking-for-work</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/looking-for-work</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Command Line Searching</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;I do keep a fair amount of information inside text files - this is how I
organize myself, keep track of what I&amp;#39;ve read, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, I need to search these files by content to retrieve some
information, or remind myself of something I read earlier. Hence the need for
software that does just that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I had settled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mythicsoft.com/agentransack/&quot;&gt;Agent Ransack&lt;/a&gt; on Windows and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houdah.com/tembo/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Tembo&lt;/a&gt; on OS X.
However, I was looking for something a bit more snappy, hence the idea of using
a command line tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I expect the reader will be familiar with the venerable &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/grep/&quot;&gt;grep&lt;/a&gt;, but it turns out
there are a whole lot more tools that can be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most useful resource I found online was &lt;a href=&quot;https://beyondgrep.com/feature-comparison/&quot;&gt;this comparison&lt;/a&gt; of tools, which
compares (at the time of writing), &lt;a href=&quot;https://beyondgrep.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ack&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://geoff.greer.fm/ag/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;ag&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://git-scm.com/docs/git-grep&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git-grep&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gnu.org/software/grep/&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;GNU
grep&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;rg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a glance, I was really tempted to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep&quot;&gt;ripgrep (&lt;code&gt;rg&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, which seems
to be the fastest of the bunch, has well-rounded features and nice
documentations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it lacked a vital feature for me: multi-line matching. I store a lot of
text formatted to hard-line-wrap at 80 characters, and I want to be able to
search for word groups accros line boundaries. So ultimately I settled on &lt;a href=&quot;https://geoff.greer.fm/ag/&quot;&gt;the
silver searcher (&lt;code&gt;ag&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, which is great as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;effective-selecting&quot;&gt;Effective Selecting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I also wanted to try &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/garybernhardt/selecta&quot;&gt;selecta&lt;/a&gt;, a command line tool by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.destroyallsoftware.com/screencasts&quot;&gt;Gary
Bernhardt&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What it does is read lines from the input stream and allow you to scroll these
lines on the command line, ultimately selecting one. If this description is
unclear, check the animated gif on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/garybernhardt/selecta&quot;&gt;github page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately selecta is Unix-only, however there are a few clones and I ended
up settling on the multi-platform &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rschmitt/heatseeker&quot;&gt;heatseeker&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s an example of what I can do with &lt;code&gt;ag&lt;/code&gt; and heatseeker (&lt;code&gt;hs&lt;/code&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;em $(ag -l parser | hs)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Or the Windows equivalent (assuming you have &lt;code&gt;xargs&lt;/code&gt; installed, it comes with
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cygwin.com/&quot;&gt;Cygwin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mingw.org/&quot;&gt;MinGW&lt;/a&gt; and even Git):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ag -l parser | hs | xargs em
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;#39;m doing is that I&amp;#39;m searching for the string &amp;quot;parser&amp;quot; in the current
directory. The &lt;code&gt;-l&lt;/code&gt; flag says to only print the file name (not the line number)
of matches. Then heatseeker is used for the selection, and once the selection is
done, the file opens in Emacs (&lt;code&gt;em&lt;/code&gt; is my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/.emacs.d&quot;&gt;custom Emacs launching
script&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this could be encapsulated in a batch script or bash function in
order to be even more convenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;filename-search&quot;&gt;Filename Search&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just to be clear, the article is about searching inside text files. However, I
also often want to search files by name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this, I use GUI programs. On Windows, the best is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.voidtools.com/&quot;&gt;Everything&lt;/a&gt;. I have
this handy program hotkeyed to &lt;code&gt;Win+S&lt;/code&gt; and I use it all the time to quickly
navigate to a file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OS X has unfortunately nothing as good as that. The main problem is that most
search programs seems to rely on the Spotlight engine, which is flaky in a
couple of places. Most aggravating for me, Spotlight will not search inside
dot-directories (e.g. &lt;code&gt;.config&lt;/code&gt;). It&amp;#39;s also not possible to formulate queries as
easily as in Everything. I think partial path matching is not possible for
instance. The search program that don&amp;#39;t use the Spotlight engine are somehow
even worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the absence of a real solution, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.houdah.com/tembo/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Tembo&lt;/a&gt; is also able to search on file names
on OS X. It&amp;#39;s not a patch on Everything, but it&amp;#39;s better than nothing
(accidental pun!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the rare cases where I want to search on the command line, I can either use
the venerable &lt;a href=&quot;http://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man1/find.1.html&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;find&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; or the use &lt;code&gt;-g&lt;/code&gt; flag of &lt;code&gt;ag&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;android&quot;&gt;Android&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also have a bunch of text files synced on my phone, and on the rare occassion
I need to make a search on the go, I use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=jp.sblo.pandora.aGrep&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;rdid=jp.sblo.pandora.aGrep&quot;&gt;aGrep&lt;/a&gt; application. I have also
tried &lt;a href=&quot;https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.docsearch&amp;amp;hl=en&quot;&gt;DocSearch&lt;/a&gt;, but the user experience was less pleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2018-02-26T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/cmd-search</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/cmd-search</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple Math: Permutations and Combinations</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;#39;s post, I want to (re-)introduce some simple math that most people
learn in high school, but forget quicly: permutations and combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Permutations and combinations allow you to answer questions like: In how many
ways can I order a set of distinct items? If I take K of those items, how many
combinations of them are there? Then we will go a bit further and see how to
deal with repetition (putting back an item after selecting it), multisets (sets
in which there are multiple copies of the same item, like a pit that would hold
4 red balls, 3 blue balls and 2 green balls) and picking from different sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sets-of-distinct-items&quot;&gt;Sets of Distinct Items&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine you have a set of distinct items. This could be a deck of cards, or a
pit containing uniquely numbered balls. We will look at the number of ways to
pick items out of this set, with and without taking ordering into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One basic rule: Once an item has been picked from the set, it can&amp;#39;t be picked
again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will look at three questions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Permutations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many ways are there to order all items in the set?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, for a set of three balls {1, 2, 3}, there are six way to order
them: 123, 132, 213, 231, 312, 321.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;k-Permutations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many ways are there to order &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items picked from a set?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, for a set of three balls {1, 2, 3}, there are 6 ways to order
two of them: 12, 13, 21, 23, 31, 32.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(k-)Combinations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many ways are there to pick &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items picked from a set?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, for a set of three balls {1, 2, 3}, there are 3 ways to pick two
of them: {1, 2}, {1, 3} and {2, 3}.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s now give the formula and intuition for how to answer these questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;permutations&quot;&gt;Permutations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;code&gt;n!&lt;/code&gt; ways to order the elements of a set of size &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;n!&lt;/code&gt; means the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Factorial&quot;&gt;factorial&lt;/a&gt; of n. The factorial of 3 is &lt;code&gt;3 * 2 * 1 = 6&lt;/code&gt;. The
factorial of 5 is &lt;code&gt;5 * 4 * 3 * 2 * 1 = 120&lt;/code&gt;, etc. The factorial of 0 is 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuition:&lt;/strong&gt; Imagine we have to order 3 balls {1, 2, 3}. First we pick one ball
and we have three to choose from, so that&amp;#39;s three possibilities. Next we pick
another ball, and there are only two left to choose from. This means that for
each choice we made when picking the first ball, there are two further
possibilities for the second ball, so that&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;3 * 2 = 6&lt;/code&gt; possibilities. Finally
there is only one ball left to pick: we have no choice. This means there are &lt;code&gt;3!
= 3 * 2 * 1 = 6&lt;/code&gt; ways to order the three balls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;k-permutations&quot;&gt;k-Permutations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The are &lt;code&gt;P(n, k) = n! / (n-k)!&lt;/code&gt; ways to order &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items picked from a set of
size &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;. For other mathematical notations, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permutation#k-permutations_of_n&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuition:&lt;/strong&gt; We start by considering all &lt;code&gt;n!&lt;/code&gt; permutations of the set. But we
are only interested in the &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; first items of these permutations. Amongst all
permutations, there are multiple that start with the same &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items. How many of
these are there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the permutations that have the same first &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items must have a different
permutations of their &lt;em&gt;n-k&lt;/em&gt; last items. With the formula for permutations, we
know there are &lt;code&gt;(n-k)!&lt;/code&gt; ways to form permutations of a set of &lt;em&gt;n-k&lt;/em&gt; items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So by dividing the total number of permutations (&lt;code&gt;n!&lt;/code&gt;) by the number of
permutations of the last &lt;em&gt;n-k&lt;/em&gt; items (&lt;code&gt;(n-k)!&lt;/code&gt;), we only keep one permutation
per possible k-permutation, and that is our answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;-k-combinations&quot;&gt;(k-)Combinations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The are &lt;code&gt;C(n, k) = n! / (k! * (n-k)!)&lt;/code&gt; ways to pick &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items from a set of size
&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;. For other mathematical notations, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combination#Number_of_k-combinations&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuition:&lt;/strong&gt; We start from the &lt;code&gt;n! / (n-k)!&lt;/code&gt; k-permutations of the set. These
have the right size, but they take ordering into account. This means the
combinations are counted multiple times, with different ordering. How many
ordering of each combination are there?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A combination is just a subset of size &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; of the whole set. With the formula
for permutations, we know there are &lt;code&gt;k!&lt;/code&gt; ways to order the items of this set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So by dividing the number of k-permutations (&lt;code&gt;n! / (n-k)!&lt;/code&gt;) by the number of
permutations (&lt;code&gt;k!&lt;/code&gt;) for each combination, we end up getting the number of
combinations!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sets-of-distinct-items-with-repetition&quot;&gt;Sets of Distinct Items, with Repetition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By repetition, we mean that we change the basic rule of the last section: once a
item has been picked from the set, we put it back and are free to pick it again,
as many times as we like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, looking at the number of permutations of a whole set doesn&amp;#39;t make
sense anymore, as we put back each item after picking it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s look at the other two questions in the presence of repetitions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;k-permutations-with-repetitions-or-n-tuples-&quot;&gt;k-Permutations with repetitions (or n-tuples)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;code&gt;n^k&lt;/code&gt; ways to order &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items from a set of size &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;, with repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuition&lt;/strong&gt;: each time we pick an item, we have &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; possibilities, and these
possibilities just multiply for each item we pick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, for a set of two balls {1, 2}, there are &lt;code&gt;2^3 = 8&lt;/code&gt; ways to pick 3
balls: 111, 112, 121, 122, 211, 212, 221, 222.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;-k-combinations-with-repetitions-or-k-multicombination-or-multisubset-&quot;&gt;(k-)Combinations with repetitions (or k-multicombination or multisubset)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;code&gt;CC(n, k) = C(n+k-1, k) = (n+k-1)! / (k! * (n-1)!)&lt;/code&gt; ways to pick &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;
items from a set of size &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;, with repetition. For the proper mathematical
notation, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combination#Number_of_combinations_with_repetition&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuition:&lt;/strong&gt; This formula is rather harder than the rest, and so the intuition
is a bit more indirect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea is that each k-multicombination can be seen as a sequence of &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; stars
and &lt;em&gt;n-1&lt;/em&gt; separating bars. Basically, the bars define &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; separated intervals
(for instance &lt;code&gt;1|2|3&lt;/code&gt;). Each interval corresponds to an item in the set, and the
number of stars (zero or more) in that interval corresponds to the number of
times that item was picked from the set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So for instance, &lt;code&gt;***|*||*&lt;/code&gt; represents a way to pick 5 (&lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;) items from a set of
4 (&lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt;) items. In this particular solution, the first item is picked thrice, the
third not at all, and the other two only once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we want to know the number of k-multicombinations, the problem reduces to
that of counting the number of such sequences. The sequences will have length
&lt;em&gt;n+k-1&lt;/em&gt;, and there are as many sequences as ways to pick the position of the &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;
stars within the sequence. That is a combination! In particular, it is &lt;code&gt;C(n+k-1,
k)&lt;/code&gt;, and the rest is just applying the combination formula.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;picking-from-multiple-sets&quot;&gt;Picking From Multiple Sets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get to the somewhat harder problem of picking in sets that contains
multiple copies of the same items, let&amp;#39;s see what happens when we pick from
multiple distinct sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to answer questions like: how many ways are there to pick 3 balls from
my first pit containing 10 balls, and 4 balls from my second pit containing 8
balls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s very simple: since picking from each set is independent, we just compute
the two combinations, then multiply them: we can pair any combination from the
first set with a any combination from the second set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same works for permutations, and we can even mix the two kinds. Just
remember: when two number of possibilities are independant (all combinations of
the two set of possibilities are valid), you can just multiply them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;multisets&quot;&gt;Multisets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In what follows, we consider multisets: sets that have repeated items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We always consider a multiset of size &lt;em&gt;n&lt;/em&gt; containing &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; kind of items, such
that there are &lt;em&gt;k1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;k2&lt;/em&gt;, ..., &lt;em&gt;km&lt;/em&gt; copies of the first, second, ..., last
item. Note that &lt;code&gt;k1 + k2 + ... + km = n&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;permutations-of-multisets&quot;&gt;Permutations of Multisets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;code&gt;n! / (k1! * k2! * ... * km!)&lt;/code&gt; ways to order the elements of a
multiset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This formula is also called the &amp;quot;multinomial coefficient&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intuition&lt;/strong&gt;: There would be &lt;code&gt;n!&lt;/code&gt; ways to order the items of the multiset, if
we considered each item to be unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s consider the first kind of items (let&amp;#39;s say &amp;quot;red balls&amp;quot;). All
configurations that have red balls in the same positions are identical. For each
of our &lt;code&gt;n!&lt;/code&gt; permutations, how many have the red balls in the same position,
except with different red balls? This is equivalent to asking to asking how many
ways there are to distribute the red balls in the &amp;quot;red slots&amp;quot;. This is the same
as asking how many ways there are to order all the red balls, which is a simple
permutation: &lt;code&gt;k1!&lt;/code&gt; ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we know there are &lt;code&gt;n!/k1!&lt;/code&gt; permutations in which we do not distinguish
between the red balls, but still distinguish between all the other balls
individually. To obtain, the final result, the same process must be performed
for each kind of ball, successively divising until we obtain the final formula:
&lt;code&gt;n! / (k1! * k2! * ... * km!)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;k-permutations-of-multisets&quot;&gt;k-Permutations of Multisets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;strong&gt;much&lt;/strong&gt; more complicated than what we&amp;#39;d seen so far. A formula can be
derived, but it is unwieldy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will still try to give some intuition, but if you&amp;#39;re after easy to use
formulas, feel free to skip this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Observe that if we pick &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt; items from our multiset such that &lt;code&gt;k &amp;lt; k1, k &amp;lt; k2,
..., k &amp;lt; km&lt;/code&gt;, then the problem is essentially that of k-permutations with
repetition, and there are thus &lt;code&gt;m^k&lt;/code&gt; such permutations. The reason is that we
can never run out of any kind of item.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When this condition doesn&amp;#39;t hold anymore, we would like to still start from
&lt;code&gt;m^k&lt;/code&gt; hypothetical permutations, but remove from this total the permutations
where we picked more of a kind of item than there were in the multiset. This
seems easy, but there is a problem: some of the permutations that have too many
of the first kind of items may also have too many of the second kind of item. We
should not remove them twice!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s call &lt;em&gt;TM1&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TM2&lt;/em&gt;, ..., &lt;em&gt;TMm&lt;/em&gt; the number of permutations where there are
Too Many of the 1st, 2nd, ..., mth item. Computing these values is not trivial:
for each &lt;em&gt;TMi&lt;/em&gt;, we have to sum all k-combinations of &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; items amongst &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;, for
all &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; such that &lt;code&gt;ki &amp;lt; x &amp;lt;= k&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we have two kind of items, the simplified formula is: &lt;code&gt;m^k - TM1 - TM2 +
TM(1,2)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The meaning of &lt;em&gt;TM(1,2)&lt;/em&gt; here is &amp;quot;number of of permutations where there are too
many of the first kind of item AND too many of the second times of item&amp;quot;. Those
permutations are actually substracted twice (once via &lt;em&gt;TM1&lt;/em&gt;, once via &lt;em&gt;TM2&lt;/em&gt;) and
so need to be added back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about three kind of items? It&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;m^k - TM1 - TM2 - TM3 + TM(1, 2) + TM(1,
3) + TM (2, 3) - TM(1, 2, 3)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now have three combinations of item kinds to consider. But after adding back
these permutations, we still aren&amp;#39;t done! Consider the permutations where we
have too many of all three kind of items. We have removed them thrice (&lt;em&gt;TM1&lt;/em&gt;,
&lt;em&gt;TM2&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TM3&lt;/em&gt;) and added them back thrice (&lt;em&gt;TM(1, 2)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TM(1, 3)&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;TM(2, 3)&lt;/em&gt;),
so we need to remove them one final time (&lt;em&gt;TM(1, 2, 3)&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more kinds of items you have, the crazier it gets. Not to mention that all
these &lt;em&gt;TM&lt;/em&gt; values are hairy to compute by themselves. Still easy stuff for a
computer to do, but don&amp;#39;t try this by hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This principle of removing and adding back duplicates is known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inclusion%E2%80%93exclusion_principle&quot;&gt;The
Inclusion-Exclusion Principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;k-permutations-of-multisets-with-repetition&quot;&gt;k-Permutations of Multisets with Repetition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually easy! Because repetition is allowed, it doesn&amp;#39;t matter how many
of each kind of item there is. The answer is thus the same as the number of
k-permutations with reptition for a set that would have only one of each kind of
item: &lt;code&gt;k^m&lt;/code&gt; (where &lt;em&gt;m&lt;/em&gt; is the number of kinds of items).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is a pitfall: while all &lt;code&gt;k^m&lt;/code&gt; k-permutations are possible, they
aren&amp;#39;t all equiprobable — they don&amp;#39;t all have the same probability to be
selected randomly. The probabilities for each k-permutation will depend on the
number of items of each kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;k-combinations-of-multisets&quot;&gt;k-Combinations of Multisets&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has just the same problem as counting the number of k-permutations of a
multiset, the only difference being we do not consider ordering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasoning is much the same, so I shall say no more of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;k-combinations-of-multisets-with-repetition&quot;&gt;k-Combinations of Multisets with Repetition&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, in turn, can be obtained in much the same way as the number of
k-permutations of multisets with repetition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Namely, there are &lt;code&gt;`CC(m, k) = C(m+k-1, k) = (m+k-1)! / (k! * (m-1)!)&lt;/code&gt; such
k-combinations. And again, not all of them are equiprobable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;probabilities&quot;&gt;Probabilities&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combinations and permutations are often used for deriving the probability that a
class of event will occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The general recipe goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Derive the number of configurations that match the class of events (e.g.
drawing three heart cards from a full deck of cards)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Derive the total number of configurations (e.g. the number of ways to draw
three cards from a full deck of cards)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ratio between (1) and (2) is your probability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So to take our example, there are &lt;code&gt;C(52, 3)&lt;/code&gt; ways to draw three
cards out of a full 52-cards deck. There are &lt;code&gt;C(13, 3)&lt;/code&gt; ways to pick three
hearts cards from all heart cards in the deck, so that&amp;#39;s also the number of
scenarios in which we pick three cards from our full deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there is a &lt;code&gt;C(13, 3) / C(52, 3) = 0.013 = 1.3%&lt;/code&gt; probabability to pick 3 heart
cards from a full deck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember you can multiply scenarios if they are independent in order to get the
total number of scenarios. This corresponds to an AND within a scenario. For
instance, the probability to draw three red cards and three black cards from a
full deck. (Answer: &lt;code&gt;C(26, 3)^2 / C(52, 6)&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also add scenarios when they are independent. This corresponds to an OR
within the scenario. Example: There are 12 balls in a bag, 3 of them are red, 4
of them are green and 5 of them are blue. We randomly take out 3 balls from the
bag at the same time. What is the probability that all three balls are of the
same colour? (Answer: &lt;code&gt;(C(5, 3) + C(4, 3) + C(3, 3)) / C(12, 3)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beware of scenarios that are not independant. For instance, if you search the
probability to draw four cards, three of which are red, and one of which is a
figure, you can&amp;#39;t just multiply the probability to pick three red cards and the
probability to pick a figure: the figure might be one of your red cards!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are ways around these issues, and we already mentionned the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inclusion%E2%80%93exclusion_principle&quot;&gt;The
Inclusion-Exclusion Principle&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;m afraid that in intricate cases, there
is no substitute for some thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Combination&quot;&gt;Combinations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permutation&quot;&gt;Permutations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2018-01-20T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/combinatorics</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/combinatorics</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is &quot;The Pervert&#39;s Guide to Ideology&quot; About?</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Like many people who like ideas, I found the
movie &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Pervert%27s_Guide_to_Ideology&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;The Pervert&amp;#39;s Guide to Ideology&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; utterly fascinating. The
movie presents philosopher &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavoj_Žižek&quot;&gt;Slavoj Žižek&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s philosophy and his views on
&amp;quot;ideology&amp;quot;. He does so through analogies to movies in which he is himself
inserted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Although let&amp;#39;s be frank, the movie would be just as enjoyable as
a powerpoint presentation with occasional video excerpts.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even while I was watching the movie, I was thinking that a good part of it was
lost on me. While Žižek&amp;#39;s presents his points quite entertainingly, there are
many of them, and the discussion goes into all kinds of directions. The
different topics are never explicitly tied together, even though the movie ends
on a call-to-action of sorts. But as I was watching the movie, I
sometimes couldn&amp;#39;t remember what was the topic two scenes prior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence I decided to go through the movie again, but this time to produce a
summary, like I have done on this blog multiple times for books and online
articles. However what ended up happening is that I produced a sort of condensed
and annotated transcript of the movie, broken up into scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also included a &lt;a href=&quot;#summary&quot;&gt;thematic summary&lt;/a&gt; at the end, but without having
read the rest (or watched the movie) I&amp;#39;m afraid it&amp;#39;s quite worthless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here comes the big talk, I hope you enjoy it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already am eating from the trashcan all the time. The name of this trashcan
is ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The material force of ideology makes me not see what I&amp;#39;m effectively eating.
It&amp;#39;s not only our reality which enslaves us. The tragedy of our predicament
when we are within ideology, is that when we think that we escape it into
our dreams - at that point we are within ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scene-1&quot;&gt;Scene 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;They Live&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using special &amp;quot;critique-of-ideology&amp;quot; glasses, the hero is able to see the real
message beneath all the propaganda.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in reality, it is ideology which acts like glasses. The critique of ideology
should be like taking off the glasses so as to see reality as it really is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, ideology is not simply imposed on ourselves. Ideology is our spontaneous
relationship to our social world - how we perceive each meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We, in a way, enjoy our ideology. To step out of ideology is a painful
experience, we must force ourselves to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You must be forced to be free. If you trust simply your spontaneous sense of
well-being, you will never get free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When taken out of the movie like this, that last paragraph sounds
somewhat ominous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the idea resonates, the real tragedy of it is that it probably resonates
with 90+% of the people. Everyone thinks everyone else are blind sheep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scene-2&quot;&gt;Scene 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;The Sound of Music&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic insight of psychoanalysis is to distinguish between enjoyment and
simple pleasures. They are not the same. Enjoyment is enjoyment in disturbed
pleasure - even enjoyment in pain. And this excessive factor disturbs the
apparently simple relationship between duty and pleasures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also a space where ideology, especially religious ideology, operates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie, the heroin is a nun sent to tutor children in a rich family. She
ultimately falls in love wih the widowed father of the children. Scared, she
runs back to the covent, but the mother superior encourages her to go back and
follow her heart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This illustrates where the power of attraction of the catholic religion resides.
Catholicism doesn&amp;#39;t really prohibit (in this case sexual pleasures), but rather
gives a hidden permission, as you are covered by the divine &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a characteristic of the Catholic church as an instution, and is the
logic of institution at its purest. The explicit message - &amp;quot;renounce, suffer,
...&amp;quot; - contradicts the true hidden message: &amp;quot;pretend to renouce, and you can get
it all&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Psychoanalysts told Žižek their patients do not feel guilty because of excessive
pleasures, pleasure who would go against their sense of duty or morality; but on
the contrary, they feel guilty for not enjoying enough, for not being able to
enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This reminds me of two other views of religion. One is that of Nietzsche, who
loaths Christianity as an opiate, for it makes people feel good about lacking
what they desire (sex, power, ...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other one (I forgot the source), says that while Protestantism is mostly
based on personal guilt, Catholicism works on externalized shame. A Protestant
faces his guilt alone, meaning he can&amp;#39;t get rid of it without addressing its
cause. The Catholic, on the other hand, always has the confessional as a way to
wipe the slate clean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Putting the three points of view together, you get sort of a win-win situation:
if you can&amp;#39;t get what you want, you get to feel virtuous; otherwise enjoy, but
don&amp;#39;t forget to confess and keep a pious demeanour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scene-3&quot;&gt;Scene 3&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visuals: &lt;em&gt;Žižek walks the desert and talks about Coca Cola, then about the
Kinder Suprise egg.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marx emphasized that a commodity is never just a simple object that we buy and
consume. A commodity is an object full of theological, even metaphysical,
niceties. Its presence always reflects an invisible transcendence. And the
classical publicity for Coke quite openly refers to this absent, invisible
quality. Coke is &amp;quot;The Real Thing&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Coke - That&amp;#39;s it&amp;quot;. It&amp;#39;s not just a
chemical property or something that can be pinpointed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our post-modern socities, we are obliged to enjoy. Enjoyment becomes a kind
or a weird perverted duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paradox of Coke is that you are thirsty, but the more you drink it the more
thirsty you get. A desire is never simply the desire for certain thing. It&amp;#39;s
always also a desire for desire itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the ultimate horror of a desire is to be fully filled-in, met - so that
I desire no longer. The ultimate melancholic experience is the experience - of a
loss of desire itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We cannot return to some foregone era where we were only consuming for actual
needs - if you were thirsty, you drank water, and so on. The excess is with us
forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Coke gets warm - improperly served - it loses its attraction. It&amp;#39;s no
longer &amp;quot;the real thing&amp;quot;. What was transcendant can suddenly turn into shit. It&amp;#39;s
the elementary dialectics of commodities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has nothing to do with its ability to quench thirst. We are talking only
here about that elusive &lt;em&gt;surplus&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Kinder surprise, the commodity&amp;#39;s surplus - the excessive object, the
cause of your desire - is materialized as the plastic toy inside the chocolate
egg.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The egg is what we bought and the toy is what we get for free. But Žižek doesn&amp;#39;t
believe the egg is there to send us on a deeper voyage towards the inner
treasure that makes the commodity desirable. He thinks it&amp;#39;s the other way
around: we should aim at the higher goal - the gold in the middle of an object -
precisely in order to be able to enjoy the surface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not sure I understand all the implications of that last distinction, but it
echoes strongly in my mind with the path/goal distinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is is a frequent trope that what really matters is the journey towards a goal,
rather than the goal itself. This is often supported by the fact that each goal
gives way to another goal - the completion of a goal unable to give us lasting
satisfaction. The journeys comprise most of our live, while the &amp;quot;arriving&amp;quot;
moments where we fullfill a goal are instantaneous and fleeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that, in turn, meshes with what Žižek says about desire - desire is always
also desire for desire itself; the loss of desire is inherently unsatisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A more street-level view about this is that if you don&amp;#39;t enjoy the process, you
will be miserable even if you manage to fullfill your goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/dan_gilbert_asks_why_are_we_happy&quot;&gt;Some research&lt;/a&gt; shows there is a base rate of happiness, and that beyond
the bare fundamentals, material conditions do very little to improve it. This is
the difference between being born rich and becoming rich. Or better, as Hegel
would say &amp;quot;To be free is nothing, to become free is everything.&amp;quot; There is not
happiness without struggle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mark Manson, my favorite street-philosopher, says it&amp;#39;s much more important to
know what pain you are willing to bear (and in fact, enjoy) than what you want
to get (the goal&amp;#39;s payload), as that is what ultimately determine how much you
enjoy the journey you are going to embark on - as well as improve the chance
that you will actually make it to the goal. He often phrases the question rather
&lt;a href=&quot;https://markmanson.net/question&quot;&gt;poetically&lt;/a&gt;: &amp;quot;What&amp;#39;s your favorite flavor of shit
sandwich?&amp;quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://markmanson.net/life-purpose&quot;&gt;Read about it here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;EDIT: I can&amp;#39;t resist to link to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/zizek/comments/40vzna/silly_i_wrote_this_response_to_the_perverts_guide/&quot;&gt;this very funny response&lt;/a&gt; to Žižek
regarding this scene.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scene-4&quot;&gt;Scene 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visuals: &lt;em&gt;Propagandist Imagery&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;A Clockwork Orange&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note: The &amp;quot;Ode to Joy&amp;quot; is the unofficial name of the fourth movement of
Beeethoven&amp;#39;s Ninth Symphony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does this famous &amp;quot;Ode to Joy&amp;quot; stand for? It&amp;#39;s usually perceived as a kind
of ode to humanity, to the brotherhood and freedom of all people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is striking here is the universal adaptability of this well-known melody.
It has been used by political movements which are totally opposed to each other:
Nazi Germany, Communist Russia and China, Apartheid-era South Rodesia, the
modern European Union, ...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how every ideology has to work. It&amp;#39;s never just meaning, it always has
to also work as an empty container open to all possible meanings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a bit like the gut feeling we have when we experience something pathetic
(&amp;quot;arousing pity, sympathy, or compassion&amp;quot;) and we conclude that there is
something deep at work. But we never know what this depth is: it&amp;#39;s a void.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever an ideological text says: &amp;quot;all humanity unite in brotherhood and joy&amp;quot;
and so on, we should alwasy ask whether they mean really all, or if some are
excluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie &lt;em&gt;A Clockwork Orange&lt;/em&gt;, Alex, the protagonist and a cynical
delinquent, is fascinated with the Ode to Joy. According to Žižek, it&amp;#39;s because
he identifies with this place of exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beethoven himself explicitly states this exclusion. We all know the main melody
of the Ode to Joy, the part that has been used by various governments and
organization. But the fourth movement of the Ninth Symphony is actually more
than twenty minutes long, and at some point it transitions into a non-longer
sublimely-beautiful, carnivalesque rythm. Interestingly this rythm is also
featured in &lt;em&gt;A Clockwork Orange&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Žižek, Beethoven identified the first (beautiful) part with
ideology. The second (carnivalesque) part tells the story of that which disturbs
the official ideology and of the failure of the offical ideology to constrain
and tame it. Beethoven was in fact practicing critique of ideology through
music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must admit the point being made in this scene, beyond &amp;quot;don&amp;#39;t trust &lt;em&gt;all is well
and we&amp;#39;re all brothers&lt;/em&gt; ideology&amp;quot; escapes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scene-5&quot;&gt;Scene 5&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;West Side Story&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br&gt;Visuals: &lt;em&gt;CCTV footage of English riots of August 2011&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;West Side Story&lt;/em&gt;, there is a musical number where young delinquents explain
to a (absent) police officer why they are delinquents: they were raised badly,
society has played a trick on them, they need a job, etc. But of course, if they
know all that, why are they acting the way they are?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds like the standard liberal explanation for the English riots: it
cannot be condemned as delinquent vandalism, because of the external conditions
that lead the delinquents to conduct their actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Žižek, this explanation is wrong, because we always have the choice of how
we subjectively interpret our objective conditions. But similarly, he judges the
conservative response demanding more policing and stern judgement to be too
simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regarding the violent form of the protests, and in particular theft; Žižek
says that the delinquents are totally caught up in the dominant ideology of pure
consumerism. They are unable to act it out in their day-to-day life, and so act
it out violently as a form of protest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the disintegration of &amp;quot;big ideologies&amp;quot; such as justice, equality,
etc, only pure consumerism is left functionning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the idea that &amp;quot;non-ideological&amp;quot; protests work within the paradigm of the
ruling ideology sounds nifty, I&amp;#39;m pretty sure looting has been a mainstay of
non-ideological protests well before consumerism was a thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scene-6&quot;&gt;Scene 6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;Taxi Driver&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;The Searchers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The its last scene, &lt;em&gt;Taxi Driver&lt;/em&gt; brings the brutal outburts of violence to its
radical suicidal dimension.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie, Travis, the protagonist, is victim of his fantasies about a young
prostitute. Fantasy is in psychoanalytical perspective fundamentally a lie. Not
in the sense that fantasy is not reality, but in the sense that fantasy covers
up a certain gap in consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things are blurred, when we cannot really get to know things, fantasy
provides an easy answer. The usual mode of fantasy is to construct a scene - not
a scene where I get what I desire - but a scene in which I imagine myself as
desired by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taxi Driver shares its structure with the western movie &lt;em&gt;The Searchers&lt;/em&gt;. In both
films, the hero tries to save a young woman who is perceived as a victim of
brutal abuse. The task is always to save the perceived victim. But what really
drives this violence of the hero is a deep suspicion that the victim is not
simply a victim. That the victim, effectively in a perverted way enjoys or
participates in what appears as her victimhood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the political dimension, this is the big problem of American military
interventions, especially so-called humanitarian interventions. From Iraq to
already Vietnam half a century ago. We try to help them, but what if they really
did not want our help? The result of this debilitating deadlock can only be an
outburst of violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the film, Travis explodes in a killing spree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Violence is never just abstract violence. It&amp;#39;s a kind of brutal intervention in
the real to cover up a certain impotence concerning what we may call cognitive
mapping. You lack a clear picture of what&amp;#39;s going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of his killing spree, barely alive, he symbolically with his fingers
points a gun at his own head. Clear sign that all this violence was basically
suicidal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Žižek, you should have the outburts of violence, but it should be
directed internally, at what ties you to the ruling ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m missing a &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-7&quot;&gt;Scene 7&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;Jaws&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Jaws&lt;/em&gt;, a shark starts to attack people on the beach. What does this attack
mean and what does the shark stand for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were different, even mutually exclusive answers to this question: foreign
threat, natural disasters, threatening immigrants, brutal big capital, ...
According to Žižek, the right answer is &amp;quot;all of them and none of them&amp;quot;. The
function of the shark is to unite all the people&amp;#39;s fears so that we can in away
trade all these fears for one fear alone. In this way our experience of reality
gets much simpler.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nazi anti-semitism worked in exactly the same way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An ordinary German citizen in the late 20s early 30s is - in an abstract way -
like a small child: totally perplexed. Nothing fucntions. Why is that? What does
society wants from him? The newspapers lie to him, and he lost his work and
money because of the inflation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original fascist dream, like every ideology, is to have a cake and eat it
too. Fascism is basically a conservative revolution: economic development,
modern industry; yet none the less reasserting a traditional hierarchical
society, with no class or other antagonisms. Yet these dangers are inherent to
capitalism. Modernisation and industrialisation means disintegration of old
stable relations, it means social conflict. Instability is the way capitalism
functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution then is to generate an ideological narrative which explains how
things went wrong in a society, not as a result of the inherent tensions in the
development of this society but as the result of a foreign intruder. &amp;quot;Things
were ok until Jews penetrated our social body.&amp;quot; The same operation as with the
shark in &lt;em&gt;Jaws&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same happened when John Major was the UK&amp;#39;s prime minister. The figure of the
unemployed single mother was put forward as the culprit for a number of woes:
violence in the suburbs (they couldn&amp;#39;t raise their kids), budge deficits (we
have to support them), etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In an ideological edifice you need some pseudo concrete image like this to
fixate your imagination and then this image can mobilise us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we look at the anti-Semitic image of the Jew, it&amp;#39;s crucial to notice how
contradictory this figure is. Jews are at the same time extra intellectual -
mathematicians, etc - and vulgar: not washing regularly, seducing innocent
girls, etc. This is typical of racism: you try to imagine how the other enjoys
their secret pleasures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In racism, the other is not simply an enemy. His figure is also usually invested
with some specific perverse enjoyment, or maybe he his someone who tries to
steal our enjoyment from us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-8&quot;&gt;Scene 8&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visuals: &lt;em&gt;Nazi Propaganda&lt;/em&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;em&gt;Rammstein Concerts&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not every element of the Nazi ideological of fascism should be disqualified, its
insistence on community and solidarity for instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The German hard rock band Rammstein are often accused of playing with the Nazi
militaristic iconography. But if one observes closely their show one can see
very nicely what they are doing. The minimal elements of the Nazi ideology
enacted by Rammstein are something like pure elements of libidinal investment.
Enjoyment has to be, condensed in some minimal tics: gestures, which do not have
any precise ideological meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Rammstein does is liberate these elements from their Nazi articulations. It
allows us to enjoy them in their pre-ideological state. The way to fight Nazism
is to enjoy these elements, ridiculous as they may appear, by suspending the
Nazi horizon of meaning. This way you undermine Nazism from within.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how does ideology articulate pre-ideological elements? These elements can
also be seen as a kind of a bribe: the way ideology pays us to seduce us into
its edifice. These bribes can be purely libidinal bribes: all those tics are
condensed enjoyment. Or they can be explicit discursive elements like notions of
solidarity of collective discipline, struggle for one&amp;#39;s destiny and so on and so
on. All these in itself are free floating elements which open themselves to
different ideological fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-9&quot;&gt;Scene 9&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Žižek talks about Starbucks coffee.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are we aware that when we buy a cappuccino from Starbucks, we also buy quite a
lot of ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you enter a Starbucks store, it&amp;#39;s usually always displayed in some
posters there, their message which is: Yes our cappuccino is more expensive than
others but we give one percent of all our income to some Guatemala children to
keep them healthy. For the water supply for some Sahara farmers, or to save the
forests, to enable organic growing coffee, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek admires the ingeniosity of this solution. In the old days of pure simple
consumerism, you bought a product and then you felt bad. &amp;quot;My God, I&amp;#39;m just a
consumerist while people are starving in Africa.&amp;quot; So the idea was you had to do
something to counteract your pure distractive consumerism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What Starbucks enables you is to be a consumerist without any bad conscience
because the price for the counter measure - for fighting consumerism - is
already included into the price of a commodity. You pay a little bit more and
you are not just a consumerist but you do also your duty towards environment,
the poor starving people in Africa and so on and so on. This is the ultimate
form of consumerism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-10&quot;&gt;Scene 10&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visuals: &lt;em&gt;Plane Graveyard in the Mojave desert&lt;/em&gt;
Movie: &lt;em&gt;I Am Legend&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should not simply oppose a principal life, dedicated to duty, and enjoying
our small pleasures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s take today&amp;#39;s capitalism. We have, on the one hand, the demands of the
circulation of the capital which push us towards profit making - expansion,
exploitation and destruction of nature - and, on the other hand, ecological
demands: let&amp;#39;s think about our posterity and about our own survival, let&amp;#39;s take
care of nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this opposition between ruthless pursuit capitalist expansion and ecological
awareness, duty - a strange perverted duty of course - is on the side of
capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalism has a strange religious structure. It is propelled by this absolute
demand: capital has to circulate to reproduce itself to expand, and for this
goal anything can be sacrificed, up to our lives, up to nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capitalism is all the time in crisis. This is precisely why it appears almost
indestructible. Crisis is not its obstacle, it is what pushes it forwards
towards permanent self-revolutionising and self-reproduction - always new
products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we see here in the Mojave desert&amp;#39;s plane graveyard is the other side of
capitalist dynamics: tremendous amount of waste. We shouldn&amp;#39;t react to these heaps of
waste by trying to somehow get rid of it. Maybe the first thing to do is to
accept this waste. To accept that there are things out there which serve
nothing. To break out of this eternal cycle of functioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The German philosopher Walter Benjamin said that we experience history, not when
we are engaged in things, when things move, but only when we see this rest waste
of culture being half retaken by nature. At that point we get an intuition of
what history means (e.g. the plane graveyard or post-apocalyptic movies like &lt;em&gt;I
Am Legend&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What confronting this waste bring to us is maybe a chance for an authentic
passive experience. Maybe something new only emerges through the failure, the
suspension of proper functioning of the existing network of our life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This last remark seems true. It is a well-known trope that only can only grow
through adversity. It&amp;#39;s also why capitalism is so good at perpetuating itself:
it imposes an evolutionary pressure on its components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, Žižek takes a step back and proposes to step back one level, and to
consider the failure of capitalism as a system. As much as this is interesting
to consider, it is maybe not so much something to wish for, for the immense
upheaval and consequent suffering it would cause.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, as we will see later, Žižek seems to believe in the redemptive
virtue of some kind of such upheaval or revolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-11&quot;&gt;Scene 11&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;Titanic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does the wreck of the Titanic stand for? The standard reading relates it to
history: the society in all its glitz and glory unaware of its future decay - it
would go on to face both world wars and the great depression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is something in excess of this entire field of meanings - the presence
of the ruin of the Titanic at the bottom of the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When James Cameron organised a trip to the real wreck of the Titanic, he also
made a similar remark. When the explorers approached the wreck, they had this
almost metaphysical experience - that they were approaching a forbidden
territory in which the sacred and the obscene overlap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every effective political, ideological symbol or symptom has to rely on this
dimension of petrified enjoyment. Of the frozen grimace of an excessive pleasure
in pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Žižek, within the movie, the couple escaping together would have
been the true catastrophe. The love affair might have lasted for a few weeks of
intense sex before fading away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kate Winslet is an upper class girl in psychological distress confused, her ego
is in shatters. The function of Leonardo Dicaprio is simply that he helps her to
reconstitute her ego.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek says it&amp;#39;s a new version of an old imperialist myth: when the upper class
people lose their vitality, they need a contact with lower classes. Basically
ruthlessly exploiting them in a vampire like way as it were sucking from them
the life energy. Revitalised they can join their secluded upper class life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often in history, the event which may appear as a catastrophe saves a person or
an idea, elevating it into a myth. Such was the case when the soviet army
crushed the Prague Spring in 1968, an attempt by Czech communists to introduce a
more human-faced socialism. The brutal soviet intervention saved the dream: the
attempt could only have turned into a liberal capitalist state, or into another
authoritarian state, once boundaries became necessary again to ward off
capitalism&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Titanic, through the temporal we have a love story which is redeemed in it&amp;#39;s
idea, saved for eternity. We can ultimately read the catastrophe as a desperate
manoeuvre to save the illusion of eternal love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the final scene of the film, as Leonardo di Caprio stands frozen into the
water, Kate Winslet repeats &amp;quot;I will never let go&amp;quot; but at the same time gently
pushes him off into the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most well remembered scenes of the film, I think in no small
part because the final scene of the film echoes the commentary of the final
scene of Titanic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But clearly the superficial point made in this scene is memorable by itself: the
rich vampirising the poor and Kate Winslet pushing off Leo di Caprio as a symbol
of that. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is also relatively unconvincing - but also utimately uninteresting.
For one, I can&amp;#39;t bring any similar example to mind (maybe the myth of the noble
savage?), and it&amp;#39;s not clear what the myth means or affects in practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not entirely sure what Žižek means when he says that every ideological
symbol has to rely on &amp;quot;this dimension of petrified enjoyment&amp;quot;. I think maybe he
speaks about the &amp;quot;saving of the dream&amp;quot;: that ideological symbols lose their
power when they are put to the test of practice. That a symbol should evoke a
vision that has either never been tested, or pertaining to an universe that is
long gone. Just guessing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-12&quot;&gt;Scene 12&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;The Fall of Berlin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The logic of the production of the couple has a long story in Hollywood and
elsewhere. As a rule we always have a couple whose link is threatened and who
somehow through this ordeal at the end happily gets together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Fall of Berlin&lt;/em&gt; is a Soviet movie that chronicles the second world war from
the soviet standpoint. In that movie, the model worker is in love with a local
girl, but too shy to propose to her. He is called to Moscow to receive a medal
from Stalin who incidentally gives him some dating advice. At this point Žižek
drops probably the funniest quote of the movie: &amp;quot;If Stalin gives you love
advice, it has to succeed.&amp;quot; So the couplet gets together, but then the obstacle
enters: Germans capture the girl. The boy joins the Red Army and we follow him
through all the great battles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea being that in a deeper logic of the film, what these battles were about
was really to recreate the couple. The boy has to get his girl. This is what
happens at the end, but in a very strange way which reconfirms Stalin&amp;#39;s role as
the supreme divine matchmaker. Stalin emerges from an airplane, delivers a
rousing speech; then the girl first sees Stalin, then turns around and sees her
lover, for whom she was waiting all the time of the war. So it&amp;#39;s only through
the presence of Stalin that the couple gets reunited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how ideology works: not Stalin&amp;#39;s speech that says &amp;quot;all the free people
will enjoy peace&amp;quot; etc, but ideology at its more fundamental. This apparently
totally subordinated and unimportant motive, the story of a couple, this is what
is the key element which holds the entire film together, that small surplus
element which attracts us and maintains our attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-13&quot;&gt;Scene 13&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movies: &lt;em&gt;M.A.S.H.&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Full Metal Jacket&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;If...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We usually think that military discipline is just a matter of mindlessly
following orders. Obeying the rules. You don&amp;#39;t think, you do what is your duty.
It&amp;#39;s not as simple as that. If we do this, we just become machines. There has to
be something more. This more can have two basic forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first more benign form is an ironic distance, best epitomised by the movie
and TV series *M.A.S.H., where the military doctors are involved in sexual
escapades and joke all the time. Some people took it as a kind of
antimilitaristic, satiric product but it&amp;#39;s not. These soldiers with all their
practical jokes, operated perfectly as soldiers. They did their duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much more ominous is a kind of obscene supplement to pure military discipline.
In practically all movies about U.S. Marines, the best-known embodiment of this
obscenity are marching chants. This obscenity is not undermining, making fun of
military discipline. It is it&amp;#39;s inner most constituent. If you take this obscene
supplement away, the military machine stops working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The drill sergeant in &lt;em&gt;Full Metal Jacket&lt;/em&gt; is a rather tragic figure. Žižek likes
to imagine him as a person that is quite decent when he returns home. All this
obscene shouting is just a show put on not so much to impress ordinary soldiers
whom he is training as to bribe them with bits of enjoyment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This rule holds not only for military communities but for all human communities.
from the largest nations up to small university departments. You don&amp;#39;t only have
explicit rules. You always, in order to become part of a community, some
implicit unwritten rules which are never publicly recognised but are absolutely
crucial as the point of identification of a group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, everyone knows about the obscene unwritten rituals, which regulate
life in public schools. Older pupils torturing, sexually abusing the younger.
Žižek says we should not simply put all the blame or all the enjoyment on the
older pupils. The victims even are part of this infernal cycle of obscenity.
It&amp;#39;s as if in order to really be a member of a community you have to render your
hands dirty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Full Metal Jacket&lt;/em&gt;, the character of &lt;em&gt;Joker&lt;/em&gt; is close to what we would call
a normal soldier, a &lt;em&gt;M.A.S.H.&lt;/em&gt; type of soldier. He has proper ironic distance.
He proves, at the end, militarily, the most efficient soldier. The character
&lt;em&gt;Gomer Pyle&lt;/em&gt;, on the other hand, ends up shooting itself after undergoing basic
training. He didn&amp;#39;t just run amok, but got too directly identifier with the
obscene rituals. He lost the distance and took them seriously, which is
self-destructive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek says here something to which I strongly disagree: the part about blaming
the victims. It is also in contradiction with some statements he makes later in
the movie about rape victims in ex-Yugoslavia (in &lt;a href=&quot;#scene-16&quot;&gt;scene 16&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think what he has in mind here is &amp;quot;hazing&amp;quot;, and indeed I can well belive that
this is a practice in which the victim can partake and find enjoyment. For
instance, at my university one can join a &amp;quot;students&amp;#39; circles&amp;quot;, and the condition
for admission is undergo such a hazing (although these days the process is to
relatively sanitized and safe). Unfortunately, he does not make clear he refers
to such &amp;quot;hazing&amp;quot;, and it is not what the movie &lt;em&gt;If...&lt;/em&gt; depicts either. And when
such hazing is not done on a voluntary, cancellable basis, there are bound to be
true victims as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-14&quot;&gt;Scene 14&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;The Dark Knight&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truly disturbing thing about &lt;em&gt;The Dark Knight&lt;/em&gt; is that it elevates lie into
a general social principal, into the principal of organisation, of our social
political life. As if our societies can remain stable, can function, only if
based on a lie; and if telling truth - an action embodied by the Joker - means
distraction and disintegration of the social order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie, it is as if lie functions as a hot potato passing from hand to
hand. First there is Harvey Dent, the public prosecutor who lies, claiming he is
Batman. Then we have Gordon, the honest policeman and Batman&amp;#39;s friend, who fakes
his own death. At the end, Batman himself takes upon himself the murders
committed by Harvey Dent, the public prosecutor turned criminal, in order to
maintain the trust of the public in the legal system. The idea is if the
ordinary public were to learn how corrupt was or is the very core of our legal
system then everything would have collapsed, so we need a lie to maintain order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an old conservative wisdom asserted long ago by philosophers from Plato,
especially, and then Immanuel Kant, Edmond Burke and so on. This idea that the
truth is too strong. That a politician should be a cynicist who, although he
knows what is true, tells to ordinary people what Plato called &amp;quot;a noble fable&amp;quot; -
a lie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s be frank. Most demostatic states - public systems of power - today are as
legitimate as you want, submitted to critical press, democratic elections, etc.
They apparently just serve us. And yet if you look closely as how their power
works, in order for them to display authority - and power needs authority -
there need to be a message that says &amp;quot;Yeah, yeah, we are legalised through
elections, but basically we can do whatever we want once in power&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-15&quot;&gt;Scene 15&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visuals: &lt;em&gt;Soviet Propaganda&lt;/em&gt;
Movies: &lt;em&gt;Milos Forman&amp;#39;s Movies&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quote &amp;quot;If there is no God then everything is permitted.&amp;quot; is a great
platitude, and yet it is simply wrong. To the contrary, if there is a god, then
everything is permitted. For those who perceive themselves as instruments of the
divine will, all &amp;quot;petty&amp;quot; moral considerations disappear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how religious fundamentalist work, but not only them. Every form of
totalitarianism works like that as well. A Stalinist political agent is not in
the position of an arrogant master, but in that of a perfect servant. In
Stalinism there is what in psychoanalytic theory is called the &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;. In
the Stalinist universe it has many names: historical progress towards communism,
or simply &amp;quot;history&amp;quot;. A communist experiences himself as simply an instrument
whose function is to actualise a historical necessity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mythic people whose instrument the totalitarian leader is supposed to be,
are never simply the actually existing individuals. It&amp;#39;s some kind of imagined
idealised point of reference which works even when the large majority of the
people are actually resisting the regime. The regime can still stay: &amp;quot;no these
are just individual, not the true people&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The standard Stalinist excuse for attrocity committed is that they do not enjoy
it but act of behalf of the &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; (historical progress). To this effect, 
the iconography of a Stalinist leader always includes details like liking cats
or small children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way to undermine Stalinism is not simply to make fun of the leader, but to
undermine this very reference: the mythic people. This is how Žižek interprets
the early Czech films of Milos Forman. These films mock the ordinary people in
their daily conformission, stupidity, egotistic lust, etc. It is more effective
to demonstate that there is no mythic people to serve a ultimate justification,
rather than to demonstate the leaders are not leaders - they are always happy to
claim being ordinary people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-16&quot;&gt;Scene 16&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;Brief Encounter&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; - the basic element of every ideological edifice has two
contradictory aspects. On the one hand, it is the secret order of things, fate,
divine reason, etc. This guarantees the meaning of what we are doing. On the
other hand, the Big Other is also the order of appearances. Many things are not
simply prohibited, but should not happend for the &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need for our stability a &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; for whom we maintain apperances. Žižek
compares it to the prattling lady in the movie &lt;em&gt;Brief Encounter&lt;/em&gt;, in front of
which the lovers have to maintain apperances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie, after parting with her lover, the woman want to confide her sorrow
in someone. But she can&amp;#39;t trust the prattling lady, and is out of the question
to confess to her husband.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to fully exist as individuals we need the fiction of a &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;.
There must be an agency which registers our predicament. An agency where the
truth of ourselves will be inscribed and accepted, a agency to which to confide.
But what if there is no such agency?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the utmost despair of many women raped in the post Yugoslav war in
Bosnia. What kept many of them alive during their terrible predicament was the
idea that they must survive to tell the truth. But they made the terrible
discovery that no one really listened to them: not ignorant bored social
workers, or some relative making obscene insinutations like that they enjoyed
the rape a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They discovered the truth of what Jacques Lacan claims: there is no &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;.
There may be a virtual &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; to whom you cannot confide, and there may be
a real &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;, whom you cannot trust. We are alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-17&quot;&gt;Scene 17&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;Brazil&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek thinks Kafka was right when he said that for a modern secular
non-religious man, bureaucracy, and especially state bureaucracy, is the only
remaining contact with the dimension of the divine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movie &lt;em&gt;Brazil&lt;/em&gt; depicts the intimate link between bureaucracy and enjoyment.
What the impenetrable omnipotence of bureaucracy harbours is divine enjoyment.
The intense rush of bureaucratic engagement serves nothing. It is the
performance of it&amp;#39;s very purposelessness that generates an intense enjoyment,
ready to reproduce itself forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early in the movie, there is an example of the obverse. The hero has a plumbing
problem and tries to get the state agency to fix it, filling much paperwork to
no avail. Then the ultimate subversive figure, a kind of clandestine plumber,
comes in and fixes the problem. This is the ultimate offense to bureaucracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the ordinary theological universe, your duty is imposed onto you by God, or
society or another higher authority, and your responsibility is to do it. But in
a radically atheist universe you are not only responsible for doing your duty,
you are also responsible for deciding what is your duty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last remark is rather detached from the rest and I have trouble seeing how
it fits into the discussion of bureaucracy. Maybe bureaucracy chases its own
tail precisely to avoid deciding what its duty is? It tries to be its own
purpose and its own justification. That could be said of many other pursuits in
life, and of those who try to drown out the questions by a endless quest for
pleasure, leisure, or carreer advancement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-18&quot;&gt;Scene 18&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;The Last Temptation of Christ&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is always in our subjectivity, in the way we experience ourselves, a
minimum of hysteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hysteria, at its most elementary is a question addressed at the authority which
defines my identity. It&amp;#39;s the question &amp;quot;Why am I what you are telling me that I
am?&amp;quot;. In psychoanalytic theory, hysteria is much more subversive than
perversion. A pervert has no uncertainties, while the hysterical position is
that of a doubt - which is an extremely productive position. New inventions come
from hysterical questioning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The unique character of Christianity is that it transposes this hysterical
questioning onto God himself as a subject. The movie &lt;em&gt;The Last Temptation of
Christ&lt;/em&gt; plays with this idea. When Jesus, in his youth, is told that he is not
only the son of God, but basically God himself, he doesn&amp;#39;t simply accept it. It
is for him a traumatic event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to Žižek, this makes Christianity an exception, and the start of this
idea is to be traced to the book of Job. Job loses everything: house, family,
possessions, etc. Three friends visit and each of them try to justify Job&amp;#39;s
misfortunes in theological terms, but Job does not accept this deeper meaning.
Towards the end of the book, when God appears, he gives right to Job. There is
no meaning in catastrophes. This is the first step in the direction of
delegitimizing suffering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contrast between Judaism and Christianity is the contrast between anxiety
and love. In Judaism, God is in charge, but we do not know what he wants from
us - a traumatic experience. God is this enigmatic, terrifying other.
In Christianity, God demonstrates he loves us by sacrificing his son: an
imaginary sentimal resolution of the situation of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek declares this jewish &amp;quot;insight&amp;quot; (the fact that god is unknowable) to be
profound, and that Christianity could be simply taken as a reversal of that
insight. But Žižek also says we can read God&amp;#39;s gesture in a much more radical
way. What dies on the cross is the guarantee of the &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;. It&amp;#39;s not that
Christ dies to pay for our sins: Pay to whom? Pay for what? It&amp;#39;s the
disintegration of the God which guaranteees the meaning of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The message of Christ is: &amp;quot;I&amp;#39;m dying but my death itself is good news. It means
you are alone, left to your freedom, be in the Holy Ghost, which is just the
community of believers.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s wrong to think that the second coming will be that Christ as a figure will
return somehow. Christ is already here when believers form an emancipatory
collective. This is why I claim that the only way really to be an atheist is to
go through Christianity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity is much more atheist than the usual atheism which can claim there
is no God and so on but none the less retains a certain trust into the &amp;quot;Big
Other&amp;quot;, whether it is called historical necessity or evolution, etc. As humans
it&amp;#39;s true we are reduced to a position within the whole of evolution or history,
but it is difficult to accept that there is nonetheless no &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; there. No
point of reference which guarantees meaning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek&amp;#39;s reading of Christ&amp;#39;s message is surely interesting, but I&amp;#39;m not sure it&amp;#39;s
shared by a lot of people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up a Christian, and I&amp;#39;ve had my breakdown with the dogma. Interestingly,
I am somewhat like what Žižek describes: I don&amp;#39;t have an absolute frame of
meaning in my life, and moreover I&amp;#39;m extremely suspicious of anything that seems
like it proposes to be one. On the other hand, while most people seem more
susceptible - more easily affected by tropes, or taken in by movements - they
don&amp;#39;t that often have clearly identifiable Big Others. And other former or
not-quite Christians I know are not that different from most ordinary people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the fact, I always found my own history with Christianity fascinating. The
Christian truths - both factual such as the existence of God, and theological:
what it meant for us - were for me facts of life, not unlike the fact that the
sky is blue and that we breathe air. People did try to reason me out of it, but
it never worked: what would you say to someone that says you aren&amp;#39;t breathing
air? But as soon as I myself considered the possibility that it might be false,
the whole edifice went crashing down, sustained only by the suspension of
disbelief as it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The frame, as I perceived it as child and then a teenager was extremely simple:
you&amp;#39;re born, you do some good stuff in accordance with God&amp;#39;s will and teachings,
you die and go to heaven. All is well. That simplicity is probably the reason it
came crashing down for me in my late teens - it would have required me to
consciously lie to myself, something I - self-aware as I am - was never able to
countenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For what it&amp;#39;s worth, I think the experience of Christianity in adulthood must be
markedly different. I can&amp;#39;t really comment from experience, but what I expect
from observation: a sort of mysticism fraught with gratitude, and a strong sense
of belonging, both socially and in terms of meaning (the Big Other of Žižek).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I digress - my point is that after searching my own experiences, I can&amp;#39;t
really see how being a Christian really made me less susceptible to other Big
Others. At least not without positing that I&amp;#39;m special snowflake, which makes
his explanation kind of moot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it is true that in the years that followed my skeptical
awakening, I had to contend with the lack of frame of meaning and &amp;quot;being
responsible for deciding what your duty is&amp;quot; as he puts in &lt;a href=&quot;#scene-17&quot;&gt;scene 17&lt;/a&gt;.
This is intensely personal, and it&amp;#39;s maybe not surprising some people come up
with the &amp;quot;wrong&amp;quot; answers, hence the idea that &amp;quot;if God is dead, everything is
permitted&amp;quot;. Observed from the Christian point of view, this statement makes a
lot of sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m sort of sad that Žižek didn&amp;#39;t cite my favourite Bible book: the Book of
Ecclesiastes. It would have been spot on because the whole book is about the
Ecclesiastes&amp;#39; search for meaning. Ultimately, it&amp;#39;s a failed search for meaning,
and the message is relatively simple: enjoy life for what it is, fear God and
keep his commands. Even though God is front and center, he does not give
meaning: &amp;quot;vanity of vanity; all is vanity&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-19&quot;&gt;Scene 19&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;Seconds&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the movie &lt;em&gt;Seconds&lt;/em&gt;, a late middle aged businessman is living a gray, totally
alienated life. Through a friend, he contacts a mysterious agency that offers to
fake his own death, reshape his body and offer him a whole new life as a hip
painter. Despite the glamour and sensuality of his new life (a beautiful
girlfriend, participation in hippie orgies, ...), he starts to miss his old
life. So he decides to go back to the agency. Only too late does he realize the
agency doesn&amp;#39;t want to help him, but will kill him and use his body to fake the
death of another client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek asks what went wrong with the man&amp;#39;s rebirth. After all, everything
changed. But his dreams didn&amp;#39;t change. The agency provided a new existence for
the man by following his dreams. But according to Žižek his dreams were wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek says dreams should be distinguished between the right dreams - pointing
towards a dimension effectively beyondour existing society - and the wrong
dreams - which are are just and idealized consumerist reflection of our society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not simply submitted to our dreams. They do not just come from some
unfathomable depths and we can&amp;#39;t do anything about it. This is the basic lesson
of psychoanalysis and fiction cinema: We are responsible for our dreams. Our
dreams stage our desires and our desires are not objective facts. We created
them, we sustained them, we are responsible for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-20&quot;&gt;Scene 20&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Movie: &lt;em&gt;Zabriskie Point&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scene of mass orgy in &lt;em&gt;Zabriskie Point&lt;/em&gt; is a nice metaphor of what went
wrong with the 1960s hippy revolution. It&amp;#39;s crucial that &lt;em&gt;Zabriskie Point&lt;/em&gt; was
made in 1970 when the authentic revolutionary energy of the sixties was already
losing its strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This orgy is somewhere between subversion of the existing social order and
already the full estheticised reincorporation of this allegedly transgressive
activities into the hegemonic ideology. Although Antonioni meant this as a kind
of transcendence of the existing constraints, we can easily imagine this shot in
some publicity campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;scene-21&quot;&gt;Scene 21&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Conclusion&lt;/em&gt;
Visuals: &lt;em&gt;Chinese Communist Propaganda&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step to freedom is not just to change reality to fit your dreams; it&amp;#39;s
to change the way you dream. And again this hurts because all satisfactions we
have come from our dreams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the big problems of all great revolutionary movements of the 20th century
such as Russia, Cuba or China, is that they did change the social body but the
egalitarian communist society was never realised. The dreams remained the old
dreams and they turned into the ultimate nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now what remains of the radical left waits for a magical event when the true
revolutionary agent will finally awaken, while the depressing lesson of the last
decades is that capitalism has been the true revolutionising force - even as it
serves only itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How come it is easier for us to imagine the end of all life on earth - an
asteroid hitting the planet - than a modest change in our economic order?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the time has come to set our possibilities straight and to become
realists by way of demanding what appears as impossible in the economic domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The surprising explosion of Occupy Wall Street protests, the mass mobilisation
in Greece, the crowds on Tahrir square, they all bear witness for the hidden
potential for a different future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no guarantee that this future will arrive. No train of history on which
we simply have to take a ride. It depends on us, on our will. In revolutionary
upheavals some energy or rather some utopian dreams take place, they explode -
and even if the actual result of a social upheaval is just a commercialised
every day life, this excess of energy, what gets lost in the result, persists
not in reality, but as a dream haunting us waiting to be redeemed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sense, whenever we are engaged in radical emancipatory politics we
should never forget, as Walter Benjamin put it almost a century ago, that every
revolution, if it is an authentic revolution - is not only directed towards the
future, but it redeems also the past failed revolutions. All the ghosts as it
were; the living dead of the past revolution which are roaming around,
unsatisfied will finally find their home in the new freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Norswap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t edit this, as the conclusion is a rather important part. It&amp;#39;s also the
last chance to experience Žižek&amp;#39;s original long-winded-but-not-too-much style.
Also, as I will explain, this is one of the part that made the less sense to me,
making it inherently harder to compact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not too sure what we have here. It does look like an unspecified call to
revolution, but it might just be expressing sympathy and support for
contemporary &amp;quot;revolutions&amp;quot; (for context, remember the movie was released in
2012).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Frankly I&amp;#39;m not convinced with this talk of the ghost of past revolutions, or
about the benefits in having one. Obviously, changes can and should be had, but
whether that has to be achieved through social upheaval is debatable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what bothers me even more is that this &amp;quot;conclusion&amp;quot; - it isn&amp;#39;t really
presented as one, but it is the think piece at the end of the movie - isn&amp;#39;t
really supported by or even connected to the rest of movie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;criticism&quot;&gt;Criticism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below are some criticism of Žižek&amp;#39;s thoughts, found on his &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Slavoj_Žižek&quot;&gt;wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Žižek&amp;#39;s philosophical and political positions are not always clear, and his
work has been criticized for a failure to take a consistent stance. While he
has claimed to stand by a revolutionary Marxist project, his lack of vision
concerning the possible circumstances which could lead to successful
revolution makes it unclear what that project consists of. According to John
Gray and John Holbo, his theoretical argument often lacks grounding in
historical fact, which makes him more provocative than insightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Critics complain of a theoretical chaos in which questions and answers are
confused and in which Žižek constantly recycles old ideas which were
scientifically refuted long ago or which in reality have quite a different
meaning than Žižek gives to them. Harpham calls Žižek&amp;#39;s style &amp;quot;a stream of
nonconsecutive units arranged in arbitrary sequences that solicit a sporadic
and discontinuous attention.&amp;quot; O&amp;#39;Neill concurs: &amp;quot;a dizzying array of wildly
entertaining and often quite maddening rhetorical strategies are deployed in
order to beguile, browbeat, dumbfound, dazzle, confuse, mislead, overwhelm,
and generally subdue the reader into acceptance.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a very negative review of Žižek&amp;#39;s magnum opus Less than Nothing, the
British political philosopher John Gray attacked Žižek for his celebrations of
violence, his failure to ground his theories in historical facts, and his
‘formless radicalism’ which, according to Gray, professes to be communist yet
lacks the conviction that communism could ever be successfully realized. Gray
concluded that Žižek&amp;#39;s work, though entertaining, is intellectually worthless:
&amp;#39;Achieving a deceptive substance by endlessly reiterating an essentially empty
vision, Žižek&amp;#39;s work amounts in the end to less than nothing.&amp;#39;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I highlighted these quotes because they allude to things I myself spotted in the
movie. The topic jumps around quite a bit, and it&amp;#39;s not easy to tie all the
think pieces together. His call to action at the end is indeed unspecified and
the lack of vision on how to actually improve things can be felt throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it is a bit unfair to critize a man&amp;#39;s thought based on a movie, when he has
written a large amounts of books expounding his idea. So I will say no more. Of
his books, the earliest, most highly-regarded, and most relevant with regards to
this movie is *&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Sublime_Object_of_Ideology&quot;&gt;The Sublime Object of Ideology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even laid out on (digital) paper and summarized as it is, it is still not easy
to see at a glance what Žižek is about. My original goal was to produce a
summary, but this turned into an annotated and somewhat condensed transcript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, here is a recap of the main points made in each scene, and
hopefully, this will make the theme apparent (some of these intentionally ironic):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ideology is our spontaneous relationship to the world, how we perceive
meaning. (1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You must be forced to be free of ideology. (1)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Enjoyment is always enjoyment in disturbed pleasure. (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Big Other covers for you. (2)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People feel guilty not because of excessive pleasure, but because they are not
enjoying enough. Enjoyment is a weird perverted duty. (2 &amp;amp; 3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A commodity always reflects an invisible transcendance. (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A desire is always also a desire for desire itself. (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The ultimate melancholic experience is the loss of desire itself: for all our
desires to be met. (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A commodity has a surplus (the transcendance) which is the cause of our
desire. (3)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ideological motifs can be recycled. (4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Universalist messages usually specify a place of exclusion. (4)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The disintegration of big ideologies (justice, equality, ...) leads to
revolutions following the hegemonic ideology: consumerism. (5)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fantasy covers up a gap in consistency. (6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Violence is never abstract: it&amp;#39;s a brutal intervention in the real covering up
an impotence concerning cognitive mapping. (6)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want to have your cake and eat it too, set up a scapegoat. (7)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The enemy is invested with perverse enjoyment, or alternatively tries to steal
our own enjoyment. (7)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can liberate enjoyment condensed in minimal gestures from specific
ideologies. (8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;These minimal gestures are bribes that ideologies use to seduce us. (8)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Commodities including the price for the countermeasure are the ultimate form
of consumerism. (9)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Maybe something new only emerges through the failure of our existing support
network. (10)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rich people vampirise the poor. (11)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a catastrophe elevates a person or idea into a myth (petrified
enjoyment). (11)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The logic of the couple in movies, an ideological motive that ties a movie
together. (12)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can&amp;#39;t just follow orders, there are to be something more. Either proper
ironic distnace, or obscenity - bits of enjoyment as bribes. (13)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Conservative wisdom: the truth is too strong, a politician should be a
cynicist who tells the people a noble lie. (14)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;God justifies everything: his &amp;quot;instruments&amp;quot; are not bothered by petty moral
considerations. (15)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both religious fundamentalism and totalitarianism are forms of &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;.
(15)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;To undermine Stalinism, one has to undermine the mythic people it purports to
serve. (15)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; is (a) the guarantee of meaning for our actions. (16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; is (b) the order of appearances we need to preserve. (16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; is (c) an agency in which the truth of ourselves is to be
inscribed and accepted, an agency in which to confide. (16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;There is no &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot;. (16)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In a radically atheist universe you are not only responsible for doing your
duty, you are also responsible for deciding what is your duty. (17)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bureaucracy as a self-perpetuating mechanism for enjoyment that serves
nothing, a distraction to avoid deciding what our duty is. (17)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hysteria is a question addressed at the authority which defines my identity, a
position of doubt (unlike perversion), hence very productive. (18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A reading of Christianity as announcing the death of the &amp;quot;Big Other&amp;quot; and
delegitimizing suffering. (18)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We are responsible for our dreams. (19)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Transcendence of the existing constraints end up being reincorporated into the
hegemonic ideology. (20)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Revolución! (21)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hasta la sabiduría, siempre!&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2017-12-19T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/zizek-ideology</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/zizek-ideology</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A simple Java Lexer</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;I just released &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/java-lexer&quot;&gt;java-lexer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.oracle.com/javase/specs/jls/se9/html/jls-3.html&quot;&gt;JLS&lt;/a&gt;-compliant yet simplistic lexer for the
Java language. It&amp;#39;s completely stand-alone and not dependent on any parser or
other libraries. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/java-lexer&quot;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2017-12-13T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/java-lexer-release</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/java-lexer-release</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights From &quot;The Denial of Death&quot;</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Denial_of_Death&quot;&gt;The Denial of Death&lt;/a&gt; is book by Ernest Becker that earned the Pulitzer
for non-ficiton in 1974. The basic premise of the book is that man is trapped in
between his &amp;quot;creatureliness&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;symbolic self&amp;quot;. Consciousness has made man
aware of his own powers, but also of his miserable creatureliness and his
destiny to die.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t read the book, but found a lot of gems in
this &lt;a href=&quot;https://taylorpearson.me/book-review/denial-death-summary-quotes/&quot;&gt;compilation of selected quotes&lt;/a&gt; made by Taylor Pearson. I also
drew from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Denial_of_Death&quot;&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a summary of some interesting points made by the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-urge-to-heroism&quot;&gt;The Urge to Heroism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our motivations have often more to do with the need to achieve than with the
matter at hand. Making a killing in business or on the battlefield frequently
has less to do with economic need or political reality than with the need for
assuring ourselves that we have achieved something of lasting worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In man a working level of narcissism is inseparable from self-esteem, from a
basic sense of self-worth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Urge to heroism is natural, and to admit it honest. For everyone to admit it
would probably release such pent-up force as to be devastating to societies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Societies, except primitive ones, cannot provide to men a path to heroism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Christianity achieved it to some extent, by mere participation: it could take
the simple and the mighty, and make them all secure heroes, simply by taking a
step back from the world into another dimension: that of heaven. Christianity
took creature consciousness — the thing man most wanted to deny — and made it
the very condition for his cosmic heroism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But humanity&amp;#39;s traditional &amp;quot;hero-systems&amp;quot;, such as religion, are no longer
convincing in the age of reason. Science attempts to serve as an immortality
project (see below), something it can never do, because it is unable to provide
agreeable, absolute meanings to human life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To become conscious of what one is doing to earn his feeling of heroism is the
main self-analytic problem of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The crisis of modern society is precisely that the youth no longer feel heroic
in the plan for action that their culture has set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Modern man cannot find his heroism in everyday life any more, as men did in
traditional societies just by doing their daily duty of raising children,
working, and worshipping. He needs revolutions and wars and &amp;quot;continuing&amp;quot;
revolutions to last when the revolutions and wars end. That is the price modern
man pays for the eclipse of the sacred dimension. When he dethroned the ideas of
soul and God he was thrown back hopelessly on his own resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-immortality-project&quot;&gt;The Immortality Project&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since humanity has a dualistic nature consisting of a physical self and a
symbolic self, we are able to transcend the dilemma of mortality through
heroism, by focusing our attention mainly on our symbolic selves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This symbolic self-focus takes the form of an individual&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;immortality project&amp;quot;
(or &amp;quot;causa sui project&amp;quot;), which is essentially a symbolic belief-system that
ensures oneself is believed superior to physical reality. By successfully living
under the terms of the immortality project, people feel they can become heroic
and, henceforth, part of something eternal; something that will never die as
compared to their physical body. This, in turn, gives people the feeling that
their lives have meaning, a purpose, and are significant in the grand scheme of
things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arbitrariness of human-invented immortality projects makes them naturally
prone to conflict. When one immortality project conflicts with another, it is
essentially an accusation of &amp;#39;wrongness of life&amp;#39;, and so sets the context for
both aggressive and defensive behavior. Each party will want to prove its belief
system is superior, a better way of life. Thus these immortality projects are
considered a fundamental driver of human conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;anxiety-fear-of-death-and-illusions&quot;&gt;Anxiety, Fear of Death and Illusions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In nature fear and anxiousness improve survival, hence today we still are
anxious, even though the environment does not justify it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man works against his fragility by seeking living experiences, moving towards
more life. Or he plunges in self-absorbing activities. Fear of death can be
ignored and sometimes absorbed into the life-expanding process: this is called
&lt;em&gt;repression&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How can people stand the really demonic activity of working behind those hellish
ranges in hotel kitchens, the frantic whirl of waiting on a dozen tables at one
time, the madness of the travel agent’s office at the height of the tourist
season, or the torture of working with a jack-hammer all day on a hot summer
street. The answer is that the craziness of these activities is exactly that of
the human condition. They are &amp;quot;right&amp;quot; us because the alternative is natural
desperation. The daily madness of these jobs is a repeated vaccination against
the madness of the asylum. Look at the joy and eagerness with which workers
return from vacation to their compulsive routines. They plunge into their work
with equanimity and lightheartedness because it drowns out something more
ominous. Men have to be protected from reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which poses another gigantic problem to a sophisticated Marxism (or universal
basic income): What is the nature of the obsessive denials of reality that a
Utopian society will provide to keep men from going mad?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the awareness of mortality dawns beyond the frenetic activity, it emerges in pure
form. Things like psychotic break can issue when repression is no longer possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man is horrified by his own basic animal condition, a condition that, especially
as a child, he cannot understand and that, as an adult, he cannot accept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a need for illusion — without being cynical. There is a great deal of
falseness and self-deception in the cultural immortality project, but there is
also the necessity of this project. Man needs a second world, a world of humanly
created meaning, a new reality that he can live, dramatize, nourish himself in.
We need new convincing illusions that enable us to feel heroic in ways that are
agreeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Becker does not provide any definitive answer as to what these illusions might
be, mainly because he believes that there is no perfect solution. Instead, he
hopes that gradual realization of humanity&amp;#39;s innate motivations, namely death,
can help to bring about a better world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;sex-love-and-the-body&quot;&gt;Sex, Love and the Body&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to have sex without guilt: the body casts a shadow on the
person&amp;#39;s inner freedom / real self that — through sex — is being forced into a
standardized, mechanical, biological role.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Love lets us feel that the other person recognizes and respects or
symbolic self even as they see us at our most animalistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The body is the clear problem over which he must triumph in order to build a
cultural personality at all, as it is the clear enemy in establishing our
divinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;character-and-reality&quot;&gt;Character and Reality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Character is a neurotic defense against despair, and shedding character means
risking death and madness. To see reality, one must die and be reborn, which
means shedding character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kierkegaard: it&amp;#39;s good to open toward new possibility and choice, to be able to
face anxiety. To be closed is evil, it means shutting out revelations and giving
up on reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The depressed person avoids the possibility of independence and more life
precisely because these are what threaten him with destruction and death. He
holds on to the people who have enslaved him in a network of crushing
obligations, belittling interaction, precisely because these people are his
shelter, his strength, his protection against the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the prison of one&amp;#39;s character one can pretend and feel that he is somebody,
that the world is manageable, that there is a reason for one&amp;#39;s life, a ready
justification for one&amp;#39;s action. To live automatically and uncritically is to be
assured of at least a minimum share of the programmed cultural heroics — what we
might call &amp;quot;prison heroism&amp;quot; — feeling like an insider.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;authority-delegated-power&quot;&gt;Authority &amp;amp; Delegated Power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you admit that you are a creature, you accomplish one basic thing: you
demolish all your unconscious power linkages or supports. Each child grounds
himself in some power that transcends him. Usually it is a combination of his
parents, his social group, and the symbols of his society and nation. This is
the unthinking web of support which allows him to believe in himself, as he
functions on the automatic security of delegated powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man has &amp;quot;an extreme passion for authority&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;wishes to be governed by
unrestricted force&amp;quot;. People have &amp;quot;a longing to be hypnotized&amp;quot; by a leader
because they want to get back the magical protection and feeling of
belongingness that they enjoyed from their parents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader is a creature of the group, as are his followers. The leader has no
more freedom to be himself, as he has to be a reflex of the group. The followers
give in the leader&amp;#39;s commands but can always retain the feeling that these
commands are alien to them — the leader&amp;#39;s responsibility. This can make people
guiltless, as they can imagine themselves temporary victims of the leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man uses morality to get to a place of belongingness and perpetuation in the
universe. By conforming to the rules made by representatives of natural power
(leaders), his safe belongingness is assured. This is natural: we tell the child
when he is good so that he doesn’t have to be afraid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first way in which man attempts to overcome his own finitude and
unimportance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;heroic-gifts&quot;&gt;Heroic Gifts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second way man attmepts to overcome his own finitude is by developing a
really valuable heroic gift, becoming extra-special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are the average man you give your heroic gift to the society in which you
live, and you give the gift that society specifies in advance. If you are an
artist you fashion a peculiarly personal gift, the justification of your own
heroic identity, which means that it is always aimed at least partly over the
heads of your fellow men. After all, they can’t grant the immortality of your
personal soul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The social hero-system into which we are born marks out paths for our heroism,
paths to which we conform, to which we shape ourselves so that we can please
others, become what they expect us to be. And instead of working our inner
secret we gradually cover it over and forget it, while we become purely external
men, playing successfully the standardized hero-game into which we happen to
fall by accident, by family connection, by reflex patriotism, or by the simple
need to eat and the urge to procreate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real problem of man: to find his true talent, his secret gift, his
authentic vocation. This question may become so intolerable as to cause suicide
and flight in the rush of experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A person spends years coming into his own, developing his talent, his unique
gifts, perfecting his discriminations about the world, broadening and sharpening
his appetite, learning to bear the disappointments of life, becoming mature,
seasoned—finally a unique creature in nature, standing with some dignity and
nobility and transcending the animal condition; no longer driven, no longer a
complete reflex, not stamped out of any mold. And then the real tragedy, as
André Malraux wrote in The Human Condition: that it takes sixty years of
incredible suffering and effort to make such an individual, and then he is good
only for dying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;repression-and-partialization&quot;&gt;Repression and Partialization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The great lesson of Freudian psychology: that repression is normal
self-protection and creative self-restriction—in a real sense, man’s natural
substitute for instinct.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is impossible without &lt;em&gt;partialization&lt;/em&gt;. What we call the well-adjusted man
has just this capacity to partialize the world for comfortable action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partializing the world is biting off what an animal can chew. Not to have this
talent means constantly biting off more than one can chew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does the artist so often avoid clinical neurosis, when he is so much a
candidate for it because of his vivid imagination, his openness to the finest
and broadest aspects of experience, his isolation from the cultural world-view
that satisfies everyone else?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is that he takes in the world, but instead of being oppressed by it
he reworks it in his own personality and recreates it in the work of art. The
neurotic is precisely the one who cannot create — the &amp;quot;artiste-manqué&amp;quot;. We might
say that both the artist and the neurotic bite off more than they can chew, but
the artist spews it back out again and chews it over in an objectified way, as
an external, active, work project.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2017-12-09T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/denial-of-death</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/denial-of-death</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Research: A Personal Perspective</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Even though it&amp;#39;s what I spend most of my time on, I don&amp;#39;t often post about my
research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One reason is that I am still a perfectionnist and I feel bad about
posting something which isn&amp;#39;t as complete as I&amp;#39;d like it to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know that, supposedly, communicating about your ongoing research is supposed
to be beneficial. Frankly, I have yet to see evidence of that, beyond the
benefit of organizing your thoughts. It might just be that my field (parsing) is
quite small, and everyone is busy on his own thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A second issue is that my research project has evolved quite a bit over the
years, as has the way I came to evaluate my research results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, today I want to do a quick tour of all my research so far. This will
include some (very high-level) technical details as well as my unfiltered
feelings on my work. It will be fairly intermingled, but feel free to skip what
doesn&amp;#39;t interest you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;prelude&quot;&gt;Prelude&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually started a PhD in networking; the topic was improving Software Defined
Networks (SDN). Over the course of a year, I grew disillusioned with SDN and
realized the difficulties to do practical research on that topic. I&amp;#39;m not saying
the field is bogus at all, there is very high quality research there — but
clearly the field wasn&amp;#39;t well matched to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point I had gotten a scholarship from the national science foundation,
and so my next move was to switch my topic and my adviser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I really wanted to do was experiment with programming language design. To
do this I had a grandiose, over-ambitious idea that was both a language feature
in its own right, and a way to enable cheap experimentation with language design
later down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal was to make a truly extensible language. The details were of course not
hammered out, but you can think about it as taking macro a step further, to
enable not only local changes, but global program transformations. These
transformations had to compose gracefully, and work within a typed language too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people warned me about the over-ambitious part, and I knew they were right.
Nevertheless, that idea was kind of the &amp;quot;true north&amp;quot; that would guide my
research direction. So I starting on my path, with the first thing I needed: a
parser.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The motiviation to rolling my own parser was that the grammar of the language
would have to change dynamically, depending on included extensions. It seemed
like an important piece of infrastructure to get full control on, and I had
written my own parser before... how hard could this be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, in the end my thesis only focuses on parsing, so it looks like it was
rather hard after all :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the rest of this post, let me walk you through the various papers I wrote
and projects I undertook&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;-sdload-an-extensible-framework-for-sdn-workload-generation-&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;SDLoad: An Extensible Framework for SDN Workload Generation&amp;quot;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://norswap.com/pubs/hotsdn2014.pdf&quot;&gt;🔗 link to paper (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is actually an extended abstract I made while I was still working on
networking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, this was a framework to generate &amp;quot;stuff&amp;quot; — graph of objects
really. I built it from scratch and then employed it to generate descriptions of
SDN workload (so basically a sequence of network events).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generation is random, modulo constraints that the user can supply, either as
filtering code, or as custom generators. It was also possible to define and use
different statistical distribution, assign weights to certain events, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The generation approach is not novel at all, as are all things so general and
abstract. The goal was not actually to make a great contribution, but rather to
build a tool to would have been useful later in my thesis (as planned at the
time) and maybe even to other researcher. Well, that didn&amp;#39;t really pan out,
albeit it might have been used in some later research project (I&amp;#39;m not sure).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the idea of generating inputs stayed with me, and I now use it
regularly to do testing, as &lt;a href=&quot;http://norswap.com/gen-testing/&quot;&gt;described in this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;-parsing-expression-grammars-made-practical-&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Parsing Expression Grammars Made Practical&amp;quot;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://norswap.com/pubs/sle2015.pdf&quot;&gt;🔗 link to paper (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first paper I wrote after switching my topic, and I wrote it rather
quickly (in about three months). I got a big surge of initial motivation from
this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically the paper, which was submitted as a &amp;quot;tool paper&amp;quot; presents a parsing
framework based on &lt;em&gt;Parsing Expression Grammars&lt;/em&gt; (PEG), a relatively recent grammar
formalism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later in my PhD I would come to dismiss this paper as &amp;quot;not really much&amp;quot;, but now
I have newfound appreciation for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The paper basically has three contributions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It presents a general algorithm to allow left-recursion in PEG grammars,
something that the formalism doesn&amp;#39;t normally allow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It presents a modification of that algorithm that enables to handle
precedence and associativity, given that grammar rules have been properly
annotated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It shows how to customize different aspects of the parse process with
arbitrary code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contribution 1, arguably the most intersting to someone reading the paper, is
actually 95% work from Chris Seaton in his master thesis (something I made
super clear in the paper). But burried in his master thesis, the technique had
never received the exposure it deserved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contribution 3 is the start of a theme that would continue throughout my thesis:
the fact that if the execution model is defined precisely enough, it becomes
easier to extend with new features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I think the value in the paper is not where it pretends to be. The
tool has little importance, more intersting are the techniques I used, that
could be reused in other tools. Having a paper that explains how you can do
left-recursion and explicit precedence and associativity with PEG — that&amp;#39;s
useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the paper is not as readily findable as I would have wished. I
have come to rue its name, which is both cocky and not very informative on the
content of the paper. I probably should take the time to link that paper from a
few places of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;-taming-context-sensitive-languages-with-principled-stateful-parsing-&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Taming Context-Sensitive Languages with Principled Stateful Parsing&amp;quot;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://norswap.com/pubs/sle2016.pdf&quot;&gt;🔗 link to paper (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper grew out of the first one rather opportunistically. Basically I
noticed a pattern in how I dealth with various kind of &amp;quot;state&amp;quot; within my parser
when backtracking (input position, tables, ...). The idea was then to generalize
that to any kind of user-defined state.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having user-defined state that can guide the parse is rather useful, as it
turns. It can be used to express grammars that feature &lt;em&gt;context-sensitivity&lt;/em&gt;,
something parsers don&amp;#39;t normally allow. Explaining context-sensitivity is rather
hard, but the simplest example is probably the issue of recall: recalling some
piece of input later. For instance in XML, opening and closing tags have to
match: &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a&amp;gt;x&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is valid but not &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;a&amp;gt;x&amp;lt;/z&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the paper basically explains how you can have state in your parser, in a way
that is safe despite the presence of backtracking. I also provided an
implementation of the approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This paper has probably been my major research effort so far, although I have
good hopes that it will be topped by what I&amp;#39;m working on right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All told, this took me a good year of work. Its first incarnation was submitted
at OOPSLA in Jan. 2016, then reworked and submitted (and subsequently accepted)
at SLE in June 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is good and useful research. In the end, the solution is almost
disappointingly simple; but it didn&amp;#39;t start out simple, it took me great pains
to get there. Someone smarter than me, or at least more mindful of his work,
would probably have completed this much faster than me, but in the end I am not
disappointed with the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My problem with this paper lays on another dimension: that of strategy and
carreer development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem that this approach solves is real, and yet it is tiny at the same
time. Most languages are 99+ % not context-sensitive, but the context-sensitive
parts will really annoy the hell of you when you get to it. Most often this is
worked around with various hacks, and — you know what — most of the time this is
good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does that mean we shouldn&amp;#39;t have a principled solution? Of course not. It just
means it&amp;#39;s a solution to a minor problem instead of a major one. Frankly,
expecting to come up with major work a few months after entering a field might
be a sign of unbridled hubris on my parts — but I&amp;#39;m just relating how feel (or
at least felt for a long time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question is then: did I have better alternatives? I&amp;#39;m not sure, really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;uranium-semantic-analysis&quot;&gt;Uranium &amp;amp; Semantic Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before getting to the next published paper, let&amp;#39;s actually get to the project
that occupied the intervening year, but didn&amp;#39;t actually lead to any publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point, it was quite clear I wouldn&amp;#39;t be able to develop even a
significant part of the extensible language during my thesis. My plan was to
reframe the thesis&amp;#39; objective as &amp;quot;improving compiler toolchains&amp;quot;, with the idea
that this might eventually help bring about the extensible language, or really
anything language-related I wanted to experiment with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During that year, I worked on a framework dubbed &lt;em&gt;Uranium&lt;/em&gt; that would make it
easier to write the semantic analysis stage of a compiler. Semantic analysis is
notably what takes care of name resolution (associating identifiers and
declarations) and typing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Uranium ended up looking a lot like &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attribute_grammar&quot;&gt;attribute grammars&lt;/a&gt;: a way to derive the
values of attributes associated with AST nodes. Besides shedding the historical
baggage (which could be considered a good or a bad thing), the framework also
took inspiration for the classical type system formal notation, which makes use
of inference rules. In line with the rest of my work, these rules were going to
be written using arbitrary code, in order to enable maximum flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, the way of it is that you define inference rules that derive the
values of attributes given the availability of some other attributes, and the
framework was going to order all this stuff for you. It works in a bottom-up
manner, trying to derive all attributes, instead of the top-down manner that
characterize most attribute grammar implementations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The framework itself ended up being rather simple, both in concepts and
implementation. I used the Java language as a use case, to try out if I could
express non-trivial semantics using it. And this is where the problems begin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Java is a big language, with a lot of edge cases and ambiguities. But it is by
no means alone — I think the same can be said of almost every language that we
can qualify as &amp;quot;mainstream&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some difficulties I ran into:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was too ambitious. I wanted the framework to be fully incremental, meaning
it could start deriving meaning even with missing information (~declarations),
and could react to updated information. This added a lot of complexity while I
was still early in the design stage. I ended up getting rid of that
requirement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I had to take care of location and loading Java classes: I did not just look
at source files and assume the program did not use any standard library. While
I think it is miles easier in Java than in, say, C or C++, it still was a
non-trivial implementation effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s hard to resolve identifier chains. First, you have to disambiguate what
is a value, what is a class, and what is a package. For instance, let&amp;#39;s assume
we have determined that &lt;code&gt;java.util.List&lt;/code&gt; refers to a type; &lt;code&gt;java&lt;/code&gt; could be
either a class or part of a package name. The Java rule is that if &lt;code&gt;java&lt;/code&gt; can
be resolved to a class, the whole chain will be resolved assuming that (and
potentially fail). In order to know whether &lt;code&gt;java&lt;/code&gt; is a class, you need to
know all the classes in the current package, the local classes, as well as all
the system classes that are available by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to their inherent ambiguity, identifier chains also posed problems
in their interactions with the framework. The right way to model identifier
chains is to make the resolution of each element in the chain dependent on the
previous element. However, I had represented identifier chains as a single AST
node holding a list, so instead I relied on a concept of &lt;em&gt;continuation&lt;/em&gt;: an
inference rule could report that it needed more information to proceed, and
the framework would re-try the rule once the information became available. An
identifier chain would emit one such continuation (one at a time) per
identifier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, the lesson was that the effort to implement the inference rules and
the surrounding support infrastructure for a single language dwarfed the effort
of building the inference framework. It&amp;#39;s a bit hard to sell an improvement that
only saves you 10% of the effort. With the approach being novel, it probably
could have flied; but with attribute grammars looming in the background, no
dice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you, an idea, in addition to just the rules, the Java system needed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Model of source elements (essentially more precise version of the AST nodes,
which could also hold extra information, for instance related to name
resolution). These models needed to come in three flavours, because there are
three ways to acquire the information of a class: through a source file,
through a bytecode class, or through reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Building a scope tree to represent lexical scoping and determine which
declarations where visible where.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fairly precise typing hierarchies and sub/supertyping algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The class location and loading mechanism already discussed before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a lot! In comparison the framework was minimal in complexity and the only
big change that it needed was the addition of the &lt;em&gt;continuation&lt;/em&gt; concept
mentionned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem was that it was hard to migrate complexity from the Java
implementation into the framework, because the framework was supposed to be
agnostic about the language it was used to implement. For instance, I could have
implemented utilities that made typing much easier to implement... but then I
would have had to tie to framework to a certain idea of how typing is supposed
to work. That approach is more in line with how language workbenches (like
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.metaborg.org/en/latest/&quot;&gt;Spoofax&lt;/a&gt;) work, and there is nothing wrong with that, it&amp;#39;s just not what I was
trying to build.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ultimately faced with the prospect of continuing to pour work into a
hard-to-sell blackhole of a use-case, I decided to write off the project and
pivot onto something different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The failure is still fresh, and so my outlook might not yet be good enough.
Nevertheless, I think that the mistake I made in this case was badly
overestimating the problem, as well as misunderstanding its nature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did look at some semantic analysis code, and I saw these big tangled messes.
My conclusion was that there should be a simpler, more structured way to go
about things. However I failed to consider that the problem might have been a
matter of &lt;em&gt;programming in the small&lt;/em&gt;: that some refactoring as well as good
documentation could have helped tremendously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also wasn&amp;#39;t really clear to me what part of the complexity
was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_Silver_Bullet&quot;&gt;intrinsic&lt;/a&gt; and which part was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/No_Silver_Bullet&quot;&gt;accidental&lt;/a&gt;: I think I
overestimated the second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What could have have done to seize up the problem better? Probably try to write
semantic analysis code without any framework, to get an intuitive sense of where
the issues lay. This is something I had done for parsing (writing a parser by
hand), although my purpose at the time was not to learn about the difficulties
in parsing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;red-shift-procedural-shift-reduce-parsing&quot;&gt;Red Shift: Procedural Shift-Reduce Parsing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://norswap.com/pubs/sle2017.pdf&quot;&gt;🔗 link to paper (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I initially wanted to publish something about Uranium at SLE 2017, but clearly
that was not going to fly. As I re-read the call for paper, I noticed that this
year they were accepting 4-page &amp;quot;vision papers&amp;quot; that outlined a vision for an
early stage idea. That was for me the opportunity to revisit an idle thought I
had during the preceding year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea was about finding the converse of &lt;acronym=&quot;Parsing Expression
Grammars&quot;&gt;PEGs&lt;/acronym&gt; for bottom-up parsing. PEGs can be seen as a
formalization of the way people naturally write top-down parsers by hand. So how
did people write bottom-up parsers by hand, and how could I formalize or package
that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, I found very little about hand-written bottom-up parsers, yet I
saw how it could make sense. The paper is precisely about that: how to write
bottom-up parsers by hand, and the potential benefits of doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Namely, in the approach I envisionned, there were two big benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The parser was permissive and so would parse as much as possible, even in the
presence of errors. The trick is that the parser recognizes low-level
structures first, and builds them up into higher-level structures (e.g. from
literals to expressions to statements to functions).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It would enable better error reporting, as the partial structures we build up
during the parse could be used to provide context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I cranked the paper out in less than two weeks, also building a small prototype
to confirm my ideas were not completely out of whack. To paraphrase a well-known
mass-murderer: &amp;quot;There are years where nothing happens; and there are weeks where
years happen.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-m-doing-now&quot;&gt;What I&amp;#39;m Doing Now&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last paper was the inflexion point I needed to pivot away from the Uranium
project. Instead, I launched into what I&amp;#39;m currently doing, which is build up
this idea into a proper framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My handmade bottom-up parsers made use of &lt;em&gt;reducers&lt;/em&gt;: bits of code that look 
at the parse stack and perform a reduction if some condition holds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized that said conditions were almost always equivalent to performing a
regular expression match over the tokens and AST nodes on the parse stack.
Hence, my first step was to built a library (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/skelex&quot;&gt;skelex&lt;/a&gt;) to perform that part of
the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next part will be to build the framework proper, which orchestrates the
regular expression matching and the nodes reductions. I&amp;#39;m still working on the
design, so there is not much I can say right now, but stay tuned :)&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2017-12-03T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/research-personal</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/research-personal</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skelex</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;I recently released &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/skelex&quot;&gt;skelex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;, a regular expression (regex) matching library that
works over streams of objects. Unlike most regex libraries, it also produces a
parse tree. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/norswap/skelex&quot;&gt;Check it out!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2017-11-29T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/skelex-release</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/skelex-release</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TSR&#39;s Series on Celerity — A Summary</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestrategicreview.net/&quot;&gt;The Strategic Review&lt;/a&gt; Series on Celerity is
an eleven-parts mailing list series written
by &lt;a href=&quot;http://sebastianmarshall.com/&quot;&gt;Sebastian Marshall&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subject is &lt;em&gt;celerity&lt;/em&gt;, roughly speed as a trait of character: &lt;em&gt;moving fast&lt;/em&gt;
as in business, not necessarly as in a race. The series explains what celerity
is and how to achieve it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the titles of the ten parts (parenthesized annotations are mine):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#01-frenzied-genius-suppression-&quot;&gt;Frenzied Genius (Suppression)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#02-power-laws-exponential-growth-&quot;&gt;Power Laws (Exponential Growth)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#03-attrition-and-maneuver&quot;&gt;Attrition and Maneuver&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#04-cohesion&quot;&gt;Cohesion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#05-sociotechnical-alignment&quot;&gt;Sociotechnical Alignment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#06-pace-maximum-vs-maximum-sustainable-speed-&quot;&gt;Pace (Maximum vs Maximum Sustainable Speed)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#07-windows-of-opportunity&quot;&gt;Windows of Opportunity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#08-surface-area-many-simultaneous-problems-&quot;&gt;Surface Area (Many Simultaneous Problems)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#09-threshold-breaks&quot;&gt;Threshold Breaks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#10-speed-of-execution-project-selection-&quot;&gt;Speed of Execution (Project Selection)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#11-effectiveness-first&quot;&gt;Effectiveness First&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The series is full of interesting insights tied around a common purpose, and I
thought it was important enough to deserve a one-page summary. I still encourage
you to read the original, especially for the vivid historical comparisons that I
often had to cut for the sake of brevity. I&amp;#39;ve put a link to the original at the
start of the summary for each issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Celerity is as much a character trait as it as actual speed. Some people are
regularly able to do things much more quickly than others, and those people tend
– unsurprisingly – to get a lot more done in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advantages to Celerity are fairly straightforward – there&amp;#39;s many things in
life that are worth doing. By accomplishing them faster, you can do more of what
matters to you. Even when you have things that aren&amp;#39;t particularly meaningful
but which you&amp;#39;re somewhat stuck doing (admin, paperwork, taxes) – getting them
done as quickly as possible frees you back up to get on with what matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you analyze where speed actually comes from, it usually isn&amp;#39;t just trying
harder to &amp;quot;go faster&amp;quot; – the Mongol horse archers, for instance, typically rode
with 3-4 horses per soldier. Their famous speed didn&amp;#39;t come from whipping the
horses to ride harder and having them break down, but from changing horses
regularly on the journey and traveling light with very little supplies needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way to gain celerity – to become fast-as-a-character-trait – is often about
small variables and far-upstream decisions that often might not seem to relate
much to speed at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It can be a little counterintuitive. You can&amp;#39;t just will &amp;quot;I want to go faster&amp;quot; –
without the relevant design, infrastructure, and thinking that allows you to go
faster. Of course, this makes perfect sense when you think it through, write it
down, and read it – but most people don&amp;#39;t think it through, write it down, or
read it; most people also don&amp;#39;t go very fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cultivation of celerity isn&amp;#39;t raw speed. Hastening your way to a loss is not
celerity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world is a marvelous and amazing place – there&amp;#39;s so many things worth doing.
Building speed into your thinking and character is worthwhile – it can then be
flexibly deployed into getting whatever you want. But first and foremost, you
have to figure out what&amp;#39;s worth moving fast towards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;01-frenzied-genius-suppression-&quot;&gt;01. Frenzied Genius (Suppression)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://us2.campaign-archive2.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=84efa10a86&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impulse or impetus – the arising of an urge or cue to go do things. We&amp;#39;re
feeling these all the time. There&amp;#39;s hunger, or the need to go to the bathroom;
likewise, remembering an old friend out of the blue and wanting to write them a
note, or remembering some recent event and wanting to learn the facts of it –
like who won the recent Dutch election?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppression or control effect – the overriding or contextualizing of an impulse
or behavior we desire to do. We put diapers on very small children because they
can&amp;#39;t suppress the desire to discharge their bowels after feeling that impulse.
Likewise, concentration involves suppressing urges to look up who won the recent
Dutch election if we&amp;#39;re doing important work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...] One hears – one does not seek; one takes--one does not ask who gives: a thought
suddenly flashes up like lightning, it comes with necessity, unhesitatingly – &lt;em&gt;I
have never had any choice in the matter.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;– Friedrich Nietzsche&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quote illustrates something close to maximum anti-suppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The right amount of personal suppression is a tricky thing. Nietzsche had strong
opinions on this, talking about how art, at its best, involved a blend of the
influences of the gods Apollo and Dionysus – Apollo being law, order, and
control; Dionysus being chaos, disorder, liberation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting the precise right amount of suppression is tricky. An inability to make
unique or new works of art, to evaluate and weigh the merits of controversial
ideas – heck, an inability to take social or interpersonal risks come as a
result of suppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we procrastinate, it can come from either side of impulse and suppression –
it might be that we have impulses that we fail to suppress; or it might be that
we feel a generalized weight against doing whatever action occurs to us, and we
don&amp;#39;t follow it through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reputation and punishments increase suppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Travelling, intoxicants (alcohol), ill health and near death experiences
decrease suppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche went frenzied notably because he ruined his reputation, travelled
constantly, used opium heavily and had a very poor health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche&amp;#39;s ability to produce an immense amount in a frenzied manic genius only
was possible because he built a huge background of knowledge and skill – he had
10-15 years of constant and diligent thinking and scholarship before he flipped
the switch and began to act in a more frenzied way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If Nietzsche had been max-anti-suppression from the age of 14, he would have
accomplished &lt;em&gt;nothing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be natural to ask if it was worth it, but who cares? Most of us won&amp;#39;t
choose Nietzsche&amp;#39;s path. He broke down mentally at only 44 years old. There are
many diagnoses, but there is no doubt that the way he lived must have
exacerbated the condition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nietzsche wrote the frist draft of &amp;quot;Thus Spoke Zarathustra&amp;quot; in 10 days. In 10
days, Nietzsche wrote one of the most important 100 pages in modern history.
Most people won&amp;#39;t ever have a run of 10 days like those. Who has? Winston
Churchill? Mustafa Kemal? But these are war leaders. Who, in peace, has 10 days
like Nietzsche&amp;#39;s best 10 days? These 10 days were hundreds of time more
productive than 10 solid productive days for most people. And yet the cost is
too high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it&amp;#39;s somewhat abstract and the exact patterns of implementation are very
personal, &lt;u&gt;thinking through what mix of suppression is in your life long-term
(culture, society, reputation) and short-term (habits, consumption, intoxicants,
training, sleep schedules, behavior, escapism) can easily unlock 3%, 5%,
10%, or much higher gains on a regular basis.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;02-power-laws-exponential-growth-&quot;&gt;02. Power Laws (Exponential Growth)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://us2.campaign-archive2.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=88438f54c4&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compound interest is an exponential growth rate, not a fixed linear amount of
growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exponential growth rates can be a lot better, but humans are bad at naturally
understanding them. The human brain, it seems, is just not well-primed to
understand how exponential growth diverges so heavily from linear growth. If you
get 10% on $100, you get $159.37 in 10 years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s better – it&amp;#39;s, well, it&amp;#39;s 59% higher. But it&amp;#39;s not shockingly better in
absolute terms; the brain naturally tends to fail to notice the huge tidal wave
of gains that&amp;#39;s about to hit. In 20 years, the fixed growth gets +$200; the
compounded growth gets +$572.75… and it keeps growing. 30 years is +$300 or
+$1644.94.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe compound interest is boring to people because 20 or 30 years seems like a
long time. But the thing is, compounding exponential gains can happen on any
timeframe – in startups, Paul Graham advocates for looking for compound business
growth on a weekly basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Norswap&amp;#39;s note: If you grow at X% per time unit, it will take you ~70/X time
units to double your capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If instead you had a new business making $100 per week (which is a measly $5200
per year), and you grew your revenues 10% per week, you&amp;#39;d make only $110 in week
two… but at week 31, you&amp;#39;d be making $1744.94 per week – or over $90,000 per
year. In just 30 weeks. That&amp;#39;s pretty exciting. Most of us can get excited about
that kind of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Three forces are arrayed against long-term compounding exponential growth:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Carrying capacity&lt;/strong&gt;: at some point, everyone in the whole world will own an
iPhone and every city will have a lot of Starbucks locations, and then growth
will slow down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operations and scaling&lt;/strong&gt;: things seem to get harder to manage, or at
least different, as they get bigger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;People don&amp;#39;t search out for exponential growth opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not just that if you want to succeed in some domain, you have to
understand the forces driving it. Understanding growth is what starting a
startup consists of. What you&amp;#39;re really doing (and to the dismay of some
observers, all you&amp;#39;re really doing) when you start a startup is committing to
solve a harder type of problem than ordinary businesses do. You&amp;#39;re committing
to search for one of the rare ideas that generates rapid growth. Because these
ideas are so valuable, finding one is hard. The startup is the embodiment of
your discoveries so far. Starting a startup is thus very much like deciding to
be a research scientist: you&amp;#39;re not committing to solve any specific problem;
you don&amp;#39;t know for sure which problems are soluble; but you&amp;#39;re committing to
try to discover something no one knew before. A startup founder is in effect
an economic research scientist. Most don&amp;#39;t discover anything that remarkable,
but some discover relativity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- Paul Graham&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Howard Schultz (Starbucks) saw an opportunity for premium-priced coffee in nice
locations, and saw that it was largely unfilled. As soon as he realized that his
stores were profitable, he raced to expand Starbucks at the fastest rate that he
could without having operations and management break down. He succeeded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s the game right here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic math&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Basic logic and thinking-through implications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Constant testing and experimenting to search for exponential growth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2g99bQw&quot;&gt;Traction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; has some great practical guides on how to do it in
entrepreneurship, and just about all of &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.to/2g99bQw&quot;&gt;Paul Graham&amp;#39;s essays&lt;/a&gt; are worth reading –
these are good starting points to start thinking about it more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;03-attrition-and-maneuver&quot;&gt;03. Attrition and Maneuver&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://us2.campaign-archive1.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=52ccee734c&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue explores the difference between taking an attrition approach or a
maneuver approach – both in warfare, and in general life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attrition is wearing down an opponent or a challenge through sheer and repeated
force: &amp;quot;charging the machine guns&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maneuver warfare is slightly less straightforward – it involves assessing
critical points in the enemy and reaching those at the lowest possible cost
using speed, surprise, and innovation. The general idea is go around the most
heavily defended points of the enemy and strike as what&amp;#39;s vulnerable – if
successful, this comes at much lower cost and much greater efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theory is straightforward. Go around the machine guns instead of charging
the machine guns. The practice is much harder, for two reasons –&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The concept seems unnatural and unintuitive to humans. Overwhelmingly, the
first instinct and response of humans to problems seems to be to charge them
head on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s often very straightforward how to fight along established lines and
conventions, whereas it&amp;#39;s almost always non-obvious how to successfully
maneuver around strong points effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue focuses on the first problem: the concept seems unnatural. Further
issues (in particular 4, 5, 6, 7 and 9) will expound on the factors that make or
break the maneuver approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the errors of attrition warfare can be attributed to two in-built flaws
typical to humans – fixation and sunk cost effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fixation&lt;/strong&gt; is becoming obsessed with a particular thing. Exemple: During the
Gettysburg battle, general Robert E. Lee believed he was close to a victory (by
the third day, he wasn&amp;#39;t) and that he needed a victory there (he didn&amp;#39;t). He
thus turned a minor loss into a very bad loss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A counter example for fixation: During the second Punic War, Roman general
Scipio Africanus ignored Hannibal entirely and focused on weaker commanders in
Carthage&amp;#39;s power base in Spain, and then invaded North Africa and launched some
very effective surprise raids against Carthage. The Romans never beat Hannibal
in the field in Italy, but he was recalled and had to leave Italy by maneuvering
around his local superiority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunk costs&lt;/strong&gt; magnify the effects – during WW2, both the Allied naval assault
and amphibious landings at Gallipoli had a chance to succeed when they were
launched with speed and surprise, but after the Ottoman Turks had defended the
initial assaults, the Allies and British in particular became very concerned
about &amp;quot;prestige&amp;quot; – thus they kept reinforcing an objectively terrible position
with more and more troops, slowly pouring units into Gallipoli in terrible
unsanitary positions, overlooked by well-defended Turkish positions. Eventually,
they left Gallipoli not with a minor defeat, but with one of the worst defeats
in British history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious thing to do in most situations is the obvious thing – but the
obvious thing is also often the most expensive in terms of material resources
and psychology. The victories in such situations are the most expensive and
exhausting – Pyrrhic victories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The human tendency is to attrition-away at problems, both in military operations
and in everyday life. The temptation is to see a large problem and go right
after it, fixating on it, and thus being denied the potential to see more
creative and less expensive ways around and through the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunk cost effects multiply the problems – once failure starts to set in, human
nature is often to throw more and more force after it, turning small defeats
into outright catastrophes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these, of course, are devastating to celerity – speed is not achieved by
focusing on an intractable and brutally expensive problem and attritioning away
at it forever; it&amp;#39;s achieved by spotting more cost-effective and innovative ways
around problems to get at gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;04-cohesion&quot;&gt;04. Cohesion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://us2.campaign-archive2.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=3d65015952&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why have so many wars throughout history bogged down into attrition warfare?
After all, the long historical record has shown maneuver-oriented commanders to
be much more successful (e.g. Hannibal, Julius Caesar and Napoleon Bonaparte).
Meanwhile, attrition warfare always came at exceedingly high cost even in
victory, and often led even the stronger side to horrific defeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partially this can be attributed to human nature – as discussed last issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet... often, there would be voices of insight and innovation within a camp
that would nevertheless up taking a disastrous approach. The challenge is,
holding firm to a non-obvious plan is hard to do when human factors get in the
way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To gain the gains and advantages of speed through creativity and unorthodox
approaches, you need &lt;strong&gt;cohesion&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to make a genuinely innovative plan succeed, there are a number of
factors you need – the first we could call sociotechnical alignment, meaning
having people, technology, and resources work effectively together. This will be
discussed in the next issue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But once you understand your capabilities and are well-trained in them, a few
more things are required:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;See the problem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unit cohesion: the ability for multiple people to execute together&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speed, especially around windows of opportunity (cf. issue 7)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cohesion: getting every element of strategy, timing, people, technology,
goals, and leadership working together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two historical examples: Germany&amp;#39;s Schleiffen Plan during WW1, and the British
assault on Gallipoli during WW2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Schleiffen Plan called for the germans to fight defensively, with minimal
forces, against the Russians on the eastern front. The goal was to deploy almost
all their forces against France on the western front, and knock it out of the
war as quickly as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Schleiffen Plan had called for both sacrifice and surprise. Sacrifice, in
that the Russians would have been able to do a lot of damage in the east as the
price for pouring all of the German Empire&amp;#39;s soldiers into France. This is also
precisely why it would be surprising. But general Moltke couldn&amp;#39;t do it; or at
least, didn&amp;#39;t do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British made similar errors at Gallipoli. The high command had been willing
to sacrifice up to a dozen obsolete warships to knock the Ottoman Empire out of
the war. But the Admiral leading the attack was not fully onboard with the plan;
he was unwilling to sacrifice the ships. In the end, half of the ships were lost
and the Ottoman Empire was still in the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The British followed up the mistake by landing not-enough troops on the
Gallipoli Peninsula. It was enough soldiers to lose in a drawn-out and brutal
fashion, not enough to break through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see that this, too, becomes a sort of fixation. The Schleiffen Plan and the
Gallipoli Naval Operations were both innovative maneuver-oriented plans. They
were surprising and audacious. Neither plan was committed to enough to succeed,
due to different incentives and indecision. As such, both plans were run
uncohesively and led to disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a bunch of political stakeholders have different personal goals, and
different traditions and preferences, plans get butchered and halfway-ran, which
is often worse than running no plan at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you&amp;#39;re working solo on your endeavors, there&amp;#39;s no doubt that we often
get conflicted within ourselves – a desire for making large gains on one hand,
for instance, and for not looking stupid on the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;No matter how innovative or good your plans are, it&amp;#39;s essential to be fully
committed in the execution in them, and to have provisioned enough resources to
them.&lt;/u&gt; This requires having all the people involved getting on the same page, and
making require sacrifices. There&amp;#39;s often major breakthroughs possible – but it&amp;#39;s
often not possible to make major breakthroughs simultaneously with doing a dozen
other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;05-sociotechnical-alignment&quot;&gt;05. Sociotechnical Alignment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://us2.campaign-archive2.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=e314c0b65e&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In WW2, the first big initial innovation was the breach-loading rifle. It was
easier to reload, even when prone, and became cheap to produce due to the
industrial revolution. This means soldier could be trained in a matter of days,
resulting in a large amount of soldiers available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second big innovation was more low key: it was the barbed wire. It
completely stopped cavalry charges in war, and it took infantrymen a substantial
amount of time to navigate it safely. Barbed wire in front of a trench, guarded
by men with breach-loading rifles, was nearly impossible to approach with any
chance of survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whichever side was attacking was, almost without fail, going to take more
losses. Unlike the old times, taking a fortified position meant little: the
ennemy could build one just like it a bit further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two sides went on to develop two very different innovations to deal with
this new reality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Germans went on to develop modern infiltration tactics. For this, they
trained shock troopers equipped with a large number of grenades to overwhelm the
ennemy, often after an artillery barrage. It was also possible to avoid strong
points to pass behind ennemy lines, then navigate to the position where it was
possible to do the most damage. Afterwards, conventional troops could clean up
isolated pockets of ennemy forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The allies, on the other hand, developped the tank to break through trenches.
Sebastian speculates it would have gone on to win the war had the armistice not
been signed. On the other hand, German innovation had come close to breaking the
front in the late stages of the war.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Germans developped a soft technology, the allies a hard one. Hard
technologies are material innovations, while soft technologies are systems,
hierarchies, processes, management methods. Typically, the second is overlooked
in favour of the first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both the largest opportunities and the largest perils in any era come from
technological evolution – both hard technologies and soft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When technology improves, it seems like the default human reaction is to try to
do whatever happened in the past in a stronger and bigger way using the new
technology. Indeed, the initial movements of World War I looked something like a
larger and more destructive high-technology version of the Napoleonic Wars from
100 years previous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sociotechnical systems in organizational development is an approach to complex
organizational work design that recognizes the interaction between people and
technology in workplaces. […] sociotechnical theory is about joint
optimization, that is, designing the social system and technical system in
tandem so that they work smoothly together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, &lt;u&gt;sociotechnical alignment is all about making hard and soft
technologies work in tandem&lt;/u&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To navigate any situation well, you need to discern the universal principles
that apply, as well as what specifics have recently changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When setting up sociotechnical systems, there are two things you should look out
for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When something that was formerly expensive becomes inexpensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;When something that formerly required high skill to accomplish can later be
achieved with low or no skill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You shouldn&amp;#39;t stop there, though – you should next ask yourself what soft
technologies and different objectives would pair with the now-cheaper hard
technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting into alignment as such is where a lot of celerity comes from – when
you&amp;#39;re operating with the right technologies, with the right tactics, and aiming
for goals and objectives that are only possible with new combinations, you can
greatly outpace those who do not adopt such measures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;06-pace-maximum-vs-maximum-sustainable-speed-&quot;&gt;06. Pace (Maximum vs Maximum Sustainable Speed)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://us2.campaign-archive.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=0c0cad8377&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s the maximum possible pace, which is going as all-out fast as possible,
and which is typically sustainable only for a brief time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;#39;s the maximum sustainable pace, which is going at a rate that doesn&amp;#39;t
deplete your capabilities faster than you can replenish them. It&amp;#39;s worth working
towards reaching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can red-line and put in all-nighters with no sleep, consume heavy amounts of
stimulants and simple carbohydrates for energy, neglect recharging and
maintenance activities like leisure and fitness, and in doing this, you can do a
much greater amount of work in a short period of time than you could if you were
running at a sustainable pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you ever red-line yourself?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a variety of smart opinions on this. One opinion is that being forced to
red-line is an error attributable to poor upstream planning. Another view is
that red-lining occasionally, going closer to the maximum possible pace, is
insightful in that it demonstrates what&amp;#39;s possible in a crisis and gives you a
better awareness of your capabilities under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A possible plan is to red-lining two or three times per year – say, once by
choice, and responding to two crises or large emergent opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One shouldn&amp;#39;t intentionally red-line too often, because it puts you in a fragile
and dangerous state following the red-lining. If a major opportunity or crisis
happens shortly after you&amp;#39;ve red-lined, you&amp;#39;re ill-equipped to handle it. Better
to red-line defensively and opportunistically rather than intentionally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Issue 9 will deal with threshold breaks, but for now, suffice to say that it&amp;#39;s
one of the times that red-lining truly makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often, there&amp;#39;s a threshold that, if you pass it, it makes a huge difference. If
you&amp;#39;re going much faster than the maximum sustainable pace, you should know in
advance when you can end it and recover from the damage you took. When there&amp;#39;s a
logical and obvious threshold or checkpoint to hit, this can help immensely. You
red-line to get past a threshold of wins or gains, and then recover afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;07-windows-of-opportunity&quot;&gt;07. Windows of Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mailchi.mp/thestrategicreview/tsr-celerity-7-windows-of-opportunity?e=0264c979a5&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seize opportunities when they present themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julius Caesar was certainly one of the figures in history who cultivated the
most celerity – he moved quickly in all things, usually to his advantage. When
the Senate threatened to make him a public enemy if he did not disband his
legions, he crossed the Rubicon. He suppressed Pompey&amp;#39;s loyalists in Spain
rapidly, and then moved to bring the fight to Pompey in Greece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;A large part of the cultivation of celerity is in seizing opportunities,
especially during a window when large gains can be made quickly and safely.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, major windows of opportunity are almost always going to
come with some measure of fear. Almost by definition, it&amp;#39;ll be something unusual
or surprising. &amp;quot;Is this really possible... ? Could I really... ?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect this can be trained, to some extent, by rapidly moving on small
opportunities. Seeing an opportunity to go to a conference, or speak at an event
on short notice if one of the speakers dropped out, or traveling to a city to
meet someone you find admirable on short notice. Some people naturally move very
fast; most people do not. The ability to cut through fear and move quickly can
be trained, probably in small and low-stakes situations. You could arbitrarily
pick any unfamiliar event this weekend and attend it. That&amp;#39;s a very unusual
pattern for most people, but it can help for getting over fear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that said, a brief caution around impatience and impulsiveness. One of the
most dangerous things is when you spot an opportunity as it&amp;#39;s developing, barely
miss it, and then jump into the fray late – it&amp;#39;s a common human error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re reasonably sure a company&amp;#39;s stock is going to go up because it&amp;#39;s doing
well, but you neglect to buy it, and then you see it rapidly double or triple –
a lot of people then jump in late, annoyed at themselves and neglecting to take
the gain, and buy after the gains have happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;08-surface-area-many-simultaneous-problems-&quot;&gt;08. Surface Area (Many Simultaneous Problems)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://us2.campaign-archive2.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=1c455f2537&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are no quest logs in real life: you need to make your own, and seek worhty
missions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As individuals, there&amp;#39;s only so much progress we can make at a given time. The
last and fundamental limit becomes the fact that we only have 168 hours per week
– even if doing everything else perfectly, we eventually run into this limit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But practically speaking, oftentimes people get &amp;quot;bogged down&amp;quot; far before hitting
that limit, and often it&amp;#39;s only time or random feats of inspiration that break
through. Renowned scientists and mathematicians would often get stuck on a
particular problem for months or years before finally making a breakthrough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution, then, is self-evident: learn about how to develop a greater
surface area of opportunities in our own lives. Seek more worthy missions. They
provide you with work to make progress on when you&amp;#39;re bogged down, and might
just provide you with the inspiration you need to break through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More surface area (good people, interesting problems, new skills and techniques)
lead to accomplishing more in life easier and faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People often view games as the opposite of work, but some sociologists believe
games are an idealized form of work. &amp;quot;Most people find work rewarding; we have
built-in emotional reward centers that encourage us to complete tasks&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At their most basic levels, work and play look a lot alike. The difference
between the two is that games couch this kind of work in a fiction that makes
them enjoyable. A game&amp;#39;s narrative makes our choices feel significant enough
that we buy into the game emotionally, and the feedback system encourages us to
keep working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Games are more consistent at rewarding us for the choices we make and are
immediately rewarding, providing instant feedback when we do something right,
and telling us how well we perform every step along the way. These highly tuned
feedback systems are the key to turning video games into an indispensable tool
for bettering our future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;About the mathematician Paul Erdos:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But for me his even greater importance is that he created a large number of
mathematicians. He was the problem poser par excellence. His ability to
formulate problems of any level of difficulty is legendary. Many people can
ask questions which are impossibly difficult or trivially easy. It is given to
few of us to tread the narrow path between triviality and unattainability.
Erdos problems were not Hilbert problems, which took half a century or more to
settle. Erdos questions were always just right. So often, when we are fumbling
with our research, it is because we are not asking the right question. Many of
Erdos&amp;#39;s questions have remained as outstanding but important problems, but
most have been attacked and partially, or perhaps completely, solved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Erdos not only asked the right question. He asked them of the right
person. He knew better than you yourself knew what you were capable of. How
many people must have got started on research by solving a $5.00, or maybe
even a $1.00, Erdos problem? He gave the confidence that many of us needed to
embark on mathematical research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He had the unique ability to identify problems which were just beyond what you
could currently do. It&amp;#39;s easy to state impossible problems but he would state
a problem whereby if you could solve this problem you would then know more
than you knew before and open the door wider. It was like climbing a mountain
and being able to drive one more piton in to be able to work your way up the
mountain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By working on the right problems, the right missions, you can build up your
confidence and knowledge to tackle increasingly ambitious tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;09-threshold-breaks&quot;&gt;09. Threshold Breaks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mailchi.mp/thestrategicreview/tsr-celerity-9-threshold-breaks?e=0264c979a5&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a closely-matched fight, whichever side breaks and flees first loses, and
often takes more casualties during retreat than they took in the fight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an example of a threshold break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;u&gt;A key aspect for celerity is understanding threshold and checkpoints. That is,
being able to recognize what targets you should sprint towards to collect large
amounts of gains.&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But moving fast towards no objective doesn&amp;#39;t get you any results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one&amp;#39;s own life, it pays to be assess where the next set of major gains are
and to devote as many resources as possible towards breaking through to those
gains. Bravado, stubbornness, or a lack of reasoning about where those threshold
breaks are will lead – at best – to middling results, and at worst to disaster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mull over it some – many people work very hard and diligently, but do not
analyze where the next round of major breakthroughs will come from. Thus, their
efforts are diffused and they never reach the next levels and thresholds of
success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thinking, analysis, and emotional fortitude are ever and always required to get
focused on what really matters and stay focused on what really matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-speed-of-execution-project-selection-&quot;&gt;10. Speed of Execution (Project Selection)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://us2.campaign-archive.com/?u=6b601ddd13ae676e0c4d8b6a2&amp;amp;id=9d6e5ec7ad&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A majority of Sebastian&amp;#39;s solo successes were &amp;quot;burst/incremental&amp;quot; projects that
were released in little pieces. He also noted that his collaborations tended to
succeed much more than his solo endeavours (about 90% vs 50% success rate).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a response, he started drastically cut down the number of solo projects he
did, and started looking to be more collaborative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From his perspective, it helped him immensely because before taking that
decision, many of his projects had been a mix of &amp;quot;too unclear&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;too clever&amp;quot;
in the initial setup and scoping of the project, and that had set him up for
failure as projects would get too complicated to ship out the door.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When engaging in collaborations, the collaborator would catch these excessive
complications as they were hammering out a scope of things to do, and they&amp;#39;d
simplify the project scope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Burst/Incremental type of work tended to succeed more often because of two
reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Regular progress got made with lots of mini-deadlines getting clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Feedback from the incremental/burst work was gotten and course corrections
could be made before getting oneself into a dead end of being stuck on some
large too-clever mess of a project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sebastian&amp;#39;s business partner, Kai Zau, emphasizes project selection as the most
crucial part of getting high project success rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He came up with two criterions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is the project &amp;quot;goldilocks-sized&amp;quot;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can the project be completed within the &amp;quot;project honeymoon window&amp;quot;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pick a project too small, and you won&amp;#39;t get enough gain. Too big and it could
fail or be a huge hassle to succeed with the costs outstripping the gains.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s better to finish a project while it is still fresh, exciting and
motivating. It should be complete within a few weeks or more rarely a few
months. It doesn&amp;#39;t feel good to have a project that lingers on. Complete the
project and collect the gains before things get stale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to complete his projects as fast as possible, Sebastian uses a
spreadsheet. For each active project he records:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the start date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the number of days elapsed since the start date&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the number of days spent working on the project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the ratio between days spend working on the project and days elapsed (as a percentage)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal is to minimize the number of days elapsed before completion, and of
course the best way to do this is to minimize the &amp;quot;advance percentage&amp;quot; (the
ratio).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, Sebastian&amp;#39;s recommendation for improving speed of execution –
completing more projects successfully in less time – boil down to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Generally sound good work habits (covered elsewhere)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Careful project selection&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Minimizing the days elapsed from the time a project starts until it completes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maximizing the advance percentage – how many days you worked on a project while
it was active, towards concluding it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you have multiple ongoing projects, you&amp;#39;re better off taking a single
day to march one of them to completion than to &amp;quot;make a bit of progress&amp;quot; on all
of them. There is actually some research/math on project payoffs and decay rates
that supports this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;11-effectiveness-first&quot;&gt;11. Effectiveness First&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mailchi.mp/thestrategicreview/tsr-celerity-11-effectiveness-first?e=0264c979a5&quot;&gt;🔗 original issue&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing so useless as doing efficiently that which should not be done
at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;– Peter Drucker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our investigation so far, we looked at different aspects of celerity. A large
part of it is sizing up the world correctly – thus, knowing of Power Laws and
how to analyze them and hone in on them is important; likewise, being able to
spot windows of opportunity, emerging technical and sociotechnical trends, and
key potential threshold breaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-management is key – we explored the difference between the maximum possible
pace and the maximum sustainable pace, and we honed in on specific instances of
each – looking at Paul Erdos and his surface area approach for an example of max
sustainable pace, and Friedrich Nietzsche&amp;#39;s frenzied genius for an example of
the maximum-possible-pace with its great rewards but also heavy downsides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last issue, we looked at raw speed of execution – with the perhaps
counterintuitive idea that project selection might be the key determinant of
speed of execution. Working in &amp;quot;goldilocks-sized&amp;quot; chunks of work and aiming to
get key initiatives done in the &amp;quot;honeymoon window&amp;quot; greatly helps with attaining
a higher speed of execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But at the end of the day, all of the raw Celerity in the world isn&amp;#39;t worth much
if deployed into the wrong areas – and so we end our series with an exploration
of some of Peter Drucker&amp;#39;s ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be reasonably effective it is not enough for the individual to be
intelligent, to work hard or to be knowledgeable. Effectiveness is some thing
separate, something different. But to be effective also does not require special
gifts, special aptitude, or special training. Effectiveness as an executive
demands doing certain — and fairly simple — things. Effectiveness can be learned
— and it also has to be learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speed is, broadly, a good thing. But rapidly dispatching and achieving a set of
things that results in nothing, that adds nothing to the world or one&amp;#39;s own life
– this is folly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Effectiveness before efficiency: going somewhere before going fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brilliant men are often strikingly ineffectual; they fail to realize that the
brilliant insight is not by itself achievement. They never have learned that
insights become effectiveness only through hard systematic work. Conversely, in
every organization there are some highly effective plodders. While others rush
around in the frenzy and busyness which very bright people so often confuse with
&amp;quot;creativity,&amp;quot; the plodder puts one foot in front of the other and gets there
first, like the tortoise in the old fable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How to become effective?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perform a &lt;a href=&quot;https://praxis.fortelabs.co/theory-of-constraints-101-table-of-contents-8bbb6627915b&quot;&gt;Theory of Constraints&lt;/a&gt;-type analysis. It will help you find the
area where work is needed in order to hit maximum performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Answer the question &amp;quot;What needs to be done?&amp;quot; (not &amp;quot;What do I want to do?&amp;quot;).
The answer almost always contains more than one urgent task. But effective
executives do not splinter themselves. They concentrate on one task if at all
possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drucker: &amp;quot;I have never encountered an executive who remains effective while
tackling more than two tasks at a time.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of both effectiveness and celerity, whatever is the most important
thing should be focused on to the maximal extent possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems common sense, but most people either don&amp;#39;t know what their most
important thing is or are not making routine progress on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I know what the most important thing is?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I focusing on that to the maximal extent possible?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2017-11-25T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/celerity</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/celerity</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple Math: Trade Rates</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;While I was driving on the highway the other day, I was thinking: &amp;quot;how much time
would I shave off if I drove at 150 km/h instead of at 120 km/h?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems like that should have a very simple answer, but I wasn&amp;#39;t able to come
up with it immediately. Here are insights I gained after thinking a bit more
about that question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;trade-rates&quot;&gt;Trade Rates&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First off, let us state that speed is a trade rate. From a human perspective,
speed allows you to trade time for distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general a trade rate is a ratio &lt;code&gt;X/Y&lt;/code&gt; that states how much of a thing A we
can trade for a thing B:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; X   A
--- --- = 1
 Y   B

X A = Y B
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;So naturally, 120 km/h allows us to trade an hour for 120 kilometers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;trade-rates-multiplications&quot;&gt;Trade Rates Multiplications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going from 120 km/h to 150 km/h, we add 30 km/h. That is precisely the quartier
of the base speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hence: 150 = 120 * (1 + 1/4) = 120 * 5/4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s see how this affects our trade rate equations:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; 5   120   km
--- ----- ---- = 1
 4    1    h

5 * 120 km = 4 h

150 km = 1 h
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;As expected, we can now trade one hour for 150 kilometers. But what if we want
to keep 120 km on the left side of that equation? Say we actually have to drive
for 120 km, how much time do we save?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;5 * 120 km = 4 h

120 km = 4/5 h = 38 m
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;We gained 1/5 of an hour, so 12 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s interesting: we increased our speed by a quarter, but only reduced the
time by a fifth. This is actually more intuitive when the numbers become larger:
double your speed, halve the required time, which corresponds to +100% speed for
-50% time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The thing to keep in mind is that we&amp;#39;re messing with the &lt;em&gt;trade rate&lt;/em&gt;. Given a
fixed speed, time and distance mirror one another: double the distance, double
the time, and vice-versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting thing: by multiplying the speed by 5/4, keeping the distance
fixed, we ended up multiplying the time by 4/5. The symmetry between those
numbers is not random. In fact we can generalize.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we multiply a trade rate &lt;code&gt;X/Y&lt;/code&gt; with units &lt;code&gt;A/B&lt;/code&gt; by a fraction &lt;code&gt;u/z&lt;/code&gt;, then either:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can trade &lt;code&gt;u/z&lt;/code&gt; times the A for the same amount of B.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can trade &lt;code&gt;z/u&lt;/code&gt; times the B for the same amount of A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The math is fairly simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; u   X   A
--- --- --- = 1
 z   Y   B

 u
--- X A = Y B
 z
       z
X A = --- Y B
       u
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;trade-rates-increases&quot;&gt;Trade Rates Increases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can think about this in another way. Multiplying the speed by 5/4 was
actually multiplying it by (1 + 1/4), so we can see this as an 1/4 increase in
speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly, when your speed increase by one quarter, you can drive one quarter more
kilometers in an hour.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s less intuitive from the other side: when your speed increases by 1/4, how
much does the time spent decrease? We already know the answer is 1/5, but how to
find this without going through the whole development?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we need a side property.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side Property: Numerator Swap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I have no idea how this property is called in reality, or whether it even has a name)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;   X             Y
------- = 1 - -------
 X + Y         X + Y
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;Proof:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;   X       X + Y     X + Y       X
------- = ------- - ------- + -------  (1)
 X + Y     X + Y     X + Y     X + Y

                 Y
        = 1 - -------                  (2)
               X + Y
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In (1) we simply add and remove &lt;code&gt;(X+Y)/(X+Y)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In (2), the first term becomes 1, while the &lt;code&gt;X&lt;/code&gt; in the second and third terms
have different signs and cancel each other out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End Side Property&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay so we wanted to know how to get that 1/5 diminution in time from the 1/4
(&lt;code&gt;u/z&lt;/code&gt; if we abstract) increase in speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is the development:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;      u    X   A
(1 + ---) --- --- = 1
      z    Y   B

 z + u
------- X A = Y B           (1)
   z

         z
X A = ------- Y B           (2)
       z + u

              u
X A = (1 - -------) Y B     (3)
            z + u
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;In (1), we pass &lt;code&gt;Y B&lt;/code&gt; to the other side, and we replace &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; by the equivalent
&lt;code&gt;z/z&lt;/code&gt;, leading to the simplified &lt;code&gt;(z + u) / z&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In (2), we just pass that term to the other side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In (3), we use our side property and get our final form.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our speed example, &lt;code&gt;u/z = 1/4&lt;/code&gt;, so &lt;code&gt;u = 1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;z = 4&lt;/code&gt;. We can see that &lt;code&gt;u /
(z + u)&lt;/code&gt; is indeed 1/5, and as the equation shows, that is the portion that the
quantity of B gets reduced by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gist of this is: add the numerator to the denominator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1/4 &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; 1/5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2/3 &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; 2/5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;3/4 &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; 3/7&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easy peasy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;diminishing-returns&quot;&gt;Diminishing Returns&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One final interesting observation: there is a diminishing return on trade rate
increase (assuming you&amp;#39;re on the right side of the equation).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is obvious with speed. Double the speed, halve the time spent to go the
same distance. Double the speed again, halve the time again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine our base speed is 60 km/h and we have precisely 60 km to go until our
destination. If we change our speed to 120 km/h, we gain 30 minutes in travel
time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if we were driving at 120 km/h, and we change our speed to 240 km/h, we only
gain 15 minutes (half of our 30 minutes travel time at 120 km/h).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you&amp;#39;re driving at 60 km/h, and you add 60 km/h, you gain 30 minutes. But
if you immediately add 120 km/h more, you only gain 15 minutes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, this is because we&amp;#39;re changing the rate. Given a fixed speed, adding more
time will yield a linear increase in distance travelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s it for today. Drive safe!&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2017-11-17T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/trade-rates</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/trade-rates</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
