<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
  <channel>
    <title>norswap</title>
    <description></description>      
    <link>http://norswap.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://norswap.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2021 Compiler Class Live</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;This year, I&amp;#39;m teaching a master-level compiler class at &lt;a href=&quot;https://uclouvain.be/&quot;&gt;Université catholique
de Louvain&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course is now live &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLOech0kWpH8-njQpmSNGSiQBPUvl8v3IM&quot;&gt;on YouTube&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve also created &lt;a href=&quot;/compilers&quot;&gt;a new page&lt;/a&gt; on this website intended to collect all
informations about the course.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-02-06T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/compiler-class-2021</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/compiler-class-2021</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chosen Tidbits 7</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-1/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-2/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-3/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-4/&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-5/&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-6/&quot;&gt;Six&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://habitatchronicles.com/2004/04/you-cant-tell-people-anything/&quot;&gt;You Can&amp;#39;t Tell People Anything&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s going on is that without some kind of direct experience to use as a
touchstone, people don’t have the context that gives them a place in their
minds to put the things you are telling them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The things you say often don&amp;#39;t stick, and the few things that do stick are often
distorted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, most people aren&amp;#39;t very good at visualizaing hypothetitcals, at imagining
what something they haven&amp;#39;t experienced might be like if it were somewhat
different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Drawing might help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you create things that you can keep on the market at a very low cost
(including your time), you almost cannot fail. Worst case scenario is a slow
success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your running costs are high, time becomes your enemy. Your profits must
beat the clock, or you go bust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When your running costs are negligible, time becomes your friend. You cannot go
bust, and the passage of time exposes you to luck 24/7.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dvassallo/status/1278563747435446273&quot;&gt;Daniel Vassallo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://siderea.dreamwidth.org/1209794.html&quot;&gt;The Asshole Filter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself wondering, or just feeling, &amp;quot;Why is everyone I wind up
dealing with an asshole?&amp;quot; you might want to consider the possibility that you
have set up an asshole filter. Asshole filters are an extremely common
phenomenon, and an extremely common problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An asshole filter happens when you publicly promulgate a straitened contact
boundary and then don&amp;#39;t enforce it; or worse, reward the people who transgress
it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Example: promulgate that mails mails must go through team mail, but still answer
your private emails or even &lt;em&gt;expedite&lt;/em&gt; the requests your receive there, thereby
rewarding transgressors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://putanumonit.com/2020/07/04/kelly-bet-on-everything/&quot;&gt;Kelly Bet on Everything&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post because of my endless frustration with my friends who have
the most slack in life also being the most risk averse. They have plenty of
savings but stay in soul-sucking jobs for years. They complain about the
monotony of social life but refuse to instigate a change. They don’t travel,
don’t do drugs, don’t pick fights, don’t flirt, don’t express themselves. They
don’t want to think about kids because their lives are just so comfortable and
why would you mess with that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://devonzuegel.com/post/the-silence-is-deafening&quot;&gt;The Silence is Deafening&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Angry Alice tweets something obnoxious or unproductive, reasonable people
just scroll past it. If Alice develops a pattern of bad behavior, reasonable
people will just unfollow, mute, or block her. The result is that it&amp;#39;s hard for
Alice to notice the silent majority of people who saw the trash fire and walked
away when they recognized that engaging would only fuel its flames.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It gets worse—Angry Alice only sees feedback from extremists, so she doesn&amp;#39;t
receive more nuanced signals that might actually cause her to reflect on her
behavior. If no reasonable people give feedback, only the unreasonable people
are left. From Alice&amp;#39;s perspective, the only people who disagree with her are
jerks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a coordination problem. Reasonable people understand that if they join
the fray alone, they&amp;#39;ll most likely be drowned out by the yelling, or worse
they&amp;#39;ll get dragged deeper into it. As a result, they choose stay out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A huge part of the problem is that digital spaces generally have no equivalent
of a disapproving glare. You&amp;#39;re stuck choosing between staying silent and
entering the fray, with few options in between. If you have little reason to
believe that other reasonable people will back you up, you&amp;#39;re going to stick
with the default: silence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://extranewsfeed.com/tolerance-is-not-a-moral-precept-1af7007d6376&quot;&gt;Tolerance is Not A Moral Precept&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tolerance is not a moral precept, it&amp;#39;s a peace treaty (or at least non-agression).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One can&amp;#39;t tolerate the intolerant, that would be a suicide pact.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sonyasupposedly/status/1280903954872676352&quot;&gt;lisatomic5 on Children&amp;#39;s Rights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thread illustrates that telling your children the functional lie that they
have bodily autonomy is exhausting to stick to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yashkaf/status/1281406459855634437&quot;&gt;Fuck Victimhood Identity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is that long ago I noticed that the less I saw and presented
myself as a victim, the less I was victimized. This kicked off a virtuous
cycle that I’m not going to jeopardize. Now my life is much improved, and I’ve
developed a very strong allergy to victim identity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spiral of victim identity is incredibly seductive. Once you step in it
your identity will be reinforced by everyone around you and your own
confirmation bias. I’ve seen this spiral claim people, groups, nations. It
didn’t make them better off, and it didn’t make them better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victimhood blinds you to the suffering of others. My dating life improved when
I stopped thinking about how women malign me and became able to understand
their own fears and frustrations with guys. Before, I literally couldn’t
fathom that dating can be hard for hot young women&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victimhood blinds you to your own mistakes, the only part you can change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone wants their suffering validated, but you will never get this
validation from those who hurt you if that’s what you seek. If you let go of
this doomed desire, you may eventually find the validation you crave among
friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t have to argue about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; you’re fighting, &lt;em&gt;while&lt;/em&gt; you’re fighting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trying to do both at once is a quick way to compound your frustration with each
other and make things worse for everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smart thing to do is to schedule relationship maintenance in advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1168145452379729921&quot;&gt;Visa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nabeelqu.co/understanding&quot;&gt;How to Understand Things&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My father has zero intellectual insecurities... It has never crossed his mind
to be concerned that the world thinks he’s an idiot. He’s not in that game. So
if he doesn’t understand something, he just asks you. He doesn’t care if he
sounds foolish. He will ask the most obvious question without any sort of
concern about it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people are not willing to do this — looking stupid takes courage, and
sometimes it’s easier to just let things slide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is striking how many situations I am in where I start asking basic
questions, feel guilty for slowing the group down, and it turns out that
nobody understood what was going on to begin with (often people message me
privately saying that they’re relieved I asked), but I was the only one who
actually spoke up and asked about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://garybasin.com/one-week-project-management/&quot;&gt;One Week Project Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a big project is tricky. I usually have some sense of what needs to
be done, but my time estimates tend to be… a little off. There’s one thing
worse than underestimating the time it’ll take: doing unnecessary work. I hate
getting traction on a project only to realize that a bunch of work was wasted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a trick that often works for me: Rescope the project to complete it
within the next week. Even when unrealistic, trying to apply that tight
constraint can get you to notice things you wouldn’t otherwise. It forces me
to consider what is absolutely necessary and what can be skipped. It forces me
to spend one of my days planning so I know exactly what I need to execute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Parkinson’s Law] states that a project takes as much time as you allow it.
Once in a while, try allowing much less time than you think is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My cynical view of humanity at large informs my sympathetic view of actual
humans. By the standards of horny status-obsessed murder monkeys, even my
outgroup enemies are often doing the best they can consider the fears and
insecurities that plague them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, if you believe that humans are by nature benign and kind and
are only &amp;quot;corrupted&amp;quot; by culture, you will have a very negative view of the
prevailing culture and most people. This will tempt you to dream of revolutions
or a return to some golden age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/yashkaf/status/1284244774199988227&quot;&gt;Jacob&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2021-01-04T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-7</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-7</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stock Market Adventures: Introduction</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;In recent months, I&amp;#39;ve taken an interest in the stock market, and started
trading. Now that I&amp;#39;ve figured a few things about it, I want to share a bit of
information about how I trade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But before I get there, I want to give you the backstory of how I came to trade.
It involves many details that I find interesting &amp;amp; relevant, like index funds
and market cycles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;invest-in-etfs&quot;&gt;Invest in ETFs?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interest in the stock market started very pragmatic. I had some money set
aside, and it was gathering dust. My bank&amp;#39;s savings account nets me a 0.10%
interest, which is both a joke in poor taste, and a competitive market rate. I
needed better yield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually already knew the answer: invest in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exchange-traded_fund&quot;&gt;ETFs&lt;/a&gt; (Exchange Traded Funds), in
particular funds tracking a broad market index (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Index_fund&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;index funds&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;). The target
index could be the ever-popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/S%26P_500_Index&quot;&gt;S&amp;amp;P 500&lt;/a&gt; (indexing the 500 biggest US
companies), or if I wanted to be more diversified than just the US, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MSCI_World&quot;&gt;MSCI
World index&lt;/a&gt;, which tries to be representative of the world&amp;#39;s economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the boring-as-it-gets investment strategy. It&amp;#39;s quite safe too. Sure,
there are recessions. But the S&amp;amp;P 500 has grown historically at &amp;gt; 5% on average.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How safe is it? Pretty safe, barring a zombie apocalypse or a nuclear holocaust.
All thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/compounding.asp&quot;&gt;compounding&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled on an interesting &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pFgPNVytlwA&quot;&gt;what-if video&lt;/a&gt; the other day: &amp;quot;What if you
invested only at market peaks?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, even if you had invested a sum of 230k$ (2k$ annual payment, increased
by 2k$ every decade) &lt;strong&gt;only&lt;/strong&gt; at the peak that preceded each recession for the
period starting in 1977, you&amp;#39;d still end up with 1M$ by retirement. It bears
repeating this is the absolute worst-case scenario. If instead, you&amp;#39;d just
invested every year, you&amp;#39;d end up with 2.5M$ instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was a simple solution to my problem. But at the time, I had some
misgivings. First, the market was at an all-time high, and there was a lot of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://letstalklovetoday.wordpress.com/2017/04/01/the-definite-indefinite-optimist-and-pessimist/&quot;&gt;indefinite&lt;/a&gt; unease floating around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, since the Coronavirus crisis, more definite criticism has emerged.
Legendary investor Charlie Munger &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tO5kr0r9g58&quot;&gt;is afraid&lt;/a&gt; about record-like valuations and
inflation by means of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quantitative_easing&quot;&gt;quantitative easing&lt;/a&gt;. Other people worry about many
companies (and in particular tech companies) being valued at historically high
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/e/earningsmultiplier.asp&quot;&gt;P/E multipliers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(By the way, I&amp;#39;ve written &lt;a href=&quot;/munger/&quot;&gt;about Charlie Munger&amp;#39;s philosophy&lt;/a&gt; before.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there was a possibility that market would take a hit for ~10 years. If you
look at the S&amp;amp;P 500 chart, this is what happened after 2000. The index only
recovered in 2008, then plunged again to only recover in 2012. 0% profit over 12
years is a long time with no returns, even if the market growth has since made
up for that slump.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;sp500.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, if you look at the slope of that graph in recent years, you can
understand why people are uneasy about us being at the peak of a bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there was, maybe, a way out: you could time the market. One option is wait
for the crash to get in. The only issue is that it might be in 1 years or in 10,
and your fear of losses could end up costing you more in lost profits. Another
strategy is to sell at the start of the crash and buy back at the bottom. But
that&amp;#39;s hard to distinguish a normal retracement from a temporary panic, and from
the start of a crash. Timing the bottom is similarly not so easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also common wisdom that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w_aOERmUWdA&quot;&gt;timing the market is typically a bad
idea&lt;/a&gt;. (Just like it is it &amp;quot;common wisdom&amp;quot; that trading is ruinous.
Yet some people do both consistently and successfully. We&amp;#39;ll get back to that later.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, only one thing was clear: I had to learn more before I came out
with a plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-the-ball-rolling&quot;&gt;Getting the Ball Rolling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everything I&amp;#39;ve laid out so far had mostly been background thinking, but I&amp;#39;d
been busy with other things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally decided to give myself a shove and start doing something. An extra
motivation here was that a family member had made quite a bit of money investing
in Tesla options. Him and my brother were very bullish on the company and
claimed of a ton of upside. I found myself agreeing about that for the
short-term.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so I decided to get my feet wet with brokers, and to buy a Tesla share (1.6k$
at the time) as well as investing very small amounts in ETFs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot to be said for getting the ball rolling like this. This was a
small enough amount of money that I could afford to lose it all (and obviously,
that was almost impossible anyway), but more than enough for me to care. I
started having questions and googling around for answers, and found quite a
treasure trove of information online, in particular on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some on these videos were on active investing, and some were on trading. I
started entertaining the notion that I could make some money in this way, and I
began running some small experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;penny-stocks&quot;&gt;Penny Stocks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started buying some stocks, for no more than 200€. Because that&amp;#39;s quite a low
amount, I was driven to buy &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Penny_stock&quot;&gt;penny stocks&lt;/a&gt;. Those are also often volatile —
very risky, but potentially profitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It didn&amp;#39;t go incredibly well, but that wasn&amp;#39;t particularly unexpected. If common
wisdom treats trading like gambling, penny stocks are treated like Russian
roulette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lost some money (not too much, less than I&amp;#39;d made on my Tesla trade and on a
couple other &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/bluechipstock.asp&quot;&gt;blue-chip stock&lt;/a&gt; trades). But I did learn a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact I think&amp;#39;s it&amp;#39;s very hard to learn to trade penny stocks other than by
trading them. You can&amp;#39;t really learn anything by looking at past scenarios:
you&amp;#39;ll get a full dose of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hindsight_bias&quot;&gt;hindsight bias&lt;/a&gt;. And penny stock trading is all about
timing entries (buying) and exits (selling).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could potentially learn by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/p/papertrade.asp&quot;&gt;paper trading&lt;/a&gt;, but you need to be very
disciplined and not make any excuses like &amp;quot;I was busy with X so this trade
doesn&amp;#39;t count&amp;quot;. You&amp;#39;re still going to be busy with X when you trade your own
money — even if X is an emergency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s also a dearth of literature on the topic of penny trading. The topic is
not very conducive to theorization, but rather to some sort of
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fingerspitzengef%C3%BChl&quot;&gt;fingerspitzgefühl&lt;/a&gt; intuition. Basically, you learn to be more paranoid, and
understand the (many) ways in which a penny stock trade can go south, or at
least no go how you predicted. You also learn to manage your emotions, and cut
your losses early.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not facilitated by the fact that penny stock trading is extremely
speculative. To give you a very simple explanation, it&amp;#39;s often based around
&amp;quot;catalysts&amp;quot; that are expected to move the stock price. For instance: a drug
being approved for a pharma company. This causes the price to run up in
anticipation of the decision, and then to crash right before, or right after the
decision, as people sell to secure profits. Even if the drug was approved!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s sometimes even worse than this — there are a number of stock market pundits
running &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pump_and_dump&quot;&gt;pump and dump&lt;/a&gt; schemes. It&amp;#39;s sometimes hard to tell apart from &amp;quot;regular
speculation&amp;quot;. When a pundit with many followers hypes a stock due for a
catalyst, you get a de facto, quite unintentional, pump-and-dump. A whole new way
to &amp;quot;monetize your audience&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t find trading penny stocks to be the most pleasant activities, but I
don&amp;#39;t begrudge it either. I think it&amp;#39;s quite possible to make a consistent
profit doing so — if one is willing to be careful and learn from mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;irrational-fears&quot;&gt;Irrational Fears&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings us to an important sidebar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said before that the &amp;quot;common sense&amp;quot; opinion was that trading was ruinous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to be sure, I think that for most people, dissuading them from trading is
the correct position.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s because most people are dumb. It&amp;#39;s not a nice thing to say, and it isn&amp;#39;t
to say they&amp;#39;re not also nice and valuable people. But it&amp;#39;s true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, trading tends to attract particularly dumb people. Just have a look at
&lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/pennystocks/&quot;&gt;r/pennystocks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://old.reddit.com/r/wallstreetbets/&quot;&gt;r/wallstreetbets&lt;/a&gt;, and you&amp;#39;ll see off-the-charts stupidity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trading requires you to plan, think things through, manage risk/exposure, and,
most of all, manage your own emotions. It&amp;#39;s hard. Too hard for people that
haven&amp;#39;t developed these skills and virtues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flip side is that if you are able to do all that, trading can be a viable
avenue to generating extra money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anybody that says that &amp;quot;trading is ruinous&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;trading is too risky&amp;quot; should
feel the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_dissonance&quot;&gt;cognitive dissonance&lt;/a&gt; with the fact that they are quite a lot of people
who make a consistent profit or even a living trading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least, there should be nuance. &amp;quot;Trading is too risky for most people&amp;quot;. I
agree with that. This leads to an interesting question: what sets the successful
traders apart from the rest of us?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led to me to this interesting thought: Imagine someone that has praised you
for being smart and level-headed. But when you tell them you&amp;#39;re going to trade;
they try to dissuade you out of it. Either they&amp;#39;re thoroughly confused in the
sense outlined above, or their real opinion of you is that you&amp;#39;re not, in fact,
smart and level-headed enough to take on this endeavour. (Fortunately this
remains a hypothetical scenario for me. Nobody has thrown shade on my trading so
far).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;finally-options&quot;&gt;Finally, Options&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trading penny stocks could have been profitable, but it wasn&amp;#39;t my favourite
thing. For one, the activity has inherent uncertainty. I once saw a stock trader
that made hundreds of thousands of dollars in profit a year run the numbers on
his trading, and his trade win rate was &amp;quot;only&amp;quot; 68%. The average profit was only
~20% higher than the average loss. Considering that these wins and losses are
not distributed uniformly, it does take some mental fortitude to ride through
the highs and lows. I&amp;#39;m really risk-averse, and even though I think I can muster
the mental fortitude, I&amp;#39;d rather not deal with the stress if I don&amp;#39;t have to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, I found a method much better suited to my taste. And it involves
dealing in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/s/stockoption.asp&quot;&gt;stock options&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Options are incredibly more flexible than stock, which you can merely buy and
sell. Options enable very safe plays (though with lower payout), but also
getting more &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/l/leverage.asp&quot;&gt;leverage&lt;/a&gt; when you want to make aggressive moves. They can also be
used to manage/lower your losses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This increased flexibility also makes options much more interesting — and
frankly more fun to work with.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In future articles, I will explain various kinds of trades I undertake using
options. Stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-12-26T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/stock-market-intro</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/stock-market-intro</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviews 9</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/every-anime/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/more-anime/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-6&quot;&gt;Six&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-7&quot;&gt;Seven&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8&quot;&gt;Eight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solo-leveling&quot;&gt;Solo Leveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Volume 1+, up to chapter 131&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;solo-leveling.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another webtoon, somewhat similar &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#skeleton-soldier-couldnt-defend-the-dungeon-up-to-chapter-109&quot;&gt;Skeleton Soldier&lt;/a&gt;, albeit more popular (given
it&amp;#39;s the only webtoon anyone&amp;#39;s ever told me about besides the even more popular
&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#tower-of-god-webtoon---up-to-episode-485&quot;&gt;Tower of God&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this universe there are &amp;quot;gates&amp;quot; that appear regularly, which lead to dungeons
full of monsters. These dungeons must be cleared under a certain number of days,
lest the monsters pour out in the real world. However, at the same time these
gates appeared, some people started developing powers, basically turning them
into RPG characters with superior physical abilities and/or magical powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main character is not very strong, but through the vicissitudes of
&lt;del&gt;narrative facility&lt;/del&gt; fate, he gets to power up pretty quickly (I&amp;#39;m sure you were
able to guess that from the title).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is a massive power trip, but somehow it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, I don&amp;#39;t really know why, but I&amp;#39;m a bit of a fan of the aesthetics and
the genre (just like Isekai). I guess I wasted too much time grinding in
World of Warcraft and now my brain is permanently damaged. Expect to see many
more review of &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; similar anime (as it turns out, there are a ton).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#39;t know whether to recommend it, I obviously enjoyed it very much, but at
the same time I have no specific glowing praise for it. It&amp;#39;s not clever in any
particularly unique way. Give it a few chapters and drop it if it doesn&amp;#39;t speak
to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Somewhat more interestingly, I think this webtoon doesn&amp;#39;t compare super
favorably to &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#skeleton-soldier-couldnt-defend-the-dungeon-up-to-chapter-109&quot;&gt;Skeleton Soldier&lt;/a&gt;. The fact that the main character can die
(albeit temporarily) in Skeleton Soldier does tend to make the stakes higher.
The story is also more involved, with characters coming in and out of the story.
In general, I&amp;#39;m also intrigued in Skeleton&amp;#39;s universe. The mystery in Solo
Leveling is rather singular for my taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;jujutsu-kaisen&quot;&gt;Jujutsu Kaisen&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched 5 episodes of this, but it just didn&amp;#39;t click for me. It&amp;#39;s a very
generic shonen that punches under its weight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being generic is not a death sentence. Nobody will accuse [My Hero Academia] of
being incredibly original, yet it&amp;#39;s the best thing since sliced bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jujutsu Kaisen completely failed to pull me into its universe. I found the
moments of tension completely unbelievable. For instance, at some point early in
the series, the main character loses a hand, and I didn&amp;#39;t believe it for even a
second. A bit later in the same episode, something even more egregious happens,
and same thing, didn&amp;#39;t believe it one bit. It&amp;#39;s not like there are amazing
fights, or really interesting character designs / personalities either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the contrast with Hero Academia is stark: some of the key fights in the
anime so far really got me invested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did like the ending theme however, it&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6riDJMI-Y8U&quot;&gt;quite funky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;zenkyou-no-terror-terror-in-resonance&quot;&gt;Zenkyou no Terror (Terror in Resonance)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;zenkyou-no-terror.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has been on my list for quite a while, and I&amp;#39;m happy I finally got around
to watching it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story follows two teenagers committing various acts of terrorism in Tokyo.
The big question: what&amp;#39;s their purpose?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it works on two plans. First, it&amp;#39;s a &amp;quot;planned crime&amp;quot; show. Early Death
Note comes to mind (sorry, I&amp;#39;m lacking better references here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second there is the mystery of purpose. You can kind of infer it as the story
unfolds, but I still found it very interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d classify alongside &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4/#parasyte&quot;&gt;Parasyte&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-7/#erased-boku-dake-ga-inai-machi&quot;&gt;Erased&lt;/a&gt; in the list of seinens that are
worth your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show is short (only 11 episodes). This is good, as no time is wasted. But on
the other hand, some aspects feel neglected. In particular the character of Lisa
Mishima, a girl that finds herself entangled with the terrorists, lacks in
depth. I understand why she&amp;#39;s in the story, but it feels like a bit more
attention could have made her into more than simply a plot device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-returners-magic-should-be-special&quot;&gt;A Returner&amp;#39;s Magic Should Be Special&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1-2, up to chapter 124&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here we are again, with a webtoon that has an RPG-like setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The setting is surprisingly similar to &lt;a href=&quot;#solo-leveling&quot;&gt;Solo Leveling&lt;/a&gt;: dungeons appear in the
world. If they are not cleared, they absorb the surrounding land in some kind of
void. Clearing the dungeons is not just about killing monsters, but also
fulfilling various quests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, the main character is part of an elite group that defeated the final
boss of the worst dungeon to ever appear - only to be killed by the blowback.
Consequently, he wakes up a student in an academy for dungeon-fighters, 10 years
before the appearance of the disastrous dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides the quests inside the dungeons, the RPG element is toned out here: there
is no XP and attributes here, only good old training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s also a political dimension as the hero tries to fix what&amp;#39;s wrong with
the continent (namely literal class warfare) to unite people against the coming
threat. Enjoyable, but a bit too much on the nose for my taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like before: I&amp;#39;m susceptible to this genre, and I liked it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;barakamon&quot;&gt;Barakamon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anime&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;barakamon.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another anime recommended by my girlfriend Sasha, and another very pleasant
surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is about a professional calligrapher in lack of inspiration and
professional turmoil. His father ships him out a tiny island to shore up his
inspiration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There he befriends the local townspeople and in particularly the kids. He falls
for the pastoral charm of the country life and learns from the folksy wisdom of
the people. etc. etc. The pitch is not very original — but it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the cute story, the show is pretty hilarious. It&amp;#39;s honestly one
of the funniest showsI&amp;#39;ve seen so far. Probably in my top 2, up there with
&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-8/#kaguya-sama-love-is-war-season-2&quot;&gt;Love is War&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also a short one (12 episodes), so don&amp;#39;t hold back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;gateless&quot;&gt;Gateless&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book, by Sebastian Marshall &amp;amp; Kai Zau&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sebastian Marshall is a &amp;quot;productivity expert&amp;quot;. That sounds pretty corny, but I
don&amp;#39;t know how else to describe him. It might be better to say he&amp;#39;s someone
obsessed with peak performance, who built a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ultraworking.com/&quot;&gt;whole business&lt;/a&gt; around that
obsession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He&amp;#39;s also one I respect immensely, despite not always agreeing with him. That
doesn&amp;#39;t preclude me from mining for useful insights, of which there are many.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been following Sebastian for a while, in particular &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thestrategicreview.net/&quot;&gt;The Strategic Review&lt;/a&gt;
(I&amp;#39;ve posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/celerity/&quot;&gt;a summary of one of the series&lt;/a&gt; back in 2017), his
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ultraworking.com/podcast&quot;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://sebastianmarshall.com/&quot;&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also not the first book by Sebastian I&amp;#39;m reading. Besides &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/23642948-gateless&quot;&gt;Gateless&lt;/a&gt; - I&amp;#39;ve
previously read &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/en/book/show/25535056-roguelike&quot;&gt;Roguelike&lt;/a&gt; which extracts lessons and analogies from classical
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roguelike&quot;&gt;roguelikes&lt;/a&gt; with application towards real-life endeavours. (I guess you&amp;#39;d see
how that would talk to me!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that Gateless was co-authored by Sebastian&amp;#39;s co-founder and friend Kai Zau.
Unfortunately, I have much fewer interesting things to tell you about Kai.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, about this book himself. Well, I didn&amp;#39;t learn much. But that&amp;#39;s also because
I&amp;#39;m well acquainted with Sebastian&amp;#39;s idea, as I think I&amp;#39;ve established.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is basically a manual in how to improve in your endeavours. It&amp;#39;s
probably most directly useful if that endeavour is something that resembles &amp;quot;a
career&amp;quot;, but it is general enough to be useful in other areas too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is short enough, but I worry that if you&amp;#39;re at the level where most of
these basics are news to you, then it might actually be a bit much to take in.
It&amp;#39;s also not the funniest read, and it&amp;#39;s notably less fun to read than most of
the Marshall stuff I&amp;#39;ve read before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, recommended if you&amp;#39;re a dutiful person looking to fill the gaps in your
strategy. But I&amp;#39;d advise to start with the Marshall productions linked in this
summary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I find myself concurring with this (4/5 stars!)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/1377037687&quot;&gt;review&lt;/a&gt; from GoodReads, which will also give you a bit more
details about the book itself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of blog-like essays on thinking about and developing personal
(&amp;quot;Capacity&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Meaning&amp;quot; sections), social (&amp;quot;Signal&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;Network&amp;quot;) and
financial capital (&amp;quot;Assets&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing terribly new here and large chunks of the book are verbatim
quotes taken from other sources. Meaning and Assets sections are largely
cursory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, I quite enjoyed it - though nothing particularly new, their
particular formulation of the ideas resonated with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, recommendable - especially for fresh graduates just entering the
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tactical-barbell&quot;&gt;Tactical Barbell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now for something completely different, a book about weightlifting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must say this one disappointed me. First, because I heard the Tactical Barbell
approach integrated conditioning (i.e. cardio &amp;amp; high intensity endurance work),
but it turns out that part is outlined in the second book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, because the book says very little about lifting, and does so in too many
words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core approach is to train only big compound lifts (squat, bench press,
deadlift, pullups, ...) at submaximal intensities (i.e. maybe a &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-5/#reactive-training-systems-rts&quot;&gt;7-8 RPE&lt;/a&gt;)
with plenty of rest (up to 5 minutes) between sets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s pretty boring, though I have no doubts that it works, at least up to a
certain point (but far enough for most people, including me currently).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An important point is that the book is targeted to an &amp;quot;operational&amp;quot; audience:
police, army, SWAT, firefighters, ... (hence the &amp;quot;tactical&amp;quot; in the title). A big
point is that these people may already have some fairly intense physical
workloads (in the course of work, or because of work-mandated training), so the
strength work should be as efficient as possible and not leave them too tired to
perform well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That being said, the book goes so much out of its way to evoke out this
&amp;quot;operational&amp;quot; image that it had me wonder if it wasn&amp;#39;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; marketed at
people who have a tactical fetish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few parts of the book also inspire distrust. The author claims to have reached
4% body fat at some point, for instance. The section on supplements is as best a
N=1 field report, and contains no actual scientific facts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#39;ll see if book 2 is better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tactical-barbell-2-conditioning&quot;&gt;Tactical Barbell 2: Conditioning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I liked the second book much better. One reason is that it actually contained
things I wasn&amp;#39;t really much informed about. It also contains an actionable plan
(a program, really). It&amp;#39;s easy to find good quality strength programs online
(e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://stronglifts.com/5x5/&quot;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://builtwithscience.com/best-full-body-workout/&quot;&gt;two&lt;/a&gt;), but I haven&amp;#39;t stumbled on a program aiming to
develop and maintain conditioning before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book is also better organized, with the principles outlined in the first
part (+ still quite a bit of fluff) and the extensive exercise plan in the
second part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, reviewing the book is not that useful — I ought to try this and
review the program. I&amp;#39;m thinking I might do the &amp;quot;base-building&amp;quot; 8-week block
after I redo a strength block when the gym re-opens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;from-dusk-till-dawn&quot;&gt;From Dusk Till Dawn&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;from-dusk-till-dawn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the last &amp;quot;Tarantino movie&amp;quot; that I hadn&amp;#39;t seen. It isn&amp;#39;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; a
Tarantino movie, as Tarantino only wrote the script (and plays a major acting
role in the movie), but the movie was directed by Robert Rodriguez.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The flick is fast-paced and pretty fun. At first glance, it looks like it&amp;#39;s
going to be classical rough-n-dirty Tarantino flick, but the genre of this movie
is actually action horror.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so things take a turn for the weird at some point. And it&amp;#39;s great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a bit hard to say if it&amp;#39;s a B-movie or an homage to B-movies. It&amp;#39;s
certainly a bit of parody, albeit of nothing in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good time that happens to involve a lot of gore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;gone-girl&quot;&gt;Gone Girl&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This movie is tricky to describe. Wikipedia says it&amp;#39;s a &amp;quot;psychological thriller&amp;quot;
and I think that does fit the bill. To me, it&amp;#39;s one of those &amp;quot;guess movies&amp;quot;,
where I can&amp;#39;t prevent myself from annoying the hell of whoever I&amp;#39;m watching it
with (in this case, Sasha) by interjecting all my hypothesis about what the hell
could be going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyhow, the pitch: writer Nick Dunne finds his wife missing and contacts the
police. A search is organized, and troublesome truths about the relationship
come to light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does sound a bit dull, but there is a mystery, and the twist and turns are
quite satisfying. This movie will have you wondering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s only really one thing I disliked about it: the very ending. Not that I
objected to it, I just thought it was poorly justified and didn&amp;#39;t make a lot of
sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In making this review, I realized that (a) this is a David Fincher, and (b) I&amp;#39;ve
actually consumed most of Fincher&amp;#39;s cinematographic output: Seven, The Game,
Fight Club, Benjamin Button, The Social Network, The Girl With The Dragon
Tattoo, Zodiac, and now Gone Girl - as well as House of Cards. Most of those are
pretty good. If you haven&amp;#39;t seen them, I&amp;#39;d particularly recommend Gone Girl, The
Game, Fight Club, and the first season of House of Cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;zero-to-one&quot;&gt;Zero to One&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Book&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book outlines Peter Thiel&amp;#39;s (a founder of PayPal and Palantir) business
philosophy - especially regarding startups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it&amp;#39;s well worth reading for anyone interested in eventually starting a
business (especially an ambitious one), or just interesting in business in
general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you an idea, here&amp;#39;s my very short summary of a few ideas I took away
from the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Startups should aim to become monopolies — because a monopoly is not
constantly under threat and thus has the space to innovate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the ways to establish a monopoly is networks effects. And paradoxically,
network effect monopolies must get started with a small market — one that the
startup can completely corner. For instance, Facebook started serving only
Harvard students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;A startup&amp;#39;s most important asset is new thinking. A startup needs &amp;quot;a secret&amp;quot; —
something it believes to be true, while the consensus (not just the majority)
thinks that it is false. What valuable company is no one else building?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sales &amp;amp; distribution matter more than they&amp;#39;re made out to in the startup
world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sales is always hidden. &amp;quot;Salesman&amp;quot; is nobody&amp;#39;s title, instead it might be
&amp;quot;customer happiness office&amp;quot; for a very transparent example. You don&amp;#39;t know
any sales grandmaster - because you don&amp;#39;t think of them as such.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Computers will not replace humans - the future is complementarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solo-bug-leveling&quot;&gt;Solo Bug Leveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1, up to chapter 40&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veteran MMO player dies, gets reincarnated in the game. Can&amp;#39;t be more classic
than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here though, the hero gets reincarnated as an (adult) lord of some small
province. Armed with his encyclopedic knowledge of the game (and, as the title
implies, of its bugs), he sets out to make right everything that is wrong, and
to prepare adequately for future turmoil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not sure I have too much to say about this one. The setting and the
execution are both solid. An enjoyable read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;slave-b&quot;&gt;Slave B&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1, up to chapter 50&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;slave-b.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this one departs &lt;em&gt;a little bit&lt;/em&gt; from the leveling webtoons I&amp;#39;ve been reading,
but it&amp;#39;s not too far away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s the story of slave kid who, after some mishap, finds the opportunity to
attend a prestigious caster/fighter military academy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The focus is not too much on leveling or skill acquisition (although there is a
bit of that), but more on inter-personal relationships and in particular the
ostracism towards the slaves. In that it&amp;#39;s a bit similar to &lt;a href=&quot;#a-returner-s-magic-should-be-special-webtoon&quot;&gt;Returner&lt;/a&gt; and its
commoner/noble distinction — except way worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one is also different in that it&amp;#39;s not a clean nice power trip drive. The
hero does experience quite a few setbacks, and a lot of suffering. The story is
also interested in dealing with the resulting anger (instead of featuring a
noble hero that would brush it off instantly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d say this story has more ambition than what I&amp;#39;d read so far. Or if not that,
at least it takes more risk by dealing with emotions and more complex
relationship dynamics. It&amp;#39;s not quite as masterful as some of these others (like
Skeleton or Solo Leveling), perhaps precisely because of these dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all in all, quite interesting, and might appeal to a more mainstream
audience that doesn&amp;#39;t have some kind of leveling fetish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-beginning-after-the-end&quot;&gt;The Beginning After The End&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Webtoon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Season 1-3, up to chapter 85&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another webtoon in the same vein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this one, our hero is nothing less than a conqueror king, reincarnated. His
original lifetime seemingly had magic but also a futuristic setting, while his
reincarnated life happens in a more medieval type of settings, complete with
elves and dwarves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I felt like this webtoon did itself a service by taking some breathing room.
Over 85 chapters, the plot advances much less than some other webtoons in the
same genre. Amusingly, we see the reincarnated hero age from 0 to 13 years old -
and he is just now about to join some kind of magic school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This space is mostly potentiality - it means the webtoon does not commit faults
by rushing the plot and the relationships between the characters, but it also
means that the number of plot points has been limited so far. If done correctly
though, the greater familiarity we have acquired with the characters will lead
to a much more satisfying punch down the line, and the character development
will feel meaningful. We can only hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s not to say that nothing happened, and it&amp;#39;s been a very enjoyable read so
far, it&amp;#39;s not exactly a tapestry of intrigue, but I have nothing critical to say
about it either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just like &lt;a href=&quot;#slave-b-webtoon-up-to-chapter-50&quot;&gt;Slave B&lt;/a&gt;, this one is also much less leveling oriented (though the
theme is present as skill acquisition and mana mastery).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, I got a very &lt;em&gt;cozy&lt;/em&gt; vibe from this toon. The hero&amp;#39;s original (and
still mysterious) life was lonely, as an orphan that somehow made it to the top.
The webtoon emphasizes, on the other hand, how precious his family and friends
are to him in his new life. And you know what, I&amp;#39;m all for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, very recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-mandalorian-season-2&quot;&gt;The Mandalorian Season 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TV&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5/#the-mandalorian&quot;&gt;Season 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second season does not disappoint — it&amp;#39;s still great. It does tell us more
about the character of the show, however. Sasha sent me this comic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;mandalorian.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And so it is - it&amp;#39;s an episodic show. The second season doesn&amp;#39;t launch in grand
intrigues any more than the first one does. With only 8 episodes and a flair for
showing great action sequences, maybe that&amp;#39;s preferable (the counterexample
here would be John Wick - great first movie, terrible franchise).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did get a bit frustrated by the 6th episode, however. There were too many
frustrations of the type where I go like &amp;quot;why didn&amp;#39;t you do this? you literally
did it 5 minutes ago! but now it&amp;#39;s useful!&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;of course that&amp;#39;s precisely the
moment where X would happen!!&amp;quot;. Probably this is actually a weakness of the show
and this happens more than I realize — I&amp;#39;m typically an easy audience. But in
that episode, it was really hard to overlook. Fortunately, the show made up for
it with an excellent 7th episode and an adequate, if
not-quite-as-good-as-first-season&amp;#39;s, finale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disney is apparently very intent on milking the Star Wars cow, and in particular
the Mandalorian cow (probably especially so after they drove the main series
into the ground). Next year we can expect, in addition to season 3, a show on
Bobba Fett. But there&amp;#39;s more! Disney is working on two more Mandalorian spinoffs,
one on Jedi &lt;a href=&quot;https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Ahsoka_Tano&quot;&gt;Ahsoka Tano&lt;/a&gt; (from the animated movies and appearing in this season
of Mando), one on the New Republic Rangers. And there&amp;#39;s also one on Lando
Calrissian. I expect a mixed bag, but let&amp;#39;s hope for one or two gems in there.
This is the way.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-12-24T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/reviews-9</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/reviews-9</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weight Training 8: Gains</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-2&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-3&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-4&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-5&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-6&quot;&gt;Six&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-7&quot;&gt;Seven&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lifting&quot;&gt;Lifting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I followed the powerlifting DUP protocol outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-7&quot;&gt;my previous post&lt;/a&gt;,
except I lowered deadlift reps to 5x and 8x.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ran the protocol for approximately 14 weeks, before I was forced to stop
because the gym closed down for another coronavirus lockdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The timing wasn&amp;#39;t too unfortunate, however. My TTP (time to peek) on the bench
press and deadlift was approximately 8 weeks. I understand from the RTS
litterature that&amp;#39;s a pretty usual timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My squat however progressed more slowly. Might not have pushed myself enough,
but I&amp;#39;m very careful with squat form as it&amp;#39;s easier to fudge up. That was still
going up as I was forced to stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I&amp;#39;ve hit new personal records on all big lifts (sets * reps *
weight in kg):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bench: 3x3x110, 3x6x100, 3x12x77.5&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Squat: 3x3x157.5, 3x6x135, 3x12x95&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deadlift: 3x3.185, 3x5x165, 3x8x135&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;cutting&quot;&gt;Cutting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said last time I was doing all this while going on a slight cut. I&amp;#39;m not too
sure how that went. I stopped tracking my calories (which I&amp;#39;d been doing for ~2
years at that point) to save a bit of time and hassle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The worst-cast scenario was to cut ~200 calories on my three weekly workout
days, and eat at maintenance the rest of the time. This comes to 600 kcal/week,
or approximately one kilo over the duration of the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I expected body recomposition (fat loss, muscle gain), I also skipped out
on weighting myself every day, but punctual measurements seem to indicate my
weight was more or less maintained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The progress on the lifts is mostly neural adaptation, but I think it&amp;#39;s likely
some amount of muscle gain occurred too, seemingly validating that body
recomposition did indeed occur.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;forward&quot;&gt;Forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve started re-running home workouts. I&amp;#39;m not giving specifics, the idea is the
same as &lt;a href=&quot;/weight-training-6&quot;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt;, but with a different exercise selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m interested in trying some bodyweight movements. I&amp;#39;ve experimented with
handstands against a wall (not too sure of my balacing skills). Also with the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.be/search?tbm=isch&amp;amp;q=dragon%20flag&quot;&gt;dragon flag&lt;/a&gt;, but I don&amp;#39;t have a good enough setup to accomodate it indoors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have some distance to go where I want to be with my cut, so I&amp;#39;m going to
continue to cut moderately. I&amp;#39;ll be tracking again and aiming for a ~1200
kcal/week deficit at first.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-11-16T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/weight-training-8</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/weight-training-8</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chosen Tidbits 6</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-1/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-2/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-3/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-4/&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-5/&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://putanumonit.com/2019/12/30/100-ways-to-live-better/&quot;&gt;100 Ways to Live Better&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any life advice that isn’t given to you personally is not designed to be
followed to the letter. Try to resonate with the philosophy that generates it
instead. Remember that directional advice (e.g., “be more …”) &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/03/24/should-you-reverse-any-advice-you-hear/&quot;&gt;may need to be
reversed&lt;/a&gt; before consumption.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re not having fun then just leave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;I know we were just introduced, but I forgot your name.&amp;quot; &amp;quot;I saw the email you
sent me last month, I just procrastinated and forgot.&amp;quot; &amp;quot;This is the best
effort I was realistically going to make.&amp;quot; Try it, it&amp;#39;s liberating.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your spouse, friend, or family member is doing something dumb but not
strictly harmful, try thinking of it as their artistic expression instead of
using facts and logic to fail to talk them out of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;#39;re home alone, blast some music and dance. Don&amp;#39;t think about your
body, just focus on the music. Then do the exact same thing when you&amp;#39;re at a
dance party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Get massages, give massages. You don&amp;#39;t have to know what you&amp;#39;re doing to
make someone feel great. Use scentless baby oil, or moisturizer if the recipient
is not going to shower afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t nitpick tweets, that&amp;#39;s the opposite of good improv. - &amp;quot;But what you
wrote doesn&amp;#39;t always apply because...&amp;quot; Congrats, you got someone annoyed and now
you&amp;#39;ll just sit there getting frustrated because you expect a response and
aren&amp;#39;t going to get one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stop lurking; write that comment. You know the saying about letting people
suspect you&amp;#39;re dumb rather than opening your mouth and removing all doubt? Fuck
that. We know you&amp;#39;re dumb, and you get less dumb by saying things and getting
feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you really going to give up on expressing yourself, learning from
mistakes, attracting like-minded people, building a reputation, and changing the
world because someone may someday try to cancel you? They can smell the fear,
you know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#39;re moving chargers and cables around, you need to buy more chargers
and cables. A girl in every port, a USB-C in every room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doctors are human, they have biases and make mistakes. It&amp;#39;s your job to be
educated about your conditions and the drugs you are prescribed. If you&amp;#39;re
confused, ask for details or a second opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.richardwiseman.com/resources/The_Luck_Factor.pdf&quot;&gt;The Luck Factor (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lucky people generate their own good fortune via four basic principles. They
are skilled at creating and noticing chance opportunities, make lucky
decisions by listening to their intuition, create self-fulfilling prohesies
via positive expectations, and adopt a resilient attitude that transforms bad
luck into good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://theartofmachinery.com/2020/01/27/systems_programming_probability.html&quot;&gt;Some Useful Probability Facts for Systems Programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an outcome has probability 1/N for each &amp;quot;attempt&amp;quot;, and it is attempted N
times, the probability it will occur at least once stabilizes at 0.62 as N
increases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you throw N balls randomly (independently and one at a time) into N
buckets. On average, a bit over a third (1/e) of the buckets will stay empty, a
bit over a third (1/e again) will have exactly one ball, and the remaining
quarter or so (1 − 2/e) will contain multiple balls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a group of things are randomly shuffled, a bit of over a third (1/e) of the
time there’ll be no fixed points (something that lands in the same position), a
bit of over a third (1/e) of the time there’ll be just one fixed point, and the
remaining quarter or so of the time there’ll be two or more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at the common “loot box” mechanism. Specifically, suppose there are
10 collector items (say, one for each hero in a franchise) that are sold in
blind boxes. Let’s take the fairest case in which there are no rare items and
each item has an equal 1/10 chance of being in a given box. How many boxes will a
collector buy on average before getting a complete set? This is the called the
coupon collector’s problem, and for 10 items the answer is about 29.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer to the coupon collector’s problem is a bit more than N * ln(N) (add N/2
for some more accuracy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The coupon collector’s problem hints at why the loot box mechanism is so
powerful. The N balls in N buckets rule tells us that the collector will have
about two thirds of the items after buying 10 boxes. It feels like the collector
is most of the way there, and it would be a shame to give up and let so much
progress go to waste, but actually 10 boxes is only about a third of the
expected number of boxes needed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/G_S_Bhogal/status/1225561131122597896?s=09&quot;&gt;40 powerful concepts for understanding the world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ergodicity: A die rolled 100 times has equal probabilities to 100 dice rolled
once; rolling a die is “ergodic”. But if the die gets chipped after 10 throws
so it’s likelier to roll 4, then 1 die 100 times =/= 100 dice once
(non-ergodic). Many treat non-ergodic systems as ergodic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://larspsyll.wordpress.com/2016/11/23/what-is-ergodicity-2/&quot;&gt;another good explanation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simpson’s Paradox: A trend can appear in groups of data but disappear when these
groups are combined. This effect can easily be exploited by limiting a dataset
so that it shows exactly what one wants it to show. Thus: beware of even the
strongest correlations. (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/G_S_Bhogal/status/1225561191470260227&quot;&gt;illustration&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Condorcet Paradox: a special instance of Simpson’s paradox applied to elections,
in which a populace prefers candidate A to candidate B, candidate B to C, and
yet candidate C to A. This occurs because the majority that favors C is
misleadingly divided among different groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Concept Creep: As a social issue such as racism or sexual harassment becomes
rarer, people react by expanding their definition of it, creating the illusion
that the issue is actually getting worse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Streetlight Effect: People tend to get their information from where it’s easiest
to look.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Woozle Effect: An article makes a claim without evidence, is then cited by
another, which is cited by another, and so on, until the range of citations
creates the impression that the claim has evidence, when really all articles are
citing the same uncorroborated source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tocqueville Paradox: As the living standards in a society rise, the people’s
expectations of the society rise with it. The rise in expectations eventually
surpasses the rise in living standards, inevitably resulting in disaffection
(and sometimes populist uprisings).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nirvana Fallacy: When people reject a thing because it compares unfavorably to
an ideal that in reality is unattainable. E.g. condemning capitalism due to
the superiority of imagined socialism, condemning ruthlessness in war due to
imagining humane (but unrealistic) ways to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://spotthedrowningchild.com/&quot;&gt;It&amp;#39;s surprisingly difficult to spot someone
drowning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/03/06/socratic-grilling/&quot;&gt;Socratic Grilling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a dialog with a lot of questions from a student, it might sound as though the
student is nitpicking and/or challenging the teacher, when he&amp;#39;s really just
trying to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/webdevMason/status/1232406997712003072&quot;&gt;Tweet by Mason&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve noticed that many of the most persistent childhood traumas related to being
made to feel unwanted, a burden, the &amp;quot;bad&amp;quot; one. I think they may persist as
&amp;quot;chronic mental illness&amp;quot; because being sick doesn&amp;#39;t heal the wound of being a
burden — being &lt;em&gt;the healer&lt;/em&gt; does&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sincerely believe that many western communities are now suffering not for lack
of services to be received by hurting people, but for lack of services to be
&lt;em&gt;provided&lt;/em&gt; by hurting people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Counterintuitive as it is, next time someone around you is struggling with
living in their own head, don&amp;#39;t ask how you can help; ask them to help you. If
they don&amp;#39;t, or they flake, just keep asking for small things. Don&amp;#39;t pressure or
punish for lack of follow-through, just ask&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;You&amp;#39;re not so broken that we don&amp;#39;t need you&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; is something that has to be
lived to be believed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://larvalsubjects.wordpress.com/2011/11/07/this-extended-mind-again-we-dont-know-what-a-human-being-is/&quot;&gt;This Extended Mind Again: We Don’t Know What a Human Being
Is&lt;/a&gt;
via &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/rsnous/status/1046286119095033858&quot;&gt;Omar Rizwan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If it is true that… many of our beliefs are actually &lt;em&gt;external&lt;/em&gt; to our internal
world, off-loaded on to the internet, books, authorities we identify with, etc…
then it might be that the project of &amp;#39;debunking&amp;#39; is of limited value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seems that &lt;em&gt;identification&lt;/em&gt; with many institutions… is every bit as much a
mechanism that binds people to oppressive systems as conscious belief… a major
strategy for undermining certain social formations would consist in the question
of how to produce &lt;em&gt;disidentification&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/nosilverv/status/1247187708184629248&quot;&gt;Tweet by Rival Voices&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lock-and-key approach to life: each thing it either a perfect fit or not. What
is a perfect fit changes with each past fit. TRY a lot of things and ITERATE
through trying them really fast (quit early, quit often). Don’t do anything
hard, do what effortlessly &lt;em&gt;clicks&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edge.org/response-detail/11783&quot;&gt;Concept: Kayfabe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because professional wrestling is a simulated sport, all competitors who face
each other in the ring are actually close collaborators who must form a closed
system (called &amp;quot;a promotion&amp;quot;) sealed against outsiders. With external
competitors generally excluded, antagonists are chosen from within the promotion
and their ritualized battles are largely negotiated, choreographed, and
rehearsed at a significantly decreased risk of injury or death. With outcomes
predetermined under Kayfabe, betrayal in wrestling comes not from engaging in
unsportsmanlike conduct, but by the surprise appearance of actual sporting
behavior. Such unwelcome sportsmanship which &amp;quot;breaks Kayfabe&amp;quot; is called
&amp;quot;shooting&amp;quot; to distinguish it from the expected scripted deception called
&amp;quot;working&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Wrestling evolved out of &amp;quot;catch&amp;quot;.] Typical matches could last hours with no
satisfying action, or end suddenly with crippling injuries to a promising
athlete in whom much had been invested. This highlighted the close
relationship between two paradoxical risks which define the category of
activity which wrestling shares with other human spheres:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A) Occasional but Extreme Peril for the participants.
B) General: Monotony for both audience and participants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kayfabrication (the process of transition from reality towards Kayfabe) arises
out of attempts to deliver a dependably engaging product for a mass audience
while removing the unpredictable upheavals that imperil participants. As such
Kayfabrication is a dependable feature of many of our most important systems
which share the above two characteristics such as war, finance, love, politics
and science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the point Kayfabe was forced to own up to the fact that professional
wrestling contained no sport whatsoever, it did more than avoid being regulated
and taxed into oblivion. Wrestling discovered the unthinkable: its audience did
not seem to require even a thin veneer of realism. Professional wrestling had
come full circle to its honest origins by at last moving the responsibility for
deception off of the shoulders of the performers and into the willing minds of
the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kayfabe, it appears, is a dish best served client-side.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edge.org/response-detail/27181&quot;&gt;Concept: Russell Conjugation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the theory goes, it is not that we don’t have our own opinions so much as
that we have too many contradictory ones, and it is generally our emotional
state alone which determines on which ones we will predicate action or inaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russell Conjugation (or “emotive conjugation”) is a presently obscure
construction from linguistics, psychology and rhetoric which demonstrates how
our rational minds are shielded from understanding the junior role factual
information generally plays relative to empathy in our formation of opinions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where words can be considered “synonyms” if they carry the same factual content
(I) regardless of the emotional content (II). This however leads to the peculiar
effect that the synonyms for a positive word like “whistle-blower” cannot be
used in its place as they are almost universally negative (with “snitch,”
“fink,” “tattletale” being representative examples). This is our first clue that
something is wrong, or at least incomplete with our concept of synonym requiring
an upgrade to distinguish words that may be content synonyms but emotional
antonyms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;firm&lt;/em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;obstinate&lt;/em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;pig-headed&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;death tax&lt;/em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;estate tax&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;illegal alien&lt;/em&gt; vs &lt;em&gt;undocumented migrant&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://churchlifejournal.nd.edu/articles/youre-a-slave-to-money-then-you-die/&quot;&gt;You&amp;#39;re a Slave to Money, Then You
Die&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the student and other forms of personal debt that prepare undergraduates
to say two words — &amp;quot;Yes, boss&amp;quot; — the ideal of the entrepreneurial self serves
a fundamentally disciplinary function: reinforcing the precarious nature of
work in today’s digitalized, low-wage, precariously employed, and increasingly
automated capitalism, one in which you are casually expendable and which
places a premium on everlasting metamorphosis: upgrade your skills, your
profile, your resume. But don’t worry, complain, or God help you, call a
union: losing your job or seeing your skill set rendered obsolescent is an
opportunity for &amp;quot;growth,&amp;quot; creativity, empowerment. When your own exploitation
can be recast as a project rather than a problem—a source of fulfillment
rather than an instance of injustice—then solidarity with others can be
vilified as conformism, the herd instinct of normies, the last refuge of
losers and mediocrities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/freWTrdfxwpn4imwn/the-value-is-in-the-tails&quot;&gt;The Value is In The Tails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I asked him why he bet on Trump, he said he didn&amp;#39;t really understand
American politics, but that it seemed extremely complicated, with random things
like whether it rains in certain parts of Pennsylvania potentially being
important. If it&amp;#39;s extremely complicated and arbitrary, then it&amp;#39;s probably also
hard to model. The projections he saw had the most likely outcome being a
moderate win by Hilary, but since he didn&amp;#39;t trust the models, he figured the
value was in the tails: the models are likely off, which likely affects the
tails more than the mean. So a landslide win by Hilary or a Trump victory seemed
undervalued by gambling markets. He wished he could hedge his bets by betting on
both outcomes (as opposed to a moderate Hilary win), but the only option he had
was to bet on Trump to win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This logic has stuck with me ever since: in the face of large uncertainty, we&amp;#39;re
probably getting the tails wrong more than the mean. The value is in the tails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/rMfpnorsMoRwyn4iP/choosing-the-zero-point&quot;&gt;Choosing The Zero Point&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can decide what state of affairs counts as neutral, and what counts as
positive or negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;e.g. animal suffering: you can define the zero point as &amp;quot;animal shouldn&amp;#39;t suffer
more than if humans were there&amp;quot; and if you accept it, that makes you a monster.
You could frame the zero point as the current situation, and every improvement
you make as a net gain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://deluks917.wordpress.com/2020/04/15/people-hate-non-shockers/&quot;&gt;People Hate Non-Shockers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A society has the following rules:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Everyone must publicly electro-shock themselves 8 hours per day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— If you see someone not shocking themselves then you must kill them&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Anyone who violates the second rule must also be killed. The same is true for
  all meta levels. Non-killers of non-killers of ... of non-shockers must be
  killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This equilibrium can get locked in even if every single person dislikes it. I
think similar but weaker dynamics apply all the time in normal life. Why is
there so much hyperbolic hate direct against furries?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most are people are very repressed. Society has a norm that you need to keep
‘low status’ or ‘cringey’ aspects of yourself private. Furries often violate
these norms. People feel the urge to punish them. And people often feel
uncomfortable even being seen as being tolerant. Afterall tolerators are at risk
too!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t claim this is the only dynamic at play. People also like to look down on
official low-status groups to feel better about themselves. Notably, even if
people don’t intrinsically want to punish non-shockers may still hate them. If
you let me see you not shocking yourself now you have put me at risk unless I
punish you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.visakanv.com/blog/prestige/&quot;&gt;Prestige&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve had several conversations with friends who’ve been incapacitated by the
burdensome bullshit obligation to Have A Meaningful Life / Be Remembered / Do
Important Work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It strikes me as socially inherited bloatware that causes tedious lag, which
ironically prevents you from being awesome. When people say things like “just be
yourself”, I think often what they mean is “be less laggy” – ie, uninstall the
bloatware.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wonderfully, it seems to me that lots of people who end up Doing Important Work
often got there by being playful and curious. Richard Feynman, for example, got
his Nobel prize from piddling around with spinning plates. And the point isn’t
to get the Nobel prize, the point is to enjoy the piddling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prestige is like a powerful magnet that warps even your beliefs about what you
enjoy. It causes you to work not on what you like, but what you’d like to
like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do not be too timid and squeamish about your actions. All life is an experiment.
The more experiments you make, the better. What if they are a little coarse and
you may get your coat soiled or torn? What if you do fail, and get fairly rolled
in the dirt once or twice? Up again; you shall never be so afraid of a tumble.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Ralph Waldo Emerson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SqhVaWKaWi&quot;&gt;5 Jokes That Make People Instantly Like
You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/noampomsky/status/1261007947410206720&quot;&gt;Tweet by Ava&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“radical honesty” is actually pretty hard because we’re so used to language
being gamified that even if you say exactly what you feel people will
generally presume you must be implying something else&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1261082945462267905&quot;&gt;Comment by Visa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the insight that blew my mind around age 20 when I read 48 Laws of
Power. The realisation that my social relations were suffering because people
weren’t interpreting my words as honest, likely because they simply weren’t used
to dealing with someone like me&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2020/05/28/creationism-unchallenged/&quot;&gt;Creationism Unchallenged&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creationism was cancer and the most dangerous thing in the early 2000s. Yet
still as many people believe it. Yet we don&amp;#39;t talk about anymore, and it&amp;#39;s not
been an apocalypse. Talking about it hasn&amp;#39;t hindered or helped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it&amp;#39;s the same with the issue of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I see people using rivers of ink to fight the modern equivalents of
creationists. Pizzagaters, flat-earthers, moon-hoaxers, QAnon, deep-staters,
people who say the coronavirus is a bioweapon, Alex Jones. Are they sure it’s
not equally useless? Equally counterproductive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tynan.com/valuableoutput&quot;&gt;Long Term Valuable Output&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s important to realize that what you create when you are at your best will be
many times more valuable than what you create at average or worse. Sometimes
work created can even be a net negative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sleep is one of the biggest factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s also important to optimize your workspace as much as possible. Get a huge
monitor, a comfy chair, and a nice desk. Get some plants. Spend the time
customizing your computer to make it easy and efficient to use. These are basic
things but they really matter a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you sit down to work, your task must be connected to a goal that matters to
you and it must be an effective lever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are at your best and are working on something that matters, that&amp;#39;s when
it&amp;#39;s time to step on the gas and work hard. The amount of valuable output you
can create in even 4-6 hours of peak performance can be better than days or even
weeks of mediocre output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://roamresearch.com/#/app/visakanv-public/page/tdzT6EDGb&quot;&gt;Visa&amp;#39;s talking points&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Earnestness will make you edgier than trying to be edgy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Persistence: geniuses are mostly just people who are uncommonly persistent in
pursuing their curiosities and interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prolificacy is a superpower: if you want to get good at something, do it 1,000
times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing anything for a long period of time (do it 100 times, do it for 10 years)
will reveal interesting things, and make you an interesting person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sex: lots of people want to be fuckable more than they want to fuck. fucking is
labor, fuckability is capital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People think focus means saying yes to the thing you&amp;#39;ve got to focus on. But
that&amp;#39;s not what it means at all. It means saying no to the hundred other good
ideas that there are... I&amp;#39;m actually as proud of the things we haven&amp;#39;t done as
the things I have done...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;— Steve Jobs&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-11-16T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-6</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-6</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviews 8</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/every-anime/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/more-anime/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-6&quot;&gt;Six&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-7&quot;&gt;Seven&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tower-of-god-anime&quot;&gt;Tower of God (Anime)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;tower-of-god.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I somehow forgot to review this last time, even though it&amp;#39;s one of the shows I
enjoyed the most of the last batch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an adaptation of one of the most popular &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webtoons.com/en/challenge/kennycomics-webtoon-101/whats-webtoonmangamanhwamanhua/viewer?title_no=5956&amp;amp;episode_no=8&quot;&gt;webtoon manhwa&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;#39;d read the
start of it a while ago (covering much more than this first anime season).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can say it&amp;#39;s a faithful adaptation which works really well. I feel like the
anime medium has the potential to clarify some stuff that is not always very
clear in the manhwa. They probably will have to simplify things a little in the
future (and maybe they already have, but things are simple enough so far that
it&amp;#39;s impercetible).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The anime spurred me to reread the manhwa. Actually, to read most of the
published stuff for the first time — it&amp;#39;s still being published and my first
read through was a while back. Since I just finished it, I&amp;#39;m going to say more
about the manhwa immediately. You can just assume everything transposes to the
anime as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, highly recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tower-of-god-webtoon---up-to-episode-485&quot;&gt;Tower of God (Webtoon - up to episode 485)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After staying vague in the anime description, it&amp;#39;s probably fair that I tell you
a bit more about the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story centers around Bam, a boy that seemingly lived his whole life so far
in some sort of huge cave, in company of a girl called Rachel (that you will
soon come to hate). The story starts as Rachel is pulled off into &amp;quot;the tower&amp;quot;,
shortly followed by Bam — who is determined to find Rachel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tower is a whole universe, subdivided into floors, which are whole worlds
onto themselves. It is moreover subdivided between the outer tower - which is
just a collection of plain old worlds where people live, and the inner tower,
where a select few are called. Usually, people are called into the inner tower
from the outer tower, in which case they are called &amp;quot;regulars&amp;quot;. Their goal is to
climb the tower. Reaching the top seemingly makes one&amp;#39;s dream come true — or
something — but it requires powering up massively along the way in order to keep
up with the competition. Climbing itself is achieved by passing tests (elaborate
games that typically involve fighting) on each floor. Very rarely, people from
outside the tower manage to enter the inner tower and climb (like Bam and
Rachel) — these are called irregulars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The strenght of the story, in my opinion, lies in the vast (very vast) crew of
colorful and interesting characters that each come with their own background and
motivations, and are deftly woven into the story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A comparison that I find apt is that &lt;em&gt;Tower of God&lt;/em&gt; is a bit like &lt;em&gt;A Song of Ice
and Fire&lt;/em&gt; (the &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; books): it too has a ton of characters that
jump in a out of the story, and complex motivations and relationships between
the characters. I find that too often anime/manga proceed in fixed &amp;quot;arcs&amp;quot; where
you get to face the villain du jour with today&amp;#39;s allies, which are quickly
forgotten about. No so in &lt;em&gt;Tower of God&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not quite &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; either. For one, there is much less dialogue
between characters where they expose their motivations and share their life
philosophy. Most of that comes in the form of flashbacks (though oftgen
occasionally be narrated flashbacks). There are a few more quiet passages where
character really &amp;quot;converse&amp;quot; about their feeling (as opposed to just trading
information without accompanying emotional/philosophical sense-making), so the
author can write them, but they are relatively few and far between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, in my opinion is that the writing gets a bit weaker towards the end of
the currently published episodes, as the stakes expand. The story focuses less
on floor tests and more on grandiose fights. Yet, games with complex ruleset is
one of the story main&amp;#39;s shticks, and the author finds a way to reintroduce them
in the forms of various bets that the characters make to settle their
differences. That feels a bit clumsy to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another issue is that while the characters are the great strength of the story,
there are simply too many of them. Most of them are interesting and could have
their own story, but unfortunately, breadth comes at the expense of depth. It at
times feel like we get to meet a character, learn part of his backstory, see him
fight, and then he is forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of the early &amp;quot;main&amp;quot; characters that felt like a big part of the story
haven&amp;#39;t been seen in more than 150 episodes at this point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pace is rather fast, and it&amp;#39;s fair to say that the webtoon is a page-turner
(or rather, a panel-scroller). It&amp;#39;s gotten me to neglect my sleep more so than
usual a few times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to make another criticism to the manhwa, is that it&amp;#39;s sometimes a
bit hard to follow. In particular, games tend to have quite intricate rules —
which I&amp;#39;m all for, but they aren&amp;#39;t explained very clearly. I often realize
partway that I misinterpreted the intent of the rules. You&amp;#39;d think that drawings
would help, but alas very often it doesn&amp;#39;t. The drawing are not especially
confusing (except sometimes during fights), but they don&amp;#39;t help that much. Also
— and funnily enough — since at some points there are so damn many characters
around, the author does not always draw all of them. That leads to some weird
situations where you suddenly realize &amp;quot;oh, that guy was there all along&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But anyhow, I find Tower of God amazing and grandiose, and I strongly recommend
you give it a look. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webtoons.com/en/fantasy/tower-of-god/list?title_no=95&amp;amp;page=1&quot;&gt;Read it online here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;perry-mason&quot;&gt;Perry Mason&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new Perry Mason show&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_5O3cMmg3JQ&quot;&gt;trailer&lt;/a&gt; got me really hyped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The character is reprised from the mythical &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perry_Mason&quot;&gt;50&amp;#39;s TV Show&lt;/a&gt;, which
has already undergone quite a few reboots since then. In this case, it&amp;#39;s an
origin story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first episode, which I watched with my girlfriend, left us both thoroughly
nonplussed. And we left it at that. Live on the hype, die on the hype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hellsing-ultimate&quot;&gt;Hellsing Ultimate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had in the back of my mind that Hellsing was a classic, and I ought to see
some. There are two versions adapting the original manga: an anime, and a series
of 1-hour-long OVAs called Hellsing Ultimate. Similarly to Fullmetal Alchemist,
the first (anime) version diverged to the (at the time unfinished manga), while
Ultimate is faithful to the source material. The general sentiment on the
internet was that Ultimate was by far superior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I ended up seeing only one of the episodes, which managed to bore me
thoroughly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is a show about the aesthetics. Since I haven&amp;#39;t mentioned anything
of the show yet: it&amp;#39;s about vampires. And two secretive organizations fighting
the supernatural and one another. And gore.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To clarify, by &lt;em&gt;aesthestics&lt;/em&gt;, I mean the mood of the modern-yet-gothic setting, not the
art and animation which don&amp;#39;t strike me as particularly something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if vampires are your thing, go for it. But I think that even if you have to
throw the story to the wind, the new &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-6/#castlevania-all-3-seasons&quot;&gt;Castlevania&lt;/a&gt; anime is far superior,
mood-wise, if you like vampires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;fire-force-s2&quot;&gt;Fire Force S2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve done quite a reversal on this one from &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5/#enen-no-shouboutai-fire-force&quot;&gt;my season 1 review&lt;/a&gt;.
I dropped it after 3 episodes. It&amp;#39;s not that it was bad per se, but rather my
time was getting rather limited, and I just found this to be the worst of the
anime I was watching.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a few things that informed my decisions. First, these three episodes
were relatively filler heavy. But when they weren&amp;#39;t they just added more
seemingly disparate strands in the story. I would expect it to go into a bit
more depth in the characters and explore their relationships, or explore the
revelations from last seasons. Instead, new elements are piled on top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having many balls in the air is not necessarily a bad thing — see Game of
Thrones (the books and the book-inspired seasons) for an example of how to do
that masterfully. But it is bad if it comes at the expense of depth. Here I have
the feeling that many of the introduced side-players are not ultimately relevant
to the storyline. This is not an intricate inter-woven story, but rather a
straightforward story that keeps stalling by adding side-cast and side-stories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, this should still be fairly entertaining, but it just didn&amp;#39;t make
the cut this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kaguya-sama-love-is-war-season-2&quot;&gt;Kaguya-sama: Love is War Season 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not much to add to &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-7/#kaguya-sama-love-is-war&quot;&gt;my review of season 1&lt;/a&gt;, this is still great. In fact,
I was surprised that they managed to keep the formula so fresh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I get the feeling that the people writing this are quite clever. It&amp;#39;s not easy
to balance the line between running gag (a big component of the humor) and
unexpected, funny development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Story-wise, the relationship manages to both progress and stay in the same
place, which is quite an achievement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m quite curious to see what they have in store for season 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-life-changing-magic-of-tidying-up-marie-kondo&quot;&gt;The Life-Changing Magic of Tidying Up (Marie Kondo)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22318578-the-life-changing-magic-of-tidying-up&quot;&gt;super famous book&lt;/a&gt; on a tidying method that famously
preaches getting rid of anything that &amp;quot;does not spark joy&amp;quot;. It even spawned a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WvyeapVBLWY&quot;&gt;Netflix series&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m pretty organized, and also pretty sympathetic with what I&amp;#39;d heard about it.
But the real reason I read it is because my girlfriend is a fan. I didn&amp;#39;t
actually &lt;em&gt;read&lt;/em&gt; it. I listened to the Audiobook. It&amp;#39;s fairly short: about 4.5hrs
— less if you speed it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d actually read quite a few things about this a few years ago, most notably
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raptitude.com/2015/07/out-of-sight/&quot;&gt;this nice article&lt;/a&gt;, but I also perused some summaries you can
find on the net, such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.actionablebooks.com/en-ca/summaries/the-life-changing-magic-of-tidying-up/&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. So actually listening to the
book didn&amp;#39;t really teach me anything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which didn&amp;#39;t mean it was all that uninteresting. Marie Kondo is quite the
character. I&amp;#39;m a major nerd, but I was at time slightly creeped out by the depth
of her obsession with tidying. I also was surprised that she seemed quite
superstitions and ... pop-spiritual? I know she&amp;#39;s a Japanese woman, but that
seemed too easy of a stereotype. It&amp;#39;s not just for the sake of the original
audience either — the woman does talk to her clothes and to her house, after
all. Not my jam, but ultimately just a funny detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What the book also tries — and achieves — is selling the cleaned-up lifestyle.
Kondo goes to great length to paint a nice picture of your life in a clean,
zen-like environment, where you can enjoy a hot cup of tea (or your beverage of
choice) surrounded only by those objects you love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of advice in the book (it&amp;#39;s quite actionable), but what I
personally got out of it was a bit of motivation to sort out my stuff a bit
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;flcl&quot;&gt;FLCL&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#39;t know much about FLCL (pronounced Fooly Cooly) going in, except that it
was well regarded, and that it had &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qAE8c7NcO7Q&amp;amp;list=PL5PW5TdgaMATZV3Z3_zhsj3V-Mu6e3owr&quot;&gt;great music&lt;/a&gt; by The Pillows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was ... not what I expected. It&amp;#39;s completely crazy, opaque, and quite
incomprehensible. Ok, to be fair, you kinda follow along, it&amp;#39;s just that the
plot is not intended to really make sense, as is clearly stated during a couple
of 4th-wall breaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it&amp;#39;s entertaining, by virtue of being an unrelenting assault on the
senses. It feels like each episode is a fan edit of a whole 4-6 episodes arc
that actually makes sense into a single ultra-condensed episode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What surprised me when writing this review is how old this anime actually is.
It&amp;#39;s from 2000 - 20 years old. Yet it looks so modern. I pulled the page for
Gainax (the studio) and they published &lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/276/Mahoromatic__Automatic_Maiden&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; the year before, and
&lt;a href=&quot;https://myanimelist.net/anime/276/Mahoromatic__Automatic_Maiden&quot;&gt;that&lt;/a&gt; the year after. FLCL must really have looked like an OVNI,
it&amp;#39;s no wonder it made such a splash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It not only looks modern, but also sounds modern. At least it&amp;#39;s as out there
today as it was back then — though we probably are more accustomed to &amp;quot;out
there&amp;quot; things today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I understand why it&amp;#39;s a classic. I&amp;#39;m pretty happy to have seen it. It&amp;#39;s very
short (6 regular-sized episodes), which helps to make it go down easy. I don&amp;#39;t
think I would say it was a good anime, but it was quite an experience which I&amp;#39;m
unlikely to forget. For some, that&amp;#39;s what it means to be good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-good-place-seasons-2-3--4&quot;&gt;The Good Place Seasons 2, 3 &amp;amp; 4&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;good-place.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4/#the-good-place-season-1&quot;&gt;Season 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good place keeps entertaining! I wondered how they would keep things going
and entertaining after the big twist at the end of season 1, but they managed
brilliantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without spoiling too much, season 2 features a lot of character development for
one particular character in a way that really adds to the dynamic of our little
group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Season 3 is quite different from the previous one, as it&amp;#39;s the first one taking
place mostly on earth. It&amp;#39;s also a bit more disjointed as the original &amp;quot;plan&amp;quot;
gets disrupted midway. All in all, a good job in keeping the charm without
exhausting the concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did actually have again a pretty large gap (two months or so?) between season
2 and 3, and it was a pleasure to come back to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Season 4 was pleasant too. I felt like the start was maybe a bit weaker, but the
enjoyment is still there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show frequently engages with philosophical questions, but the end was, I
think, the most interesting stab at this in the series. In term of watching
experience, I love it. But as far as the philosophy is concerned, I hate it. Let
me discuss it being a spoiler tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;details&gt;
&lt;summary&gt;Discussion with &lt;b&gt;spoilers&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/summary&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the final arc of the good place grapples with the idea of immortality, and
eternal boredom. Basically, everyone in the real good place is bored out of
their minds. The solution the protagonists come up with is simple: let people die
for real (no afterlife), whenever they chose to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In principle, this is a good solution. I&#39;m generally pro-freedom, people
shouldn&#39;t be forced to live, especially forever (no quoting out of context: we
should make effort to keep depressive people alive here in the real world). But
also, nobody should be forced to die, and the solution leaves open the
possibility to live forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worry, however, that the philosophical message is all wrong. It says
something like &quot;life is worth living only because it ends&quot;. One of my
controversial opinion (though really, I don&#39;t think it should be) is that we
should strive to live forever, i.e. fight the disease known as aging. This &lt;a
href=&quot;https://www.nickbostrom.com/fable/dragon.html&quot;&gt;parable&lt;/a&gt; is an excellent
introduction if you&#39;re not familiar with the idea (there&#39;s also &lt;a
href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cZYNADOHhVY&quot;&gt;a narrated/illustrated
version&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just don&#39;t think that I&#39;d ever get bored if I were to live forever. The
truth is that the world moves faster than we can apprehend. There are constantly
new &lt;emph&gt;interesting&lt;/emph&gt; things happening. I&#39;m interested in so many things
that I will never have time to investigate, but worse: the mass of interesting
things grows faster than my ability to investigate them. The idea that
everything is just repeating is popular, but it&#39;s jaded cynicism. I still enjoy
learning new things about topics I&#39;m an expert in. Your favorite game is never
boring if you haven&#39;t played it in a while. The idea that super long lifetimes
would be boring is just a sad failure of the imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really think &quot;death makes life worth living&quot; is more of a cope than
anything else, because in the current state of things we are all destined to
die, and it does make us feel better to believe currently unavoidable death is
somehow meaningful. Unfortunately, this has the side-effect of generating anger
towards people fighting the good fight against aging. It shouldn&#39;t be so - aging
is the number one cause of mortality. People typically talk a big game, but it
seems to me that nobody who&#39;s not greatly in pain (mentally or physically) ever
chooses to voluntarily end their own life. If given the choice, anybody who
isn&#39;t tremendously suffering will choose to live another day, every single
day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enough about the philosophy. I said that despite this, the final arc was
great. It is, because — you guessed it — most of the characters eventually
decide to die, and the idea is executed gracefully, providing an emotional
payload that is only appropriate for the season finale. I don&#39;t think I can say
much more than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/details&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;rezero-season-2-part-1&quot;&gt;Re:Zero Season 2 (Part 1)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;https://norswap.com/even-more-anime/#rezero&quot;&gt;Season 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had big expectations ... and it&amp;#39;s too early to tell if they will be met or
not. Season 3 certainly kicks off fast &amp;amp; hard, and difficulties and mysteries
keep piling on ... and on ... and on. What&amp;#39;s going on?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Past what I would say is the &amp;quot;introduction&amp;quot; of the season, the arc becomes very
unusual because (1) the number of variables seemingly keep increasing all the
time, and (2) it doesn&amp;#39;t have a proper ending!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision to split the season in two parts, with the break before the arc
could find a resolution, seems very questionable to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not that the setup is bad — mostly it is excellent. It&amp;#39;s that the timing is
deplorable. The show builds up tension for 10 weeks, and then goes on hiatus for
months. Chance is we won&amp;#39;t remember all the balls that are in the air when part
2 comes around. And there are now more balls in the air than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also while the setup is excellent, it&amp;#39;s hard to offer commentary on the arc
without knowing its resolution. A crappy resolution could make the setup
worthless, while a good one will sublimate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven&amp;#39;t seen this yet, my advice would be to wait and watch it only
shortly before part 2 comes around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;deca-dence&quot;&gt;Deca-Dence&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you go into Deca-Dence blind, the second episodes yield a pretty unexpected
twist (read at your own risk).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deca-Dence is an original story (not an adaptation). Earth is now a sort of
post-apocalyptic MMORPG entertainment park for androids living in a space
station. The last humans live in the mobile fortress Deca-Dence, which they
mostly maintain, while androids log into human-looking avatars to fight the
post-apocalyptic monsters that threathen the fortress (that&amp;#39;s the
&amp;quot;entertainement&amp;quot;). But the humans are not aware of all this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly, Deca-dence is okay. The story is good but not great, so are the
characters. It&amp;#39;s above average without really shining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;m not a fan of the pseudo-chibi style used to depict the androids. I think it
might have been selected in part to reduce cost and speed up production, but it
adds nothing artistically speaking (and I just don&amp;#39;t like how it looks).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lukewarm recommendation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-god-of-high-school&quot;&gt;The God of High School&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;god-of-highschool.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This anime gets my award for worst-named anime of the year. No high school is
actually featured, and the protagonists neither look nor act like they&amp;#39;re high
school students (more like 20-somethings).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, this is really the &lt;em&gt;anime&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#39;s fault. This is actually an adaptation of a
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webtoons.com/en/challenge/kennycomics-webtoon-101/whats-webtoonmangamanhwamanhua/viewer?title_no=5956&amp;amp;episode_no=8&quot;&gt;webtoon manhwa&lt;/a&gt; of the same name, made in collaboration with CrunchyRoll, just
like &lt;a href=&quot;#tower-of-god&quot;&gt;Tower of God&lt;/a&gt;. And this time too, it&amp;#39;s one of the most popular manhwa on
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webtoons.com/en/&quot;&gt;webtoons.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s get it out of the way: the story isn&amp;#39;t really brilliant. The titular &amp;quot;Gof
of Highschool&amp;quot; is actually a free-style everything-allowed mixed-martial-arts
tournament (powered by convenient nanobots that can heal almost any wounds).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The early season is heavy on flashbacks that flesh out the personality of
the main characters and also various other secondary characters. It&amp;#39;s not
exactly subtle, but mostly it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partway, it is revealed that most of the stronger participants use &amp;quot;charyeok&amp;quot; to
draw on the power of some kinds of spirits/divinity — because eh, why the hell
not? It&amp;#39;s almost funny how everyone takes it in stride that some fighters have
basically magical powers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, God of Highschool doesn&amp;#39;t really bother to avoid straining credibility.
Surprisingly, this ends up working to its advantage. While fights start
innocuous enough, they escalate to ridiculous over-the-top mystically-powered
world-threatening WTF-inducing affairs by the end of the season. And it works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being more of a story guy, I didn&amp;#39;t expect to enjoy this so much, but enjoy it I
did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rent-a-girlfriend-kanojo-okarishimasu&quot;&gt;Rent-a-Girlfriend (Kanojo, Okarishimasu)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &amp;quot;harem&amp;quot; anime was popular this summer, but I&amp;#39;m going to give it a &amp;quot;meh&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plot is simple: main guy Kazuya uses a girlfriend-for-rental service to go
on a date with main girl Mizuhara. Accidentally they get introduced to each
other&amp;#39;s grandmothers and have to keep the pretense up to keep them happy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main problem with the show is the cast. Mizuhara is probably the best of the
lot, in a harsh-but-secretely-kind way, though there&amp;#39;s nothing incredible about
the characterization. The other girls thouh... you have a psychopath, an
&lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; overly attached girl, and a girl that appears in  a single episode
(all four being prominently featured in the OP and ED). As for Kazuya... let&amp;#39;s
just say he makes Shinji &amp;quot;just get into the robot&amp;quot; from &lt;a href=&quot;/every-anime/#neon-genesis-evangelion&quot;&gt;Evangelion&lt;/a&gt; look like a
paragon of bravery and poise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the character designs are pretty cool. But still meh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hunter-x-hunter-2011-14-episodes&quot;&gt;Hunter x Hunter 2011 (14 episodes)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I watched the start of this show on a couple recommendations, but I&amp;#39;m conflicted
about it. It&amp;#39;s a sympathetic show, but it hasn&amp;#39;t given too much reason to care
so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What surprised me most about it is that the anime came out in 2011. It feels
more like a Pokemon-era anime, or even Dragon Ball-era. This can probably be
explained by the fact that it&amp;#39;s an adaptaiton of a 1998 manga, and also the
reboot of a 1999 anime series. I&amp;#39;m wondering if it would have been possible to
impart a slightly more &amp;quot;modern&amp;quot; flair to the series (not that the vintage style
detracts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main issue I have with the series so far is that it&amp;#39;s quite slow. It&amp;#39;s not
&lt;em&gt;quite&lt;/em&gt; filler, but there are quite a few episodes that could be easily
compressed to half the time without losing much. It&amp;#39;s not so much about useless
plot as about timing — scenes just seem to linger a bit (or for some, a lot)
longer than they should.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve also been told the first arc is not the best, so I might give it another
shot, but I think I&amp;#39;ll give some other animes a chance in the meantime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kuragehime-princess-jellyfish&quot;&gt;Kuragehime (Princess Jellyfish)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;kuragehime.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of my girlfriend Sasha&amp;#39;s favorite anime. And what can I say, the
lady&amp;#39;s got good taste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I struggle to explain why this is good. It&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Josei_manga&quot;&gt;josei&lt;/a&gt;, so admittedly not the
genre I&amp;#39;m the most familiar with. I think mostly it comes done to great loveable
dorky characters, and impeccable timing that never leaves you bored nor makes
you feel hurried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show is about a sisterhood of major lady nerds (each nerding on a very
specific topic). Things are shaken up a little bit when a stylish lady enters
their lives and the future of their shared housing is threatened. The story is a
solid driver, but isn&amp;#39;t going to have you gripping the edge of your seat. Again,
you&amp;#39;re going to be watching this for the characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one short season (11 episodes), forming an incomplete adaptation of a
longer manga series. It stops at a logical place, but quite clearly the story is
far from over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;tenet&quot;&gt;Tenet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve enjoyed all of Nolan&amp;#39;s films that I&amp;#39;ve seen, and this one was no exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many of Nolan&amp;#39;s film, it features a complicated time structure. This time
dealing with actual time travel — sort of. If you really liked the idea of
Inception, you might feel at home here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s tackle the elephant in the room: the movie will hurt your brain. The
time-travelling mechanism presented is not intuitive and has a lot of fun but
finicky implications. This is definitely the most complex time-travel movie I&amp;#39;ve
seen, maybe tying with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Primer_(film)&quot;&gt;Primer&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually enjoy these kind of movies. At least if I&amp;#39;m able to figure out most
of it, or if it&amp;#39;s explained at some point. I managed to follow the plot pretty
well, and fortunately, because what transpires in the most intricate scenes is
never laid out explicitly. The movie never stops to do a play-by-play of what
transpired, and the criticism I&amp;#39;ve heard is that it left some people stranded
during the viewing. Fortunately, the movie is still enjoyable as-is (you can
still follow), but if you want pure actions, there are better flicks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So all in all, a unique viewing experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;skeleton-soldier-couldnt-defend-the-dungeon-up-to-chapter-109&quot;&gt;Skeleton Soldier Couldn&amp;#39;t Defend The Dungeon (up to chapter 109)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;skeleton-soldier.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Skeleton Soldier (for short) is a another &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webtoons.com/en/challenge/kennycomics-webtoon-101/whats-webtoonmangamanhwamanhua/viewer?title_no=5956&amp;amp;episode_no=8&quot;&gt;webtoon manhwa&lt;/a&gt; I&amp;#39;ve been devouring
one month or two ago, catching up to the current state of publication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s about... a skeleton soldier, that dies, but is reborn. Except this time,
he&amp;#39;s some sort of RPG protagonist in his own world. He can level and acquire
abilities. If he dies, he travels back in time to start again, but keeping his
level and abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s an interesting premise, and the webtoon does it justice by introducing
interesting characters that kriss-kross through the skeleton&amp;#39;s multiple
lifetimes, and setting up engaging mysteries about the universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fact that skeleton can die is a big plus story-wise. Even though death is
merely a setback, the skeleton is invested in his &amp;quot;lifetime&amp;quot;, typically building
relationships with other characters who will forget all about him if he dies.
He&amp;#39;s also typically trying to achieve something. The hero actually being able to
die and be meaningfully set back does avoid the &amp;quot;plot armor&amp;quot; problem where the
hero always succeeds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for having a skeleton as a main protagonist, that&amp;#39;s also an interesting
choice. It&amp;#39;s ultimately not a huge deal (this would have worked just as well
with a human), but it&amp;#39;s an interesting twist that the story does exploit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The premise and setting bears a lot of resemblance to &lt;a href=&quot;https://levelingsolo.com/&quot;&gt;Solo Leveling&lt;/a&gt;, a webtoon
I&amp;#39;m currently reading (review next time, probably). I&amp;#39;d say that from what I
have read so far (~ 70 chapters), Skeleton Soldier has the more interesting and
intricate story. Solo leveling being very enjoyable still.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Very recommended if you&amp;#39;re into RPG, isekai or action manga/manhwa at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rick--morty-season-1--2&quot;&gt;Rick &amp;amp; Morty (Season 1 &amp;amp; 2)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I&amp;#39;m giving the phenomenon a shot, watching it with Sasha (it&amp;#39;s a
rewatch for her).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s good. It&amp;#39;s weird. It&amp;#39;s definitely somewhat unique. I&amp;#39;m not sure it hypes me
up incredibly however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem might be the episodic nature. I like stories, and most episodes
don&amp;#39;t really move the story or the characters forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show is notoriously absurd or over-the-top sometimes, and while it&amp;#39;s not
something I generally enjoy, it works okay here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, what I liked the most so far were the really dark moments, where
characters hit rock bottom (in a way that is not just implied to be funny and
temporary) and have to live with the consequence of their actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Episode 6 of season 1 is the best example of that, and is my favorite Rick &amp;amp;
Morty moment by far. Season 2 also built something like that, but it&amp;#39;s up to
season 3 what to make of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The humor is okay by me, but if I were in for the laughs, I&amp;#39;d rather watch
Brooklyn 99 or The IT Crowd or How I Met Your Mother.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder about the popularity of this. Is it for others like it is for me, that
the enjoyable but light nature of the show, punctuated by unexpected gut punches
that makes it memorable?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-boys-season-1--2&quot;&gt;The Boys (Season 1 &amp;amp; 2)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;the-boys.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, a show gave me a reason to check out that Prime video I have since
forever!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this show, superheroes are real, and they&amp;#39;re a big business. In addition to
being a contractor police force, the whole Marvel-style
cinema/comics/merchandising complex is in full swing. All the big names are
being managed by a megacorp called Vought. Unfortunately, not all superheroes
are as nice as it seems, and many are assholes and downright psychopaths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The destiny of the main protagonist is changed when his girlfriend is caught in
an &amp;quot;accident&amp;quot; involving a superhero, and a man called Butcher offers his help to
take down the responsible superhero.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to be remarked about the show is how it situates itself in the
zeitgeist. It has Marvel-style hero mania, sexual harrassment scandals,
marketing-driven diversity, social justice, political polarization, christian
fundamentalists, using terrorism as an excuse to do nefarious shit, and even
meme-based opinion campaigns. And mostly, the show makes it work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show is adopted from a comic book, but from what I&amp;#39;ve read, it takes a lot
of liberty with the original material — I think its situation within the
zeitgeist is an example of that. The original comic started publishing in 2006,
two full years before the first Iron Man movie (arguably the first modern MCU
movie).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first season was my favourite of the two. The story is more straightforward.
The second season ... I have mixed feelings about. Well, it was very good, and
very enjoyable to watch. Some small elements felt off, however. In particular,
it felt that sometimes &amp;quot;world-level&amp;quot; happenings are being pushed to drive the
plot forward in a way that is unsubtle, and not particulary credible — typically
involving fickle public opinion. Some choices were questionable to me. Did the
plot really need to involve &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; nazis (not neo-nazis, but 1940s nazis)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the second season also pulls no punches. The third episode could
basically have been a season finale, and it gets crazier after that. I thought
the ending was a bit of a cope (an easy way out, if you will), but eh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Shoutout to Karl Urban, whose Butcher is fantastic. And shoutout to the writers
for making Hughie not too annoying. After watching the first episode, I expected
him to be a painful drag of a protagonist, but the writers dosed his reticence
just right, so this didn&amp;#39;t happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What else? Anti-heroes, obviously, in a very literal sense. Morally gray, as
they are not always entirely morally upstanding. Butcher, in particular, has to
deal with his demons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well worth watching, feels very fresh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;dorohedoro&quot;&gt;Dorohedoro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;dorohedoro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dorohedoro takes place in some sort of slum called &amp;quot;the hole&amp;quot; that is connected
to a magical realm. Sorcerers regularly come out to &amp;quot;practice&amp;quot; (which mostly
involves transforming, killing and mangling innocent holes denizen). The
protagonist Caiman lost all his memories and his head was changed to that of a
reptilian, presumably due to such an encounter. Together with his cook friend
Nikaido, he tries to reclaim his memory and original form. Doing so, he&amp;#39;ll face
against a gang of magicians including a dude that turns everything into
mushroom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dorohedoro is kinda crazy, but in a good way. I liked the humor and the action,
and for a universe that is so non-sensical, the world-building is suprisingly
solid. The story is solid, with clues to the main mystery being given
throughout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also greatly appreciated that the anime dumps you in its universe, giving you
information as necessary instead of doing tedious information dumps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only regret is that after the 13 episodes first season, it feels like we have
barely scratched the main story, and a second season hasn&amp;#39;t been confirmed (yet?).&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-11-13T23:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/reviews-8</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/reviews-8</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chosen Tidbits 5</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-1/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-2/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-3/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-4/&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1189756911677104128&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1189756911677104128&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mediocre magic beats optimal greatness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mediocre peasant with shabbily constructed crossbow pwned legendary
warrior-knight with one dumb shot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/11/21/the-categories-were-made-for-man-not-man-for-the-categories/&quot;&gt;The Categories Were Made For Man, Not Man For The Categories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This cannot be summarized in full, but it is a joy to read, and comes with an
important lesson for your arguments and debates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the key takeaway, and a taste:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a series of disputes on categories, which are really disputes on the
definition of the category. (Is a whale a fish? Is gender dysphoria a mental
illness?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, multiple definitions often makes sense. The key being to pick the
right one for the task at hand. An alternative categorization system is not an
error. You draw category boundaries in specific ways to capture tradeoffs you
care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The (controversial) hair dryer incident:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one obsessive compulsive woman would drive to work every morning and
worry she had left the hair dryer on and it was going to burn down her house.
So she’d drive back home to check that the hair dryer was off, then drive back
to work, then worry that maybe she hadn’t really checked well enough, then
drive back, and so on ten or twenty times a day [...] to the point where her
career was in a downspin and she thought she would have to quit and go on
disability. [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She’d seen countless psychiatrists, psychologists, and counselors, she’d
done all sorts of therapy, she’d taken every medication in the book, and none of
them had helped. [...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So she came to my hospital and was seen by a colleague of mine, who told her
“Hey, have you thought about just bringing the hair dryer with you?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Musashi is quoted as saying:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The primary thing when you take a sword in your hands is your intention to cut
the enemy, whatever the means. Whenever you parry, hit, spring, strike or touch
the enemy’s cutting sword, you must cut the enemy in the same movement. It is
essential to attain this. If you think only of hitting, springing, striking or
touching the enemy, you will not be able actually to cut him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the primary thing in psychiatry is to help the patient, whatever the
means. Someone can concern-troll that the hair dryer technique leaves
something to be desired in that it might have prevented the patient from
seeking a more thorough cure that would prevent her from having to bring the
hair dryer with her. But compared to the alternative of “nothing else works”
it seems clearly superior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tynan.com/regret&quot;&gt;http://tynan.com/regret&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To minimize regret, act without hesitation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/patio11/status/1195563505983746055&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/patio11/status/1195563505983746055&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is a high status and uncontroversial belief to say that writing makes you
better at substantially everything white collar people do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is more controversial to believe being able to code makes you more effective
at everything white collar people do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Exploit until the market corrects” is one of my preferred ways to deal with
sustained disagreements. I am told this is intellectually bankrupt. I therefore
commit to exploiting it until the market corrects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1191665750391394304?s=09&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1191665750391394304?s=09&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;men want sex but don&amp;#39;t know how to be sexy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the internet has made it so easy to know what women find sexy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which suggests to me that many (most?) dudes are either too stupid or lazy (or
scared?) to do what it takes to get what they want&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and also, probably, that many (most?) don&amp;#39;t really want what they say they want&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;things I’ve known women to find disarmingly sexy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;a man cooking, doing DIY, working on his car/guitar, working with his hands&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;being skilled+charming with a child or elder person in a strong, masculine way&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;smiling and laughing when she expected him to get upset/angry&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things that are unsexy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;nitpicking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“debating”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;condescension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;contempt&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“you can have this precious penis if you pass these following tests and jump through the following hoops”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;neediness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;solipsism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;insecurity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lack of imagination&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inability to read subtext&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.calnewport.com/blog/2011/11/11/if-youre-busy-youre-doing-something-wrong-the-surprisingly-relaxed-lives-of-elite-achievers/&quot;&gt;If You’re Busy, You’re Doing Something Wrong: The Surprisingly Relaxed Lives of Elite Achievers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time diaries revealed that both groups (elite and average players) spent, on
average, the same number of hours on music per week (around 50).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elite players were spending almost three times more hours than the average
players on deliberate practice — the uncomfortable, methodical work of
stretching your ability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The average players, they discovered, spread their work throughout the day. The
elite players, by contrast, consolidated their work into two well-defined
periods (two peaks: in the morning and in the afternoon).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The elite players slept an hour more per night than the average players. The
elite players were significantly more relaxed than the average players.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hard work (delibrate practice) vs hard to do work (draining, busy).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution suggested by this research, as well as my own, is as simple as it
is startling: Do less. But do what you do with complete and hard focus. Then
when you’re done be done, and go enjoy the rest of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sivers.org/book/Overachievement&quot;&gt;https://sivers.org/book/Overachievement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Performance coach, with a bent towards sports, surgery, and executive
performance, gives his thoughts on being a top performer. The key is the
&amp;quot;Trusting Mindset&amp;quot;: like a squirrel runs across a telephone wire. Just doing it,
without thought, because you&amp;#39;ve trained yourself plenty until that point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best in every business do what they have learned to do without questioning
their abilities — they flat out trust their skills, which is why we call this
high-performance state of mind the “Trusting Mindset.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You cannot pull up all those years of education, training, and experience in
your memory as you perform — that’s the “Training” Mindset. In the Trusting
Mindset, you have to let all that expertise be there instinctively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different, in fact, as you and a squirrel running across a telephone wire!
Squirrels cannot think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Put a two-by-four board on the floor and walk from one end to the other. It is
not hard. Not one of my students has ever fallen off the board. If you videotape
yourself doing this exercise, you will see that your foot hits the middle of the
board every step of the way, as if you were walking down the street. Your eyes
just look past the board at the far end, to where you’re going, and your feet
just move. Now suspend that board thirty feet in the air and walk from one end
to the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success depends on emptying your head rather than filling it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I actually have recommended to some clients to create even more chaos at work
so that getting any work done at all will force them to be in the present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplify and narrow what you think about: Just go out target shooting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sivers.org/book/PeakPerformance&quot;&gt;https://sivers.org/book/PeakPerformance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Periodization: Balance the right amount of stress with the right amount of
rest. Stress + rest = growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don’t multitask. Ever. Compartmentalize your day down to the hour. Each
compartment has a concrete objective. Be fully intentional with how you spend
your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Walking tends to be more effective at fostering creativity than other
movements that require greater focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being in nature, or even just looking at pictures of nature, helps with the
transition from stress to rest and promotes creative thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sivers.org/book/TalentCode&quot;&gt;https://sivers.org/book/TalentCode&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Group A studied the paper for four sessions.
Group B studied only once but was tested three times.
A week later both groups were tested, and Group B scored 50 percent higher than Group A.
They&amp;#39;d studied one-fourth as much yet learned far more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Capture failure and turn it into skill. The trick is to choose a goal just
beyond your present abilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more we fire a particular circuit, the more myelin optimizes that circuit,
and the stronger, faster, and more fluent our movements and thoughts become. The
best way to build a good circuit is to fire it, attend to mistakes, then fire it
again, over and over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How the human cardiovascular system actually works: that we can improve it by
targeting our aerobic or anaerobic systems, that we can strengthen our heart
and muscles by pushing ourselves to operate at the outer edges of our
ability - lifting a slightly heavier weight, or trying to run a slightly
farther distance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sivers.org/book/Peak&quot;&gt;https://sivers.org/book/Peak&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gaining expertise is largely a matter of improving one’s mental processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If improvement is to occur, performances must not be automatic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Purposeful practice requires getting out of one’s comfort zone. This is perhaps
the most important part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://paulgraham.com/genius.html&quot;&gt;http://paulgraham.com/genius.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone knows that to do great work you need both natural ability and
determination. But there&amp;#39;s a third ingredient that&amp;#39;s not as well understood:
an obsessive interest in a particular topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you look at the lives of people who&amp;#39;ve done great work, you see a
consistent pattern. They often begin with a bus ticket collector&amp;#39;s obsessive
interest in something that would have seemed pointless to most of their
contemporaries. One of the most striking features of Darwin&amp;#39;s book about his
voyage on the Beagle is the sheer depth of his interest in natural history. His
curiosity seems infinite. Ditto for Ramanujan, sitting by the hour working out
on his slate what happens to series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is a difference between Ramanujan and a bus ticket collector. Series
matter, and bus tickets don&amp;#39;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s a mistake to think they were &amp;quot;laying the groundwork&amp;quot; for the discoveries
they made later. There&amp;#39;s too much intention in that metaphor. Like bus ticket
collectors, they were doing it because they liked it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I had to put the recipe for genius into one sentence, that might be it: to
have a disinterested obsession with something that matters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aren&amp;#39;t I forgetting about the other two ingredients? Less than you might
think. An obsessive interest in a topic is both a proxy for ability and a
substitute for determination. Unless you have sufficient mathematical
aptitude, you won&amp;#39;t find series interesting. And when you&amp;#39;re obsessively
interested in something, you don&amp;#39;t need as much determination: you don&amp;#39;t need
to push yourself as hard when curiosity is pulling you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are some heuristics you can use to guess whether an obsession might
be one that matters. For example, it&amp;#39;s more promising if you&amp;#39;re creating
something, rather than just consuming something someone else creates. It&amp;#39;s
more promising if something you&amp;#39;re interested in is difficult, especially if
it&amp;#39;s more difficult for other people than it is for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you can never be sure. In fact, here&amp;#39;s an interesting idea that&amp;#39;s also
rather alarming if it&amp;#39;s true: it may be that to do great work, you also have
to waste a lot of time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21615415&quot;&gt;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21615415&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My advice would be: rigorously eliminate everything from your life which doesn&amp;#39;t
fit inside your top X critical priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where X is as small as possible, and seek to cull it further by combining
equivalents and trying to identify why some &amp;#39;important&amp;#39; things might actually be
utter wastes of time in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The world generally uses a ratchet approach to conquer your attention. Use a
ratchet to take it back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fivethirtyeight.com/features/media-bubbles-arent-the-biggest-reason-were-partisans/&quot;&gt;Media Bubbles Aren’t The Biggest Reason We’re Partisans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“People have a notion from hearing about information echo chambers that most
Americans are getting news and information from a very slanted media diet,” he
told me. “Empirical evidence suggests that’s not true.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two people might see the same facts about the current impeachment investigation
but interpret that news in wildly different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1200707613526114305?s=09&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1200707613526114305?s=09&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;guy: how become good writer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;me: write 100 things&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[later]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;guy: ive written 80 things... nobody seems to care. when do people start caring?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;me: do you care?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;guy: do I care if other people-?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;me: no. do &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; care about your writing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;guy: uhhh I guess?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;me: that’s not enough&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/DctWqpGLZwTnrGdLT/tapping-out-in-two&quot;&gt;Tapping Out in Two&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I do now is say something to the effect of: &amp;quot;after this, I&amp;#39;m limiting
myself to two more replies in this thread.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has various advantages. It feels less rude. It doesn&amp;#39;t look like I&amp;#39;m
quitting because I have no reply. It helps the conversation reach a more natural
conclusion. And it also feels a lot easier to do, partly for the above reasons
and partly for the normal reasons precommitment helps me to do things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/KbCHcb8yyjAMFAAPJ/when-wishful-thinking-works&quot;&gt;When Wishful Thinking Works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But f could have multiple fixed points. Which one is right? You get to pick;
whichever fixed point you decide to believe ends up being correct, since they
are fixed points of the function determining the true probabilities from your
beliefs. Cases in which there are multiple such fixed points are cases in
which you actually can make something be true by believing it. So you may as
well believe the fixed point according to which you have the highest expected
utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://tynan.com/thekey&quot;&gt;Consistency is The Key&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most productive people I know are people who absolutely master the basics.
They know how to fill the time in the day with the most important tasks they
have, and they know how to string those days together in such a way that
they&amp;#39;re making meaningful progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important basic skill to master, without a doubt, is consistency.
Those who are able to be consistent end up with huge success, very often much
greater success than they expected or even hoped for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People in finance say that people aren&amp;#39;t able to comprehend the benefits of
compounding interest over time. Consistency in productivity creates compound
benefits which people are similarly not able to comprehend. Your starting
point doesn&amp;#39;t matter, because you can quickly scale up to your capacity once
you have a history and habit of consistency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s say you wanted to write a book. Maybe you&amp;#39;d tried and failed before. If
you commit to writing for thirty minutes every day for a month, you&amp;#39;ll write
at least 10 to 15 thousand words. Not bad. Then the next month you up your
quota to just one hour. Now you have a cumulative 30 to 45 thousand words. Not
quite a book yet, but you&amp;#39;re a month away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And how easy does that process sound? Anyone can do half an hour a day. Anyone
who has done a half hour a day for a month can do an hour a day. And anyone
who has done an hour a day can do another month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, it doesn&amp;#39;t seem to matter what you choose to be consistent on
or how easy or difficult it is. I&amp;#39;ve experimented a lot with this, and even
the easiest tasks lead to a positive spiral of consistency. I&amp;#39;ve found that as
soon as I get a coaching client to be consistent with any tasks relevant to
their lives, they will generally remain consistent forever, with a few
variances here and there&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sebastianmarshall.com/vita-brevis&quot;&gt;http://sebastianmarshall.com/vita-brevis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vīta brevis,
ars longa,
occāsiō praeceps,
experīmentum perīculōsum,
iūdicium difficile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or in English —&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Life is short,
and art long,
opportunity fleeting,
experimentations perilous,
and judgment difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hotelconcierge.tumblr.com/post/113360634364/the-stanford-marshmallow-prison-experiment&quot;&gt;The Standford Marshmallow Experiment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not convinced that the Stanford Marshmallow Experiment tests for anything
even remotely resembling “innate willpower,” because waiting fifteen minutes
for a single marshmallow is a stupid thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The experiment could have lacked any tangible reward and some kids
still would have waited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a type of joke that I think of as the “white people” joke, although
it’s rarely funny and it doesn’t have to be about someone who’s white. The
joke is about a mid-40’s housewife who is way too well-educated and bored to
be a housewife, and so she tries to find the Grail of healthy food (organic,
GMO-free, low acidity, one diet after another) and she plants a garden, and
she adopts pets, and she joins nonprofits, and she joins the school board, and
she reads every novel on NPR’s end of the year list, and she gets weekly
therapy and monthly massages (to about the same effect), and she meditates on
the present, and she achieves peace with the past, and she contemplates the
future, and everything is feng shui, and yet, despite all this, she feels
restless, anxious, unhappy, and she dreams of some sort of vacation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or sometimes the joke is about an elderly businessman on his second hair
transplant and third cardiac stent and twenty-billionth dollar, and his kids
all have grandkids and his wife is deceased, and when he goes out he he orders
scotch more expensive than houses, but that isn’t too often—he’s seen enough
parties, he’s seen enough people, he has no strong affections, and he works
round the clock fighting tooth-and-nail for his billions, because he’s not
sure what else, exactly, he’s supposed to be doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or the joke is about a magazine-cover movie actress who has the adoration of
thousands and still feels worthless. Or the joke is about a virginal computer
science genius who has deleted his OKCupid and decided to eschew all noncoding
activities. Or the joke is about a millionaire athlete under investigation for
using anabolic steroids. Or the joke is about a 50-something cardiologist who
hates all his patients but knows that he’d hate being retired even more. Or
the joke is about a young power couple who like each other very much, love,
maybe, but they’re both distracted by the nagging feeling that they could do
better, that they should be shooting for something greater, and so they break
up and find new partners and the process repeats again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the joke, which you hear on forums or sitcoms or in crowded sports bars,
goes: “Haha, even though these people are successful, they’re still
dissatisfied.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I’m here to tell you that this joke is totally backwards. It’s because
these people have always been dissatisfied that they achieved success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This study implies that socially prescribed perfectionism is maladaptive and
self oriented perfectionism is adaptive, but it has the causality backwards. If
you ace a difficult O-chem test, do you want to believe that this was the result
of your übermensch willpower or “big surprise, my parents have been pushing me
for years”? Inversely, if you just failed an O-chem test, it’s much preferable
to think “My family thinks I’m a failure. They’re so unfair,” instead of “I’m a
loser.&amp;quot; This is Psych 101:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being intrinsically motivated doesn’t make you successful. Feeling successful
makes you intrinsically motivated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/vgr/status/1205320897495625729&quot;&gt;100 Candid Political Opinions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;30&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Cat people make for better political leaders but dog people are more
electable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;42&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Georgism is a good idea that Homo sapiens is not an enlightened enough
species to put into practice&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;85&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The financial/investment world has no clue what&amp;#39;s going on, is afraid of
everything, and has been largely reduced to One Weird Trick: financialization.
The One Weird Trick is increasingly being executed by minds that have already
retreated to New Zealand bunkers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;90&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most bad politics arises out of bad literary tastes, as in enjoying stories
about stereotypes. Good politics arises out of pattern matching archetypes while
they still have &amp;quot;alpha&amp;quot; (predictive power) with a tasteful literary sensibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;91&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stereotypes are real, and there is always a subset of every stereotyped
population that actually willingly conforms to that stereotype, performing it
with an aggressive deadness. These dead player zombies are the core of all
politics. All politics is about seeing dead people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;93&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Zizek is correct. The Normie ideology is cynicism, and conversely, all
ideology turns into cynicism by the time it goes normie. This is why Noble Lie
political philosophy is bs because there is no unawakened consciousness laboring
under from it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol start=&quot;97&quot;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You have no obligation to be useful or interesting to the world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/TheAnnaGat/status/1206922953729957888?s=09&quot;&gt;https://twitter.com/TheAnnaGat/status/1206922953729957888?s=09&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No person would ever create anything unless they&amp;#39;re bored, scared or horny out
of their mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#39;t dampen it in people, don&amp;#39;t make it all &lt;em&gt;mindful&lt;/em&gt;; you will lose that
too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-08-14T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-5</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-5</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chosen Tidbits 4</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-1/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-2/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/chosen-tidbits-3/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/DoPo4PDjgSySquHX8/heads-i-win-tails-never-heard-of-her-or-selective-reporting&quot;&gt;Heads I Win, Tails?—Never Heard of Her; Or, Selective Reporting and the Tragedy
of the Green Rationalists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reliability of the Bayesian belief-updating process depends entirely on how
facts are being reported. If someone distorts the reporting, it won&amp;#39;t work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within your faction you are disincentivized to report things that are coded to
the other faction. So Bayesian updating becomes broken unless you take this
distortion into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2016/06/the-mind-of-donald-trump/480771/&quot;&gt;The Mind of Donald Trump&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than even Ronald Reagan, Trump seems supremely cognizant of the fact that
he is always acting. He moves through life like a man who knows he is always
being observed. If all human beings are, by their very nature, social actors,
then Donald Trump seems to be more so—superhuman, in this one primal sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Trump, the concept of “the deal” represents what psychologists call a
personal schema — a way of knowing the world that permeates his thoughts.
Cognitive-science research suggests that people rely on personal schemata to
process new social information efficiently and effectively. By their very
nature, however, schemata narrow a person’s focus to a few well-worn approaches
that may have worked in the past, but may not necessarily bend to accommodate
changing circumstances. A key to successful decision making is knowing what your
schemata are, so that you can change them when you need to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like all of us, presidents create in their minds personal life stories—or what
psychologists call narrative identities—to explain how they came to be who they
are. This process is often unconscious, involving the selective reinterpretation
of the past and imagination of the future. A growing body of research in
personality, developmental, and social psychology demonstrates that a life story
provides adults with a sense of coherence, purpose, and continuity over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trump has never forgotten the lesson he learned from his father and from his
teachers at the academy: The world is a dangerous place. You have to be ready to
fight. The same lesson was reinforced in the greatest tragedy that Trump has
heretofore known—the death of his older brother at age 43. Freddy Trump was
never able to thrive in the competitive environment that his father created.
Described by Blair in The Trumps as “too much the sweet lightweight, a mawkish
but lovable loser,” Freddy failed to impress his father in the family business
and eventually became an airline pilot. Alcoholism contributed to his early
death. Donald, who doesn’t drink, loved his brother and grieved when he died.
“Freddy just wasn’t a killer,” he concluded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://theoryengine.org/mental-health/book-review-impro-by-keith-johnstone/&quot;&gt;Book Review: Impro by Keith Johnstone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Play-acting to avoid failure:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students will arrive with many techniques for avoiding the pain of failure. John
Holt’s ‘How Children Fail’ (Penguin, 1969, Pitman, 1970) gives examples of
children learning to get round problems, rather than learning to find solutions
to problems. If you screw your face up and bite on your pencil to show you’re
‘trying’, the teacher may write out the answer for you... I explain to the
students the devices they’re using to avoid tackling the problems – however easy
the problems are – and the release of tension is often amazing…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This realisation that as adults we are avoiding problems by play-acting “please
be nice to me” signals, signals we learned as children to please overworked
teachers, that are a pointless distraction from actually doing something seems
an excellent insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On status:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Johnstone came up with the idea of Status when finding a problem with his
actors in the studio – ordinary conversations on the stage seemed to be
incredibly dull and lifeless. At one point while watching another play, he was
inspired to think of strong or weak motivations for characters to do things,
and eventually asked his actors to try to seem very slightly higher or lower
in status than their partner. This method transformed the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people understand status very intuitively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just tricks to get students to experience status changes. If I speak
with a still head, then I’ll do many other high-status things quite
automatically. I’ll speak in complete sentences, I’ll hold eye contact. I’ll
move more smoothly, and occupy more ’space’. If I talk with my toes pointing
inwards I’m more likely to give a hesitant little ‘er’ before each sentence,
and I’ll smile with my teeth covering my bottom lip, and I’ll sound a little
breathless and so on. We were amazed to find that apparently unrelated things
could so strongly influence each other; it didn’t seem reasonable that the
position of the feet could influence sentence structure and eye contact, but
it is so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But sometimes it&amp;#39;s not so intuitive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As soon as I introduced status work at the Studio, we found that people play
one status while convinced that they are playing the opposite. This obviously
makes for very bad social meshing… and many of us had to revise out whole idea
of ourselves. In my own case I was astounded to find that when I thought I was
being friendly, I was actually being hostile! If some had said ‘I like your
play’, I would have said ‘Oh, it’s not up to much’, perceiving myself as
‘charmingly modest’. In reality I would have been implying that my admirer had
bad taste. I experience the opposite situation when people come up, looking
friendly and supportive and say, ‘We did enjoy the end of Act One’, leaving me
to wonder what was wrong with the rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is that the best ideas are often psychotic, obscene and unoriginal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/visakanv/status/1149362892157775874?s=09&quot;&gt;Visakanv on Friendship&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possibly the most important thing in a friendship - including one with
yourself, or your spouse, or your child - is attention. Deep, focused,
undivided, non-judgemental attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To really see + hear the other person, in a world where people constantly feel
unseen &amp;amp; unheard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.takimag.com/article/the-great-awokening-conspiracy-theory/&quot;&gt;The Great Awokening Conspiracy
Theory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conspiracy theory is that the emergence of a socialist protest movement
three years after the economic collapse of 2008 terrified the rich. But they
noticed that Occupy was easily distracted from its class warfare by its urge
to indulge the perpetually wounded feelings of the “progressive stack.” The
more intersectional Pokémon Points that would-be speakers possess, the more
likely they are chosen to orate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rich white guys, who aren’t dumb, would have quickly figured out that their
biggest worry is not-rich white guys. In contrast, privileging more
intersectional personalities, such as black women, tended to get leftists
sidetracked from discussing confiscatory taxes into passionate diatribes about
how white Beckys were dissing their Afros.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This theory that Woke Capital cynically conspired to divide and conquer
economic leftism by promoting the Great Awokening sounds plausible enough.
Certainly, Bernie Sanders feels that now-fashionable notions like reparations
and open borders are millstones around the necks of any Democrats’ seriously
hoping to stick it to the billionaires.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/csallen/status/1189244690840932352?s=09&quot;&gt;Tweet by Courtland Allen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Underrated: The ability to steal the essence of what makes something else work
well, without also copying the superficial idiosyncratic details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/2019/10/30/new-atheism-the-godlessness-that-failed/&quot;&gt;New Atheism: The Godlessness That
Failed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Atheism was a failed hamartiology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hamartiology” is a subfield of theology dealing with the study of sin, in
particular, how sin enters the universe. Orthodox Christian hamartiology says we
all have original sin because Adam and Eve ate the apple. Gnostic hamartiologies
say we sin because we are ignorant of our true nature as celestial beings. Some
heretical hamartiologies say that all of this is irrelevant, and we sin because
we choose to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most movement atheists weren’t in it for the religion. They were in it for the
hamartiology. Once they got the message that the culture-at-large had settled on
a different, better hamartiology, there was no psychological impediment to
switching over. We woke up one morning and the atheist bloggers had all quietly
became social justice bloggers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it took its first baby steps, the Blue Tribe started asking itself “Who am I?
What defines me?”, trying to figure out how it conceived of itself. New Atheism
had an answer – “You are the people who aren’t blinded by fundamentalism” – and
for a while the tribe toyed with accepting it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Bush administration, with all its struggles over Radical Islam and
Intelligent Design and Faith-Based Charity, this seemed like it might be a
reasonable answer. The atheist movement and the network of
journalists/academics/pundits/operatives who made up the tribe’s core started
drifting closer together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gradually the Blue Tribe got a little bit more self-awareness and realized this
was not a great idea. Their coalition contained too many Catholic Latinos, too
many Muslim Arabs, too many Baptist African-Americans. Remember that in 2008,
“what if all the Hispanic people end up going Republican?” was considered a
major and plausible concern. It became somewhat less amenable to New Atheism’s
answer to its identity question – but absent a better one, the New Atheists
continued to wield some social power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Betweem 2008 and 2016, two things happened. First, Barack Obama replaced George
W. Bush as president. Second, Ferguson. The Blue Tribe kept posing its same
identity question: “Who am I? What defines me?”, and now Black Lives Matter gave
them an answer they liked better “You are the people who aren’t blinded by
sexism and racism.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, it was beautiful, simple, and perfect. We were “the reality-based
community”. They were ignoring Reason and basing all of their opinions on blind
hatred and prejudice. There was nothing confusing or unsettling at all about the
situation, and we did not need to question any of our own beliefs. It was just
that some people had been brainwashed by white supremacy and an all-consuming
desire to protect their own privilege, and so they did. Sin began with the apple
tree in Eden; conservativism began with the cotton plant in Jamestown. Language
separates us from the apes; not being blinded by bigotry separates us from the
Republicans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=21376838&quot;&gt;Comment on &amp;quot;Thriving on the Technical Leadership Path&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience has been that the value of very senior technical staff is not that
they solve &amp;quot;extremely high level&amp;quot; technical problems but they are very easily
able to see how what appears to be a complex problem is isomorphic to a much
simpler, easy to solve problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difference between expert and advanced/intermediate technical staff is that
the advanced engineer has an understanding of complex solution and mistakenly
tries to apply them everywhere, so the net effect is to increase complexity. The
expert typically sees simple solutions and method of resolving complexity and
has a net effect of reducing overall system complexity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believing that the value add of experienced technical staff is to only solve
really hard problem is likely caused by having too many advanced/intermediate
people playing the role of experienced technical leads. All of the great
technical team member I worked with always make call solutions simpler and
easier to implement by knowing exactly what doesn&amp;#39;t need to be done and what is
essential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-08-03T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-4</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/chosen-tidbits-4</guid>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviews 7</title>
      <description>
&lt;p&gt;Previously: &lt;a href=&quot;/every-anime/&quot;&gt;One&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/more-anime/&quot;&gt;Two&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/even-more-anime/&quot;&gt;Three&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4&quot;&gt;Four&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-5&quot;&gt;Five&lt;/a&gt; / &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-6&quot;&gt;Six&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time, I&amp;#39;m also reviewing books!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;darwins-game&quot;&gt;Darwin&amp;#39;s Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I forgot to review this one &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-6&quot;&gt;last time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, it follows the &amp;quot;death game&amp;quot; formula: the protagonist gets sucked in a
game (via a smartphone app in this case) that gives him powers and in which
currency can be acquired by defeating (lethaly or not) other players. Of course
there&amp;#39;s a bunch of psychopaths, but also potential allies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really enjoyed it, it was pretty fun. The show is thoughtful about powers and
how to use them. Nothing incredibly, but it&amp;#39;s only an 11-episode show and it&amp;#39;s
well worth a watch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;erased-boku-dake-ga-inai-machi&quot;&gt;Erased (Boku Dake Ga Inai Machi)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really liked this one. The basic plot is that the hero is sent back to his
elementary school past, where he endeavours to prevent the murder of three kids
in his home town. These events are also connected to his present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story is really solid and there is some real mystery. The tone reminded of
&lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4/#parasyte&quot;&gt;Parasyte&lt;/a&gt; a lot: it feels &amp;quot;mature&amp;quot; - it&amp;#39;s darker than most anime, but never
edgy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Parasyte, this had the advantage to be an adaption of a finished series,
and a short one at that — the anime is only 12 episodes long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really solid recommendation from me, there is no reason not to watch this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;unsong&quot;&gt;Unsong&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, a book review! Unsong is a book you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://unsongbook.com/&quot;&gt;read for free online&lt;/a&gt;,
written by the brilliant Scott Alexander (of &lt;a href=&quot;https://slatestarcodex.com/&quot;&gt;Slate Star Codex&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#39;s fame — one of
my favorite blogs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the (wild!) plot: in 1972, instead of sending men on the moon, the Apollo
rocket crashed into the vast crystal sphere encircling the world. It turns out
it was part of the vast machinery of heaven built by archangel Uriel to slow the
divine light to a trickle, and ensure science works properly. With it cracked,
divine light enters the world once more and as some technology stop working, the
supernatural becomes possible once more. In particular, it is possible to speak
some of the names of god in order to produce spell-like effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsong is imaginative and brilliant. There are many other things introduced in
the universe besides the names of god, and their consequences are taken
seriously (though always somewhat humorously as well). For instance, there is a
whole branch of government (the titular &lt;em&gt;Unsong&lt;/em&gt;) dedicated to enforcing
copyrights on the names of god.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsong is brilliant, but it is also weird. Its lore centers around the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kabbalah&quot;&gt;Kabbalah&lt;/a&gt;, and it&amp;#39;s full of kabalistic jokes. Things like &amp;quot;this word means X
and Y and Z and so we get meanings A, B and C&amp;quot;. It&amp;#39;s clever and cute, but it
works better the first three times than the 50th time. Towards the end, I got a
bit tired of it, especially since it breaks the rythm of the descent towards the
conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unsong is really two intertwined stories of different magnitudes. On the one
hand it is the story happening in the story&amp;#39;s present in the 2010s, and on the
other hand it is the story of how the world evolved since 1972, under the
influence of the radical new conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s really hard to describe Unsong as a story I realize. I think the best thing
would be to give it a shot. If you generally like fiction that is a little weird
(e.g. Terry Pratchett, Snow Crash, ...) then I&amp;#39;d definitely recommend it. Ditto
if you tend to enjoy Scott&amp;#39;s normal writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-rise-and-fall-of-software-recipes&quot;&gt;The Rise and Fall of Software Recipes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;banana-book.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aka &lt;em&gt;the banana book&lt;/em&gt;, after the lovely fruit peel that adorns the cover.
It&amp;#39;s written by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dariusblasband.com/&quot;&gt;Darius Blasband&lt;/a&gt;, the founder of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.raincode.com/&quot;&gt;Raincode&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, from reading the book&amp;#39;s back cover, you&amp;#39;d be forgiven to think the book had
some grand thesis about &amp;quot;software recipes&amp;quot; and methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In reality, the book never really bothers to define what a software recipe is
(it does convey that it is a cookie cutter pattern to make software). Instead,
it should be taken as Darius&amp;#39;s working, tech &amp;amp; business, memoir.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that sense, I think the book works relatively well. Darius describes himself
as a &amp;quot;codeaholic&amp;quot;, and he is definitely a compiler geek — which also happens to
be my case. As such many chapters of the book where of particular interest to
me. That being said, they remain accessible enough that any semi-competent
programmer should be able to understand the subject matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sometimes disagreed with Darius, and often wanted to add more nuance, but his
opinions never struck me as wrong-headed. There&amp;#39;s a lot of references to
projects and experiences on the ground that help to lend weight to some of his
points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The writing is snappy and fun enough to keep you engaged. Chapters are typically
not too long, and the books lends itself well to sporadic reading. It would
actually have made a great toilet book. That being said, don&amp;#39;t expect your mind
to be blown away either. This is a no-nonsense collection software advice,
stories and ideas. While there are definitely some nuggets of insight to glean
there, I don&amp;#39;t think this will cause anyone that wasn&amp;#39;t already on board to
reconsider their whole processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;kaguya-sama-love-is-war&quot;&gt;Kaguya-sama: Love is War&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was strongly recommended to me by my friend Gorby. And I have to admit:
it&amp;#39;s damn funny. The humor reminded me of &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4/#dumbbell-nan-kilo-moteru-how-heavy-are-the-dumbells-you-lift&quot;&gt;Dumbbell nan Kilo&lt;/a&gt;, in a good way.
Despite the silly tone, the last episode managed to have my heart in a vise.
That&amp;#39;s how you know it&amp;#39;s good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, I&amp;#39;m a sucket for that opening theme:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot;
src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/UqpdDTeHbd8&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot;
allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot;
allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That Japanese crooner really did steal my heart 😍 I also like the visuals, it
reminisced me of the better James Bond openings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-gatsu-no-lion-march-comes-in-like-a-lion&quot;&gt;3-gatsu no Lion (March Comes In Like a Lion)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3-gatsu no Lion has an excellent MyAnimeList score (8.45) and has is often
described as being great &amp;amp; artful. And I was curious to know what the fuss was
about. Well, I ended up dropping it (for the nonce at least) after 10 episodes
(out of 22 for the first season).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s not bad by any stretch of the imagination. It&amp;#39;s just... very contemplative?
Slow? I think what I&amp;#39;ve seen so far could have been conveyed in half the time,
there are very repetitive scenes. At the same time, it might have been
deliberate. The anime certainly feels deliberate, and not like it&amp;#39;s trying to
please anyone, nor give itself a genre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this is related to the subject matter, which is ... complex. It&amp;#39;s
about the state of mind of this young pro shogi player. I&amp;#39;ll paste the MAL
description:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having reached professional status in middle school, Rei Kiriyama is one of
the few elite in the world of shogi. Due to this, he faces an enormous amount
of pressure, both from the shogi community and his adoptive family. Seeking
independence from his tense home life, he moves into an apartment in Tokyo. As
a 17-year-old living on his own, Rei tends to take poor care of himself, and
his reclusive personality ostracizes him from his peers in school and at the
shogi hall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, not long after his arrival in Tokyo, Rei meets Akari, Hinata, and
Momo Kawamoto, a trio of sisters living with their grandfather who owns a
traditional wagashi shop. Akari, the oldest of the three girls, is determined
to combat Rei&amp;#39;s loneliness and poorly sustained lifestyle with motherly
hospitality. The Kawamoto sisters, coping with past tragedies, also share with
Rei a unique familial bond that he has lacked for most of his life. As he
struggles to maintain himself physically and mentally through his shogi
career, Rei must learn how to interact with others and understand his own
complex emotions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, I dropped it because I found myself dragging my feet a little to
watch it, which is not a good sign. I &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; give another chance at some point,
as I think there might be something great which I haven&amp;#39;t gotten to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mob-psycho-100-season-1&quot;&gt;Mob Psycho 100 (Season 1)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;mob-psycho-100.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I almost dropped Mob Psycho 100 after the first episode, which repeated its
&amp;quot;funny&amp;quot; shtick a bit too much, and I was unsure about the graphical style. I&amp;#39;m
glad I didn&amp;#39;t, as it turns out it&amp;#39;s quite entertaining, and you get used to the
goofiness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wouldn&amp;#39;t call it groundbreaking or anything, but it&amp;#39;s short (12 episodes) and
watchable. I don&amp;#39;t really have much more to say about it. It seems to be a very
beloved show (8.5 rating on MAL), and I can understand, the anime is not
incredible, but it is emminently sympathetic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hamefura&quot;&gt;Hamefura&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;hamefura.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Whole title &amp;quot;Otome Game no Hametsu Flag ...&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;My Next Life as a Villainess:
All Routes Lead to Doom!&amp;quot;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This anime was not at all what I expected it to be. The premise is that the
titular character gets reincarnated in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_novel&quot;&gt;visual novel&lt;/a&gt; romance game, as the
villainess character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From this premise I expected a &lt;a href=&quot;/reviews-4/#the-rising-of-the-shield-hero&quot;&gt;Shield Hero&lt;/a&gt;-like situation: the main character
being treated unfairly and having (in this case) to battle its way to
recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, spoilers: that&amp;#39;s not at all what happens. Instead this is a very wholesome
sorta-kinda-harem anime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I really really loved it. I don&amp;#39;t really know why - the story is nothing to
write home about. I&amp;#39;m guessing it&amp;#39;s the &lt;em&gt;wholesomeness&lt;/em&gt; of the whole affair that
just put me in a good mood. It reminded me a bit of what I liked about &lt;a href=&quot;/more-anime/#k-on&quot;&gt;K-On!&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;gleipnir&quot;&gt;Gleipnir&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plot-wise, Gleipnir is a sort of death game where protagonists have special
abilities. In that, it&amp;#39;s quite similar to last season&amp;#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;#darwin-s-game&quot;&gt;Darwin&amp;#39;s Game&lt;/a&gt;, but the
similarity stops there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whereas Darwin&amp;#39;s game is very focused on the strategies and combat, Gleipnir is
more about the mystery of the game&amp;#39;s existence. Well, at least it tries to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start is intriguing enough, but then the anime tramples around in its
midsection, not achieving much. The mystery plotline picks up towards the end,
just enough to keep things interesting. It&amp;#39;s not all that masterfully executed
however. They also could easily have concluded the 13 episode arc with some something
more impactful happening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was ready to give up around episode 8, then got interested enough to finish,
but I&amp;#39;m not sure I&amp;#39;ll care enough for season 2 (if they make it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;yesterday-wo-uttate&quot;&gt;Yesterday wo Uttate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started watching this show on the basis of its wistful mood. I&amp;#39;d seen a short
review of it (part of an overview of the whole season) that praised its little
philosophical sentences — but as it turned out there were relatively few of
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The show is about a sort of amorous ... rectangle (?) between two guys and two
gals. I won&amp;#39;t deny the setting and the mood is nice, but unfortunately the story
gets nowhere pretty fast. A lot of time is spent of repetitions rather than
evolution in the characters&amp;#39; relationship. The conclusion comes out of the blue,
and does not really feel satisfying, or really coherent with what transpired
before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe it can just be seen as a realistic (or more realistic than usual) take on
human relationship — with a unmistakable Japanese flair.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This feels like it could have been so much better if the story had been better
conceived though.&lt;/p&gt;
      </description>
      <pubDate>2020-08-03T22:00:00.000Z</pubDate>
      <link>http://norswap.com/reviews-7</link>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://norswap.com/reviews-7</guid>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
